<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Byte Tank - Pedro Lopes Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-22T02:33:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://lopespm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bluetooth Headphones Safety]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/22/wireless-headphones.html"/>
    <updated>2025-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/22/wireless-headphones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After nearly 4 years of continuous usage at work, taking calls and listening to audiobooks during long walks, my wired in-ear <a href="https://www.bose.co.uk/en_gb/support/products/bose_headphones_support/bose_in_ear_headphones_support/qc20.html">Bose QuietComfort 20 MK2 Active Noise Cancelling Earphones</a> are finally starting to become faulty<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, so I went on a search for a replacement.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="searching-for-replacement-wired-anc-earbuds">Searching for replacement wired ANC earbuds</h2>

<p>To my surprise, not only have these types of earphones been discontinued by Bose, but the selection of wired in-ear active noise cancelling headphones is incredibly slim. After an extensive search, I’ve found <a href="https://rog.asus.com/uk/headsets-audio/in-ear-headphone/rog-cetra-ii-model/">Asus ROG Cetra II</a> and <a href="https://www.bang-olufsen.com/en/us/earphones/beoplay-e4">Bang Olufsen B4</a>, which appear to offer inferior quality in terms of Active Noise Cancelling (ANC), when compared to recent highly rated <a href="https://www.bose.co.uk/en_gb/products/headphones/earbuds/bose-quietcomfort-earbuds-ultra.html#v=QCUE-HEADPHONEIN-WHTSM-WW">Bose</a>, <a href="https://www.sony.co.uk/headphones/gallery?filters=trulyWirelessHeadphoneFeatures%3AID_020_noise-cancelling">Sony</a> or <a href="https://www.apple.com/uk/airpods-max/">Apple</a> headphones, which are either wireless or are <a href="https://www.bose.co.uk/en_gb/products/headphones/noise_cancelling_headphones/bose-quietcomfort-headphones.html#v=QC-HEADPHONEARN-BLUDK-WW">over-ear</a> / on-ear. Quality in-ear<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> ANC earbuds are almost exclusively wireless.</p>

<h2 id="health">Health</h2>

<p>I understand the popularity of using wireless earbuds. They are extremely practical and neat. It is not surprising that <a href="https://www.kantarmedia.com/news-and-resources/rise-of-bluetooth-headphones">penetration of bluetooth headphones has jumped considerably in recent years</a>, but given that I use my headphones for several hours each day, it is not an enticing proposition to have two wireless devices extremely close to my brain, even if they output a low amount of EMF radiation. The (cumulative) dose makes the poison.</p>

<p>Several experts <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> claim there is no danger in prolonged usage of these devices, because they don’t emit ionizing radiation, but it has been reported both in <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6025786/">studies</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wireless_device_radiation_and_health#Electromagnetic_hypersensitivity">anecdotally</a> that exposure to high levels of EMF radiation <em>might</em> have detrimental effects long term.</p>

<p>I’ve found it challenging to discover quality studies that correlate the usage of bluetooth headphones and their effect on overall health. I assume that this correlation is hard to experiment upon with statistically significant results, due to how long this exposure needs to happen, and other confounding environmental and behavioural factors. Regardless, one of these <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-024-63653-0">studies draws a significant link between the usage of bluetooth headset and thyroid nodules</a>.</p>

<h2 id="unknowns-risks">Unknowns Risks</h2>

<p>We should be humble enough to acknowledge that we don’t have the full picture clearly laid out of the complete repercussions of long term usage of these devices, especially when in close proximity to one of the most valuable organs of our body, our brain.</p>

<p>It’s not what is known that concerns me, but rather what is not known. Until proven the contrary, I will continue to play it safe, and avoid using wireless earbuds.</p>

<p>Hopefully a larger swath of the population will increasingly exercise caution and awareness on this issue, signalling manufacturers to drive the supply of competitive good quality wired in-ear ANC headphones that empower the consumer to make the best choice for their use case, and their health.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>The battery is still pristine, but the left earbud started to give out a random noise when active noise cancelling is enabled.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>I’m exclusively looking for in-ear headphones because of how <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1HJs34y1u_w">challenging</a> it is to find over-ear or on-ear headphones that doesn’t cause discomfort after several hours, when using glasses. I also appreciate the style of in-ears, although that is secondary.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23619813/">Effect of Bluetooth headset and mobile phone electromagnetic fields on the human auditory nerve</a> - Marco Mandalà, Vittorio Colletti, Luca Sacchetto, Paolo Manganotti, Stefano Ramat, Alessandro Marcocci, Liliana Colletti<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBqMqLyy9HQ">Are Bluetooth Headphones Safe?</a> - Dr. Matt MacDougall &amp; Dr. Andrew Huberman<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_xOpkyt5eMY">How Unhealthy Are Your AirPods?</a> - Doctor Mike<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story of the Human Body Book: Lessons]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/10/story-human-body-lessons.html"/>
    <updated>2025-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/10/story-human-body-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently finished reading <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Story-Human-Body-Evolution-Disease/dp/030774180X">The Story of the Human Body: Evolution, Health, and Disease</a>, a book from Daniel Lieberman of how the human body evolved over millions of years, that I would recommend all Humans to read. These are are my main takeaways:</p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="why-we-are-the-way-we-are">Why we are, the way we are</h1>

<h2 id="it-is-all-about-how-energy-is-used">It is all about how energy is used</h2>

<p>Us humans and other living beings are essentially organisms that use energy to reproduce and maintain ourselves.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Natural selection prunes off organisms that don’t use energy in a way that is suited to their conditions and environment.</li>
  <li><strong>Every energy transformation feature / trait has a cost</strong>. For example: walking upright allows one to walk using less energy, but lacks the speed of a quadruped.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="long-distance-walking--running-machines">Long Distance Walking / Running Machines</h2>

<h3 id="what-drove-selection-for-bipedalism">What drove selection for bipedalism</h3>

<p>Hominid bipedalism was likely to have been initially selected to help the first hominids forage and obtain food more effectively in the face of major climate change</p>

<p>Between 10 and 5 million years ago, the earth climate cooled considerably, and overall effect in Africa that caused rainforests to shrink and woodlands to expand. If you were to be in the heart of the rainforest, you likely wouldn’t have noticed much of a difference, but if you were in the margins, this change must have been stressful. As the forest shrinks and becomes woodland, ripe fruits become less abundant, more dispersed and more seasonal. These changes would require you to travel farther to get the same amount of food.</p>

<p>Walking on two legs is more energy efficient for longer routes. Main trade off is less speed, because we could not gallop. We are 3x more efficient moving a distance of 6km than a chimp.</p>

<h3 id="the-consequences-of-bipedalism">The consequences of bipedalism</h3>

<p>Not only was endurance walking useful, but also long distance running was likely selected for scavenging. Running to fresh carcasses, running with food and, persistence hunting, where a big animal is followed  by running and walking on sun. They need to find shades and pant, and eventually collapse due to heat stroke.</p>

<ul>
  <li>We are unique in that we have sweat glands all over the body. Other apes mostly have on the palms of their hands. And we. Don’t have fur, allowing the air to come in contact with sweat and cool your body down. This is essential for long distance running and walking.
    <ul>
      <li>Other animals have fur that reflects solar radiation, but does  it allow body to cool down through sweat</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Other features that help us to run effectively. Some of them not specially helpful for walking, like shorter toes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Big gluteus maximus muscles, mostly active when running.</li>
  <li>Nuchal ligament is a back neck ligament that connects head to arm that helps stabilize the head while running. It was developed independently in humans and other animals well adapted for running.    </li>
  <li>Big semi circular inner ear canals to have more signals to allow for stabilization of our inner systems, such eye actions to compensate for the jiggle.</li>
  <li>Predominance of slow twitch fibers in legs. More endurance, thus compromising speed.</li>
  <li>Narrow waists, wide shoulders, shorter toes.</li>
  <li>Long noses are selected for walking long distances without drying up. Nose humidifies air coming into the lungs, which is necessary, and retains moisture going out. Trade-off is that lungs have to work a bit harder.</li>
</ul>

<p>All of these walking and running adaptations made us clumsy climbing trees, like shorter toes, but also freed up our hands to interact with the world, create the first tools and throw objects (we are especially good at throwing, having shoulders and upper body that makes it ideal for it), which not only provided some protection, but also allowed us to obtain and process fallback / lower quality foods (which were essential due to scarcity from global cooling climate).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Only mad dogs and Englishmen go out in the midday sun
<em>― Noël Coward</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="better-dexterity-tools-cognition-less-digestive-cost-more-energy-availability">Better dexterity, tools, cognition, less digestive cost, more energy availability</h3>

<p>In the average adult human, the brain represents about 2% of the body weight, but accounts to about 20% of total energy consumption.</p>

<p>As the ability to create and use tools allowed the gathering and processing of fallback foods, more usable energy was able to be extracted. Processing foods to smaller chunks, or cooking it, largely increases how much energy can be obtained during digestion, but also requires less intense chewing (we didn’t need as bigger teeth as australopithecus, which resulted in use losing the snout due to less space being needed in the head) and shorter intestines, which reduce energy required for digestion, increases surplus energy to be used by the brain. These factors selected hominids with better manual dexterity and better cognition.</p>

<p>Our manual dexterity, and what it unlocks, plays a big role in our evolution.</p>

<h3 id="energy-hungry-brain-and-relation-with-fat">Energy hungry brain, and relation with fat</h3>

<p>If our brain<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> is deprived of glucose for even 1 minute or two, it causes irreparable damage. This likely selected humans to become unusually fat. 400 to 500 calories daily, are for the brain alone. Extra intense thought only increases hourly usage by 5 calories per hour.</p>

<p>Hunter gatherer mothers have to expend about 2.3k calories for themselves alone to raise kids. Babies are unusually fat. 60 percent of their energy consumption is for the brain. It takes 12M calories to grow a child into a full grown adult. Twice as much as those needed for a chimpanzee.</p>

<p>Our way of living affected the size of our gut so profoundly, that now we are pretty much dependent on cooking to get the caloric intake we need for our body and brain.</p>

<p>Exercise is not great to lose fat (unless you don’t succumb to overeating after exercise) but it’s good to prevent fat gain. It increases muscle (and not fat) sensitivity to insulin and makes the muscles more readily available to store energy, and also increases the number of mitochondria that burn fat and sugar.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A lean man that doesn’t exercise has twice the risk of dying, compared to obese men that engaged in regular physical activity</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="high-offspring-investment">High offspring investment</h3>

<p>Life is fundamentally a way of using energy to make more life.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If the environment is risky: quick returns are favored, where little investment is made during life, but a lot during reproduction. Such as spiders, salmon that lay a lot of eggs, hoping that a lucky few will survive</li>
  <li>But when resources are predictable and infant mortality is low, it is feasible to mature slowly and invest a lot in raising the few offspring. This is the strategy of humans, elephants and apes.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cost-of-clear-speech-choking">Cost of clear speech: choking</h3>

<p>What good is it to have a good idea, if you can’t communicate it? One of the main features we developed as humans was our ability to use speech to clearly communicate thoughts, ideas, plans, and other information.</p>

<p>The price is that we are the only mammal that can risk asphyxiation when swallowing something too large or imprecisely<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, because of the big common space behind the tongue through which food and air both travel to get either into the esophagus or trachea, a consequence of our short and retracted faces and selection of anatomy that favors clear speech. As a result, food sometimes gets lodged on the back of the throat, blocking the airway.</p>

<p>When you are having lunch with friends, consider that you are doing two things: speaking clearly, and swallowing a little dangerously.</p>

<h1 id="diseases">Diseases</h1>

<p>We’ve created a system that makes people sick through a surplus of energy, and keeps them alive without needing to turn down the energy flow</p>

<p>Lieberman presents the concepts of Mismatch diseases and Dysevolution:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Mismatch diseases</strong>: Diseases that occur because our bodies are poorly or inadequately adapted to environments in which we now live. An example would be eating large amounts of sugar or being very physically inactive leads to problems like diabetes or heart disease that then make us sick    </li>
  <li><strong>Dysevolution</strong>: Form of cultural evolution where the symptoms of a mismatch disease are treated, but not the cause.  One example of this is cavities, which are treated with dentists, and not by removing the sugar from our diet, which is the underlying cause. Lieberman emphasizes that mismatched diseases and their causes must be understood fully to treat the true cause.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-much-energy-surplus">Too much energy surplus</h2>

<p>Our ancestors ate fruits as sweet as carrots, but as energy dense foods had their availability increased<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, more humans moved from subsistence farming and physically strenuous jobs to lower physical effort jobs (in the USA, only 11 per cent are actually factory workers. The rest are in management, services, wealth management and banking services), the same mechanisms that made us effective is storing energy and craving certain foods, are also the ones that have become maladapted to our current environment.</p>

<p>It has been only about 300 generations since we’ve been subsistence farmers, which didn’t give enough time for natural selection and body adaptations to develop.</p>

<h3 id="sugar-and-fat-absorption-mechanisms-and-effects">Sugar and fat absorption mechanisms and effects</h3>

<p>Your body can use <strong>glucose</strong> as energy readily, but <strong>fructose</strong> can only be worked as fat or in the liver.</p>

<ul>
  <li>When the liver is flooded with too much fructose, too quickly, it is overwhelmed and converts most of the fructose into fat, triglycerides. Some of this fat fills up the liver and causes inflammation, which blocks the action of insulin in the liver.    </li>
  <li>Chain reaction occurs, in that the liver releases stores of glucose into the bloodstream, driving the pancreas to release more insulin, shuttling extra glucose and fat into cells. The rest of fat created by the liver is dumped into the bloodstream, where it ends up in fat cells, your arteries, and other potentially bad places.
    <ul>
      <li>Visceral fat is more hormone sensitive than other fat cells, resulting that its stores are dumped fat more readily than other fat cells, and since it sits close to the liver, it tends to clog up the liver and constrain its glucagon function when it dumps fat.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Sugar is 50 percent fructose; fruits also have it. An apple for example has 13g of sugar. 30 percent is glucose, the rest is fructose.</li>
</ul>

<p>Comparing an apple to a highly processed fruit roll, apart from nutritional differences:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Fiber</strong> covering the apple (the skin) prevents the full absorption of sugar. Fiber makes food stay longer in the stomach, generating signals that release appetite suppressing hormones.
    <ul>
      <li>Speed of eating and amount of fiber is important. That’s why salads and low glycemic foods should come first in your meal</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>An apple gives your pancreas time to realize how much insulin to release. On the other hand, high glycemic, calorie dense foods are easily and quickly absorbed in the digestive process, prompting the pancreas to produce a lot of insulin, which it often overshoots, plunging blood sugar levels, which in turn makes us hungry.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="height-as-a-measure-of-extra-caloric-availability-and-health">Height as a measure of extra caloric availability and health</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Maximum height is constrained by genes, but available energy will limit actual height. Because if you spend most of your energy fighting diseases and toiling in the fields, then you won’t have extra calories to gain height. 
    <ul>
      <li>It was seen for populations that turned to subsistence  farming, like in Asia and America, to have had their height shortened. For example, subsistence farming children spent about 4 or 6 hours working, as compared to children of hunter gatherers that would spend about 1 to 2 hours working in tasks like gathering firewood and helping in domestic tasks.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Tall people are naturally selected in hot climates, because of higher surface area to release heat. Colder climates select for shorter ones, because they can retain more heat.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-much-stress">Too much Stress</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Stress is an ancient adaptation to save you from dangerous situations, and activates energy reserves when you need them.
    <ul>
      <li>If a Lion roars nearby, a car nearly runs you over, or if you go for a run, your brain triggers your adrenal glands (which sit on top of your kidneys), to secrete a small dosage of the hormone cortisol.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cortisol does not cause stress. It is released when you are stressed.</li>
  <li>One of cortisol’s functions is to cause liver and fat cells (specially visceral fat cells) to release glucose into the bloodstream. It increases heart rate and blood pressure, makes you more alert and prevents sleep, and makes you crave for calorie rich foods.
    <ul>
      <li>Chain reaction for long bouts of stress: as you crave more energy rich foods and consume them, this increases insulin levels, which inhibits the brain’s response to leptin (fat cells release it to increase satiety), as such, the stressed brain thinks you are starving, so activates reflexes to make you hungry and other reflexes ot make you less active.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-little-sleep">Too little Sleep</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Insufficient sleep promotes stress and stress promotes insufficient sleep. Higher income populations get on average more sleep, likely because of having of less challenges of making ends meet and less stress
    <ul>
      <li>Sleep deprivation is sometimes caused by elevated levels of stress, thus more cortisol.</li>
      <li>Sleep deprivation elevates the ghrelin hormone, a hunger hormone that stimulates appetite.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Only until recently did we do start sleeping alone or with a single partner the child detached from parents during sleep, and in stimulus deprived environments
    <ul>
      <li>On the other hand, hunter gatherers used to sleep in relatively noisy environments, woke up at about 7h, took a one hour nap in the middle of the day, and then went to sleep at 9pm, where they would get two sleeps. Likely an adaptation, that prevented predator under vigilance</li>
      <li>But now we have entertainment and lights that are able to keep us awake far beyond 9pm, in sensory deprived environments, with less exercise, excess calories, and stress</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-crowded">Too Crowded</h2>

<p>Villages, cities, are our human fortresses from the wild. Because we have that fortress, we don’t need to carry arms and be attentive to outer animal threats, like lions. Mostly. There were costs to these though:</p>

<ul>
  <li>High concentration of humans in low<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> sanitation<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> environments facilitated the spread of these diseases, and close contact with animals gave rise to diseases such as influenza, coming from pigs.</li>
  <li>Before the 1900s, the death rates in cities such as London were higher than in rural areas, so they needed a large influx of rural immigrants to keep them going. Which they did, because of a larger scope of opportunities and wealth.</li>
  <li>Cows’ digestive systems were adapted to eat grass, but in the crowded industrial complexes they are fed grains, and as a consequence they have to be constantly medicated with antibiotics, to counter their chronic diarrhea and diseases coming from these crowded, filthy environments.
    <ul>
      <li>Antibiotics given to industrially raised animals because microbes also consume energy. So this makes them fatter</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cancer">Cancer</h2>

<p>There is a <strong>positive correlation between cancer development in reproductive organs and high energy balance</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Women’s bodies adapted towards delivering as many children as possible, and are maladapted towards having a high energy balance:
    <ul>
      <li>High exposure to estrogen incentives cell division in breast, ovaries, and uterus, in preparation of a fertilized embryo. Chances to develop cancer in these organs increases substantially from the number of menstrual cycles, and decreases as the number of children the woman bears.
        <ul>
          <li>During the menstrual cycle the levels of estrogen and progesterone rise significantly</li>
          <li>While nursing, chances of having cancer go down, as there is less exposure to reproductive hormones, and likely breast feeding aids flushing memory ducts.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>For women, the incidence of breast cancer was observed to be higher in nuns (hence, the nuns disease)</li>
      <li>Women in contemporary USA have about 350-400 menstrual cycles, start menstruating at 12, 13, and then stop at early fifties
        <ul>
          <li>Hunter gatherers have about 150 cycles, and start menstruating at 16. They spent most of their life being pregnant or nursing, while barely having energy to do so.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Obese women can have 40 per cent more estrogen, because of the role of fat in the endocrine system. So after menopause being obese is correlated with cancer in women</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>For men, higher exposure to testosterone throughout their life is correlated with prostate cancer. But correlation is not as strong as in women.</li>
</ul>

<p>More exercise results in lower chances of cancer. Likely because the energy spent there is not otherwise spent on reproductive hormones that have these side effects.</p>

<ul>
  <li>There is <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC1402378/">compelling evidence</a> that routine physical activity is associated with reductions in the incidence of specific cancers, in particular breast and colon cancer. Physically active men and women exhibited a 30%–40% reduction in the relative risk of colon cancer, and physically active women a 20%–30% reduction in the relative risk of breast cancer compared with their inactive counterparts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="use-it-or-lose-it-no-strain-no-gain">Use it, or lose it; No strain, no gain</h2>

<p>Imagine you are tasked with building a robot that is aimed to accomplish a task in the future that is unknown. You can either create a series of specialized robots (e.g. only able to swim, to dig, jump, etc), or a single one that adapts to multiple situations. When you don’t know what the robot will do, the latter works best. That is how animals and plants work. But if you don’t use it, you lose it.</p>

<h3 id="bone-loss">Bone loss</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Bones are a reserve of calcium, an essential component to the body. If there is not enough calcium, osteoclasts start dissolving them at a higher rate.</li>
  <li>Most people will reach their peak bone mass between the ages of 25 and 30, then it keeps going away. Specially struts in spongy bones like vertebrae and joints. They don’t come back.    </li>
  <li>Just having a supply of calcium and vitamin D is not enough. You also need to load your bones, otherwise the osteoblasts will not kick in to start building bone.
    <ul>
      <li>High intensity weight bearing can stop or even moderately reverse some loss.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="teeth-problems">Teeth problems</h3>

<p>If you don’t chew enough when you are young, teeth will become misaligned, and overcrowding happens, leading to issues on wisdom tooth growth for example. The body needs that stress.</p>

<h2 id="allergies-and-hygiene-hypothesis">Allergies and hygiene hypothesis</h2>

<p>Hygiene hypothesis states that early childhood exposure to particular microorganisms (such as the gut flora and helminth parasites) protects against allergies by properly tuning the immune system. In particular, a lack of such exposure is thought to lead to poor immune tolerance. There are two main hypothesis for it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>First hypothesis is that T helper 1 cells are not busy enough<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, which increases the number of T helper 2 cells. With more sterilized environments, children’s immune systems are less busy, having more of these T helper 2 cells swimming unemployed, leading to a higher probability that they react to a non-threatening component. First reaction is mild, but the immune system keeps a memory, so the following time that component is detected, it’s devastating.</li>
  <li>Second hypothesis is microbiome destabilization, the “old friends” hypothesis. Microbes have evolved to cohabit with others and us in a cold war kind of environment. Once you start killing several of them with antibiotics and cleaning products, you destabilize their equilibrium
    <ul>
      <li>There is a case to be made that possible treatments would be to have fezes or filth</li>
      <li>And it also follows that after antibiotic treatments, that probiotics are taken</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="we-frequently-mistake-comfort-for-wellbeing">We frequently mistake comfort for wellbeing</h2>

<p>Hannah Arendt introduced the expression and concept of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eichmann_in_Jerusalem#Banality_of_evil">banality of evil</a>, where a common person does nefarious actions, since they became accepted and normalized in their society.</p>

<p>Actions that we perceive as normal, such as usage of cancer inducing sodium nitrate in foods (which stems for a trade-off between structural economic gain and health), wearing comfortable shoes, reading and sitting, are in fact not normal when seen through the lenses of long term evolution.</p>

<h3 id="comfortable-shoes">Comfortable shoes</h3>

<p>Our feet have adapted for us to efficiently run and walk, but highly cushioned, constraining shoes deform and inhibit our feet from fulfilling their purpose</p>

<ul>
  <li>Habitual barefoot people have much lower incidence of flat foot, which very likely is due to the high usage of the foot arch, which is restrained on comfortable shoes with arch support, which instead overload the plantar fascia, leading to plantar fasciitis</li>
  <li>A constrained toe box restrains how much stability the foot can provide, and an unbalanced foot leads to an unbalanced knee, hip, body.</li>
  <li>I’ve personally transitioned to using barefoot shoes daily and when hiking, and can only recommend them after using them for more than one year.
    <ul>
      <li>One common question is if these are appropriate on hard terrain. Turns out that your foot already has a built in mechanism, which is to forefoot / midfoot strike, instead of heel strike. Try to jump to see how your foot automatically lands using the ball of your foot, and how softly you land, when compared to a (dangerous) similar jump landing on your heel.</li>
      <li>Going barefoot or using minimal shoes, provides you full perception of the terrain and impact, so you’ll adapt towards hitting the ground more softly, and not using heel strikes as much.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>

<p>Myopia is a formerly rare evolutionary mismatch that is exacerbated by modern environments. In the USA and Europe, about one third of all children (aged 7 to 17) become nearsighted.</p>

<p>Evidence suggests that being nearsighted used to be very rare: that less than three per cent prevalence amongst hunter gatherers and populations that practices subsistence agriculture. In 1813, it was noted that amongst the Queen’s guards, many were myopic. On the hand, from the 10k foot guard, less than half dozen were myopic.</p>

<p>The mechanisms of how myopia are still not fully understood, but two main causes are suggested:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Close work, forcing long bouts of close focus. Singapore <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4041336/">study</a> found that students who read more than 2 books per week had strong myopia.</li>
  <li>Children spending <a href="https://bjo.bmj.com/content/104/5/593">more time outdoors</a> have lower incidence of myopia. Brightness of light and visual stimuli appear to have a beneficial effect.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="sitting">Sitting</h3>

<p>While sitting in different positions to rest after strenuous activity has been around for much of our species, only until recently have we been multiple hours sitting in a chair, day after day, which is a risk factor towards:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Muscle atrophy and shortening: calf muscle shortening also happens for high heels usage</li>
  <li>Lower back pain. To prevent this issue, make sure to maintain a strong back via moderate intensity load, but not too much load, like furniture movers.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="how-to-solve-these-issues">How to solve these issues</h1>

<p>One solution would be to wait for natural selection to sort out these problems, which is very unlikely due to the high rate of change in our societies and environments, in short time windows. As the commander of the Albigensian Crusade said, on a mission to eliminate heretics: <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caedite_eos._Novit_enim_Dominus_qui_sunt_eius.">“Kill them all; let God sort them out.”</a></em></p>

<p>We are all subject to influence by advertising, availability and peer pressure, but we can be nudged to acquire behaviours that benefit us. Daniel Lieberman suggests:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We should invest in prevention over treatment    </li>
  <li>Although adults have the right to get sick, children need guidance. How different is it to restrict fast foods to them, to restricting which movies they are able to attend? Or availability of alcohol to them?</li>
  <li>Just like nature obliged us to do the right thing and evolved our behaviours, government has the right and duty to have information to do rational decisions and nudge or even push us to do so:
    <ul>
      <li>Question is how much and where and when</li>
      <li>Government shouldn’t prevent you from smoking, but “you are free to do as wish, as long as I don’t have to pay for it”</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="culture-does-not-allow-us-to-transcend-biology">Culture does not allow us to transcend biology</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Culture is roughly everything we do and monkeys don’t.
<em>― FitzRoy Richard Somerset</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Clever as we are, we cannot modify our human bodies any more than superficial ways. And it’s arrogant to think we can engineer body parts any better than nature did. There will be no Pasteur for mismatched diseases.</p>

<p>We should come to terms that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We are fat, furless, bipedal primates that crave sugar, salt, fat and starch.</li>
  <li>We crave comfort, but our bodies are endurance athlete machines.</li>
  <li>As Voltaire wrote: “Let us cultivate our garden”. <strong>We must cultivate our body.</strong></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Compared to other animals with the same body weight, they have a fifth of the brain size, and double the intestine system. Size of the brain correlates with the size of the group. Humans are able to interact with 100 to 200 individuals.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Choking on food is the fourth leading cause of accidental death in the USA.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Between 1985 and 2000, the purchasing power of the US dollar decreased by 59 per cent, the price of fruit and vegetables doubled, fish increased by 30 per cent, diary about the same. In contrast, sugars and sweets became 25 per cent less expensive, fats and oils 40 per cent, soda 66 percent less expensive. Portion sizes ballooned: in a fast food restaurant in 1955 order of hamburger and fries would yield 412 cals. Today for the same inflation adjusted size, the same order would have double the calories, 920 cals.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>If you are curious of how the sewers of earlier cities smelled, the <a href="https://musee-egouts.paris.fr/en/">Paris Musée des Égouts</a> provides an <em>illustrative</em> tour through these sights and smells  <a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Thomas Crapper did not invent the toilet. But was a pioneer in its mass manufacturing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Crapper#Origin_of_the_word_%22crap%22">Origin of the word “crapper”</a><a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>For example, Hepatitis A virus stimulates T helper 1 cells, which suppress the number of T helper 2 cells<a href="#fnref:6" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2024 Lookback]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/31/2024-lookback.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/31/2024-lookback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s time to wrap up and celebrate 2024, an eventful year that fueled my yearning for internal growth and curiosity, with challenges and lessons I am grateful for.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>I’ve recently built a set of <a href="https://grafana.com/">Grafana</a> dashboards to track my personal goals, which I’ve been finding incredibly interesting to explore and visualise (something that might be interesting to share in a later post).</p>

<h2 id="final-tally">Final Tally</h2>

<p>There are other metrics I track, but specifically to 2024 content creation, these are the final statistics<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="2024 Stats">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/2024_lookback/stats.webp" aria-label="2024 Stats" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/2024_lookback/stats.png" aria-label="2024 Stats" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/2024_lookback/stats.png" aria-label="2024 Stats" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<ul>
  <li>17 posts on this blog, 16 of them being <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/">notes</a> (not counting this one), and one of them being a full blog article sharing how to build a <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html">personal local (Llama3 8B) LLM, extended with WhatsApp and Obsidian data</a></li>
  <li>10 YouTube videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@lopespm">main channel</a>. 8 of them being long form, the other 2 being shorts.</li>
  <li>5 YouTube videos on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@out-and-about-channel">Out and About</a>, a recently created channel where I share random experiences on activities such as walking / hiking around or driving.</li>
</ul>

<p>Notice that the tracked metrics are on the volume of content produced, not their number of views, subscribers, likes. Although keeping track of topline metrics makes sense for a full fledged business, I chose instead to track what I <em>can</em> control, which is my output. At the end of the day, this is a hobby, a labor of love.</p>

<p>If I can influence someone’s life for the better, that will already fill my heart to the brim. This, added to how important posting these contents has become to consolidate and structure my thoughts, and serendipitous opportunities they randomly opened, make this an incredibly satisfying endeavor.</p>

<p>I’ve experienced time and time again that consistency eventually bears wonderful fruits. Who knows which doors might open one day later? I don’t, but I’m curious to find out.</p>

<h2 id="one-day-away">2025, one day away</h2>

<p>With 2024 wrapped up, let’s welcome 2025. <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html#an-example">I’ve pinned down next year’s goals</a> and will be looking forward to sharing what I learn along the way. Happy new year, and see you on the other side! 🫡</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This dashboard was produced using a custom Grafana dashboard, where the RSS feeds for this blog and YouTube channels were tracked, transformed and presented in simple gauge widgets</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Note Taking]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/30/note-taking.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/30/note-taking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
          <picture aria-label="Stack of notebooks">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/note_taking/note_stack.webp" aria-label="Stack of notebooks" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/note_taking/note_stack.png" aria-label="Stack of notebooks" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/note_taking/note_stack.png" aria-label="Stack of notebooks" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Over the past 4 years, I&rsquo;ve written about 1820 pages on the 13 A5 notebooks shown in the picture above. This tool has become essential for my job, and in this article I&rsquo;ll describe the simple process behind it, which I&rsquo;ve found to deliver consistent results, reliably.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="write-consolidate-repeat">Write, Consolidate, Repeat</h2>

<p>The process I&rsquo;ve been using for several years is based on <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2023/05/18/solving-task-switching-through-documentation.html">Option 3. of Solving Task Switching Through Documentation</a>, and is broken down in three steps:</p>

<p><strong>1. Write</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Material</strong>: A5 spiral notebook (it makes it easier to be written anywhere, because the pages can always be flipped around in a way that only the writing page is facing up, and the rest of the pages serving as a solid writing surface; plus the notebook&rsquo;s rings are great for carrying your pen or pencil reliably), with clear pages (this allows for diagrams, phrases, texts, tidbits, collaborations to happen without any formal restriction). Have another backup notebook within reach, to replace the main one when it runs out.</li>
  <li><strong>When</strong>: Make sure to always have your notebook and pen / pencil at your desk, meetings, conferences, 1:1s, and any environment where a collaboration is made, within reason.</li>
  <li><strong>What</strong>: Write down your thoughts, key points that coworkers communicate, ideas, anything else you find relevant. These are your notes, so allow yourself to expand and experiment.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Consolidate</strong></p>

<p>With several notes written, their consolidation can happen in three different time spans:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Immediately</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>The mere act of writing often helps the thought process, since it forces ethereal concepts to be materialized into paper. Expect that a good portion of the written notes to not be read ever again.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Shortly after they are written</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Keeping track of conversations: has it ever happened to you that suddenly you completely lost track of the discussion, especially a complex / ambiguous one? Refer back to the jotted down key points to quickly recall and connect points. Soon after you will be back on track, and maybe with new insights.</li>
      <li>Summarization of conversation segments, usually at the end of a meeting: leverage the written notes to summarize key takeaways and action points. There is nothing worse than spending 30 minutes in a discussion without material end results or follow ups.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Some time after notes are written</strong>: I avoid this period to be longer than one day.
    <ul>
      <li>Transcribe key points into a structured medium, such as a document, article, or personal log (I use a simple text file where I log important events during the day; this text file has been consistently updated for 4 years, and is a personal historical treasure trove spanning several thousands of lines).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>3. Repeat</strong></p>

<p>Just like other processes, their value only becomes apparent after they have been used several times. Build a habit. It will then become immediately apparent whenever a notebook is not at hand, or when structured notes are not written down.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diary of a CEO Book: Lessons]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/28/diary-of-ceo-book-lessons.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/28/diary-of-ceo-book-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently finished reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Diary-CEO-Laws-Business-Life/dp/0593715837">Diary of a CEO: 33 Laws of Business and Life</a>, which draws from both Steven Bartlett’s entrepreneurial journey and interviews from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@TheDiaryOfACEO">homonymous podcast</a>. These are are my main takeaways:</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="building-high-performance-groups">Building high performance groups</h2>

<h3 id="incentives-and-culture">Incentives and culture</h3>
<ul>
  <li>If you want to predict what a group of people will do over the long term, you need to look at their incentives, not their instructions.</li>
  <li>Companies don’t have one company culture: every manager in an organization creates a subculture underneath them.</li>
  <li>In a small group / startup, when the culture is strong, new joiners become like the culture. When the culture is weak, the culture becomes like the new joiners.</li>
  <li>In a small group / startup (and likely this can be applied to teams), create a cult-like dynamic upon its inception, but then transition it to a more sustainable structure. Key elements of a cult:
    <ul>
      <li>Provides meaning, purpose and belonging. Asserts superiority of the group.</li>
      <li>Clear shared identity and commitment to ideology.</li>
      <li>Leaders present themselves as infallible, confident and grandiose.</li>
      <li>“Us vs Them” mentality: there is a clear adversary.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="traits-of-a-good-leader">Traits of a good leader</h3>
<ul>
  <li>The factor that kills meaning the fastest is a leadership team that dismisses employee’s work or ideas, removes their sense of ownership and autonomy, and asks them to spend time on work that is cancelled, changed or disregarded before it’s been completed.</li>
  <li>Allow people the space to fail and succeed. The main job of a leader is to be a supportive enabler, not a critical micromanager.</li>
  <li>Leaders should proactively remove any obstacles, bureaucracy and sign-off processes that prevent the team to achieve daily progress, this includes identifying and providing the required resources for them to do their job. To discover these gaps, ask the teams informally or formally about these problems (via retros for example).</li>
  <li>Leaders need to point out, publicize and praise progress as loud, far and wide as they possibly can. Recognition reinforces behaviour, but it also acts as evidence to adjacent teams that progress is possible for them too.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Ferguson">Alex Ferguson</a>, the widely successful manager from Manchester United, didn’t care about tactics, strategies and formations. He cared about getting the best out of each individual, the team’s culture and attitude. He didn’t want them to be become complacent:
    <ul>
      <li>He had different ways of dealing with different players. He knew how to get the best out of everyone. He knew his players well, and what made them tick, like Gary Neville’s important connection with his grandparents.</li>
      <li>Some players strived under Ferguson’s “hairdryer” treatment, others under a more compassionate approach, and others by being more hands off. There was not a size fits all approach. The main objective was always to have the team and club at a higher ground.</li>
      <li>It is impossible to seamlessly blend into a team as a jigsaw piece, unless you comprehend the unique shape of each of your team members.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="ask-who-not-how">Ask who, not how</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Every CEO and founder will be judged on their ability to hire the best, and bind them into a culture that gets the best out of them. An environment where they become more than the sum of the parts.</li>
  <li>Your ego will insist that you do. Your potential will insist that you delegate.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="excise-bad-apples-promote-bar-raisers">Excise bad apples, promote bar raisers</h3>
<ul>
  <li><em>“The cost of one bad apple can be the loss of many good ones”</em> - CEO of General Electric
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2018/03/research-how-one-bad-employee-can-corrupt-a-whole-team">Study</a> found that employees were 37% more likely to commit misconduct at work when they encountered a new co-worker who had a history of misconduct themselves. Toxic employees really are contagious.</li>
      <li>When a bad apple isn’t fired, it can lead to employee disengagement, other employees copying the behaviour, social withdrawal, anxiety and fear. Culminating in the deterioration of trust in the team and further disengagement from its team members.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.rismedia.com/2024/02/01/thoughts-leadership-building-winning-team-with-3-bars-framework/">3 bars framework</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Ask yourself, or managers: “if everyone in the organization had the same cultural values, attitude, and level of talent as this employee, would the average bar be lowered, maintained, or raised?</li>
      <li>Fire the ones that lower the bar, promote the bar raisers.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wTgQ2PBiz-g">“(…) not settling for B and C players, but really going for the A players”</a>. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/8586131-it-doesn-t-make-sense-to-hire-smart-people-and-then">“It doesn’t make sense to hire smart people and tell them what to do; we hire smart people so they can tell us what to do”</a> - Steve Jobs</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="dealing-with-discomfort">Dealing with discomfort</h2>
<ul>
  <li>“Hard” is the price we pay today for an “easy” tomorrow.</li>
  <li>When you refuse to accept an uncomfortable truth, you’re choosing to accept an uncomfortable future.</li>
  <li>When something is unresolved because we’ve chosen to bury our heads in the sand, it doesn’t sit dormant, waiting to be addressed; it becomes toxic, contagious and poisonous to those around us, inflicting more collateral damage with every day that it remains unaddressed.</li>
  <li>When seeking the truth that is causing the discomfort, listen to understand, not to look for a victory, but rather in the perspective of a partner that wants to overcome that difficulty.</li>
  <li>In a relationship, if you’re having the same conversation over and over again, you are having the wrong conversations. You’re avoiding the uncomfortable conversation you should be having.</li>
  <li>It is in talking about our disconnections that people create more connectedness with one another.</li>
  <li>You can predict someone’s success in any area of their life by observing how willing and capable they are at dealing with uncomfortable conversations. Your personal progression is trapped behind an uncomfortable conversation.</li>
  <li>As mentioned by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism#Vaillant's_categorization">George Vaillant</a>, denial can be healthy, enabling individuals to cope with rather than become immobilized by anxiety, or it can be unhelpful, creating a self deception that alters reality in ways that can be dangerous.</li>
  <li><a href="(https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10225430-even-when-we-think-we-re-seeking-pleasure-we-re-actually-driven)"><em>“People think they’re motivated by seeking pleasure; they’re wrong, they’re motivated by avoiding discomfort”</em></a> - Nir Eyal</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="pressure-only-comes-to-those-who-earn-it">Pressure only comes to those who earn it</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.usopen.org/en_US/news/articles/2024-07-19/billie_jean_king_reveals_origin_of_iconic_quote_pressure_is_a_privilege.html"><em>“Pressure is a privilege, and champions adjust”</em></a> - Billy Jean King (BJK)</li>
  <li>Pressure is external, stress is internal.</li>
  <li>How you handle pressure and its resulting stress is essential, and makes a difference between positive and negative outcomes.</li>
  <li>Great pressure moments often precede great privileges.</li>
  <li>Life without pressure is a life without purpose.</li>
  <li>Pressure is neither good nor bad. It’s what we do with it that matters.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/kelly-mcgonigals-ted-talk-on-stress-2014-3#in-the-first-study-mcgonigal-looked-at-university-of-wisconsin-researchers-tracked-30000-american-adults-for-eight-years-they-found-that-subjects-with-a-lot-of-stress-had-a-43-increased-risk-of-dying--but-only-if-they-believed-stress-was-harmful-1">Kelly McGonigal</a> looked at a study made for 30k American adults, and noticed that people who experienced a lot of stress during their lives had 43% increased risk of dying, but this was only true for the ones who perceived stress as harmful. The ones that did not perceive it as harmful had the lowest risk of dying, even when compared to the ones who experienced relatively little stress.</li>
  <li>Objective is not to get rid of pressure, it’s to change your relationship with it altogether.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/7-it-is-not-the-critic-who-counts-not-the-man"><em>“It is not the critic who counts; not the man who points out how the strong man stumbles, or where the doer of deeds could have done them better. The credit belongs to the man who is actually in the arena, whose face is marred by dust and sweat and blood; who strives valiantly; who errs, who comes short again and again, because there is no effort without error and shortcoming; but who does actually strive to do the deeds; who knows great enthusiasms, the great devotions; who spends himself in a worthy cause; who at the best knows in the end the triumph of high achievement, and who at the worst, if he fails, at least fails while daring greatly, so that his place shall never be with those cold and timid souls who neither know victory nor defeat”</em></a> - Theodore Roosevelt</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="building-good-habits">Building good habits</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Instead of fighting against a bad habit, acknowledge the cue, routine, reward habit loop. When removing any of these elements, its void will need to be replaced. Replace rather than delete.</li>
  <li>Cues are powerful, since they are the starting points to routines. As such, be mindful of how you set up your environment. For example, Steven Bartlett placed his DJ set in the kitchen table, in plain sight, and made sure to take only one click to start practicing, in order to reduce perceived cost of practicing it. I’ve personally done the same thing with my camera setup to shoot <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@lopespm">YouTube videos</a>, by using a simple and predictable set up for video and microphone, which I have with highly visible in my living room, incentivizing me to do more videos.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="persistence">Persistence</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10644791-we-don-t-have-to-be-smarter-than-the-rest-we"><em>“We don’t have to be smarter than the rest. We have to be more disciplined than the rest.”</em></a> - Warren Buffett</li>
  <li>Katherine Milkman shared <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/plan-a-works-better-when-theres-no-plan-b-1471356000">research</a> that having a plan B, in any ambition, has a net negative on our chances of succeeding with a plan A.
    <ul>
      <li>The more you perceive negative emotions in the event of failure, the more driven you will be to succeed-</li>
      <li>But don’t be reckless. Take risks that don’t put you in irreversible and dangerous circumstances.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-jeffersoncc-introliterature/chapter/680/"><em>“If there be no alternative but death, the soldiers exert themselves to the utmost.”</em></a> - Sun Tzu, The Art of War</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="incremental-wins-keeping-momentum">Incremental wins, keeping momentum</h3>
<ul>
  <li>How much you are achieving is pretty much irrelevant to your motivation: but if you feel like you are getting somewhere, you’ll be driven to keep going.
    <ul>
      <li>When problems seem insurmountable or too hard or unknown, that’s when procrastination creeps in.</li>
      <li>The key here is to break down the problem into smaller, more manageable ones. The small resulting improvements and the sense of momentum will keep you going, and these will eventually compound.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="applying-time-and-energy-effectively">Applying time and energy effectively</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The exact same skill applied in a different industry or context can have a widely different value, as seen by a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/magazine/pearls-before-breakfast-can-one-of-the-nations-great-musicians-cut-through-the-fog-of-a-dc-rush-hour-lets-find-out/2014/09/23/8a6d46da-4331-11e4-b47c-f5889e061e5f_story.html">Washington Post experiment</a> where one of the world’s greatest violinists Joshua Bell, who was able to professionaly command $1,000 a minute, barely got any attention or spare change from playing in the subway.</li>
  <li>Position yourself correctly, and get the skills that your industry finds to be rare and valuable, and that your competitors don’t have.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="time">Time</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Time betting exercise
    <ul>
      <li>Imagine you, and everyone is sitting around the game of life. Each player is assigned a number of chips, each representing an hour. They don’t know how many they have. Maybe it’s one, maybe it’s 500k. You can try to predict, but you don’t really know.</li>
      <li>The rule is that every hour you need to put one chip on the table, or it will just be placed automatically. You can place it on Netflix, learning a new skill, sleeping, etc. Certain actions that increase your health will increase your stock of chips.</li>
      <li>Your fitness will block you from betting on certain positions. For example, if you have a serious locomotion injury, you cannot choose to run.</li>
      <li>The game ends when all chips are gone. You don’t get to keep anything you earned during the game.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Being selective about how you spend your time, and who you spend your time with, is the greatest sign of self respect.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="failure-as-an-advantage">Failure as an advantage</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Ask the questions: Why will this fail? Why is this a bad idea?</li>
  <li>Apply the pre-mortem process to visualize and attempt to preempt failures in your plan. This will mitigate risk and likely increase your prediction accuracy.
    <ul>
      <li>A <a href="https://hbr.org/2007/09/performing-a-project-premortem">1989 study</a> found that prospective hindsight—imagining that an event has already occurred—increases the ability to correctly identify reasons for future outcomes by 30%.</li>
      <li>Steven Bartlett’s pre-mortem method:
        <ul>
          <li>Set the stage: the objective of the exercises. It is to uncover risks, not to look for escape goats.</li>
          <li>Fast forward to failure. Ask team to visualize failure as clearly as possible.</li>
          <li>Brainstorm reasons for failure.</li>
          <li>Ideate independently, and then share and discuss.</li>
          <li>Develop contingency plans.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Share experiment failures, so that their knowledge can be leveraged when building new experiments.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/acref/9780191826719.001.0001/q-oro-ed4-00003960"><em>“I have not failed, I have just found 10k ways that won’t work”</em></a> - Thomas Edison</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling seen]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/21/feeling-seen.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/21/feeling-seen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
          <picture aria-label="Being seen ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p1.webp" aria-label="Being seen ad" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p1.png" aria-label="Being seen ad" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/feeling_seen/p1.png" aria-label="Being seen ad" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p>This ad struck me as the culmination of a long-standing trend. I struggled to articulate it at the time, but I’ll attempt to do just that in this article.</p>

<p>Let’s start by the ad itself. It carries implicit symbols and memes, whose interpretations will vary wildly from person to person, but in general I believe it attempts to convey these subtle messages:</p>

<ol>
  <li>In order to be seen and acknowledged as an individual, one must spark admiration and rise above the crowd with a stylish look, makeup and fashionable garments. Appearance <em>is</em> the solution.</li>
  <li>Feeling seen is about exterior validation (which requires the advertised beauty products), rather than real understanding and connection with another being.</li>
  <li>You need to command the attention of acquaintances and strangers, their judgement is important for your self worth.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
</ol>

<!--more-->

<p>Relying only on external validation, specially from foreign entities, as a means to sustain one’s self-esteem is a time honored strategy to produce nefarious results. Yet, it’s celebrated by certain influencers, mainstream media, TV shows, ads and movies that attempt to distort a small sample into a normality.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p5.webp" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p5.png" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/feeling_seen/p5.png" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="demanding-standards">Demanding Standards</h1>

<p>When external validation is postulated as a basic human need, and one’s default natural, vanilla body is not sufficient to garner the validation one needs (as the above ad suggests), it soon follows that external interventions are required to achieve it.</p>

<p>I was fortunate enough to grow in an environment where artificial external displays of vanity were seen as a quirk, and sometimes even frowned upon (depending on the situation), thus not a requirement for a happy and fulfilled life. But once one is born or dislodged into the eye of a hurricane, it is hard to see the surrounding damage, especially when peers abide by those standards, generating an underlying group integration peer pressure.</p>

<h2 id="hazardous-trends">Hazardous trends</h2>

<p>Several off-the-shelf beauty products are known for their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rObAX1r8r0s">toxicity</a>, contributing to increased prevalence of cancer and infertility, yet they stand as one of the cornerstones of modern standards of beauty.</p>

<p>How we show up is important, and is a meaningful way of self expression, but when the baseline for allowing one’s self expression requires one to consume / apply several products (sometimes on the go), or even subject to invasive body modifications, then I would argue that something is wrong in the underlying societal system.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p3.webp" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p3.png" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/feeling_seen/p3.png" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="mind-the-ouch">Mind the ouch</h3>

<p>One such body modification, turned mainstream, is the injection of botox.</p>

<p>Botulism is an often-fatal nervous system disease, first recorded in Europe in 1793, claiming the death of over half of those patients who had become ill through eating uncooked blood sausages. <em>botulus</em> being the Latin word for sausage. One one-millionth of a gram this neurotoxic protein can kill a man, and one pint would be enough to kill everyone on earth.</p>

<p>In 1989, purified botulinum toxin was approved as a drug under the brand name Oculinum, and later renamed to <em>Botox</em>. In small doses, the same nerve damage that causes fatal paralysis in poisoning cases, helps to remove forehead creases and crow’s feet, with the only side effects being an inability to express emotion using your face, and an occasional case of drooping eyelids.</p>

<p>Today, injecting the deadliest substance on earth into one’s face is normalized, as seen in this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uSjIfBNwvYw">TV commercial</a> (where its mid-commercial disclaimers makes one question if it’s a real ad, or a parody<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>), or as seen in this suggestive London tube ad:</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Mind the ouch ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p2.webp" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p2.png" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/feeling_seen/p2.png" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="look-within">Look Within</h1>

<p>I hold nothing against those who choose to subscribe to a certain mode of expression or style. I too, have my own. I do welcome you to introspect <em>why</em> you chose it. If your sincere <em>why</em> comes from a deep rooted desire to feel accepted and valued by others (good to receive these in healthy dosages, but dangerous when overbearing), then it might be something to look out for.</p>

<p>Relying <em>solely</em> on external validation likely results in feelings of emptiness and insatisfaction. I’ve been there several times, and its not pleasant. Instead, attempt to obtain self validation by looking in, rather than out. <a href="](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LzHmifZo5Jk)">Some simple, yet powerful strategies</a>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Consider your ancestors, a stable past. For example, what would your ancestors eat, do, that worked out for their health? Our bodies have adapted throughout milenia to certain patterns, and if we are on their descendancy line, surely they did <em>something</em> right. Time is the great filter of nonsense and fallacies.</li>
  <li>Recognize the cycle: ask yourself why you are seeking external validation, and understand the patterns and needs that lead to it.</li>
  <li>Practice self-appreciation: build your self-acceptance structure, practice gratefulness and appreciation for what you are and did (a journal might help).</li>
  <li>Rejection therapy: put yourself in situations you seek rejection. Start small, such as asking for a discount or applying for a job you think you are not qualified for. It helps you realise that rejection is not as bad as it appears, which decreases the need for other’s validations.</li>
  <li><a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html#an-example">Set personal goals</a>: instead of relying on others to measure against, take control, and set goals that serve your needs and desires. Keep yourself accountable to hit them.</li>
  <li>Listen to your intuition: you know yourself best, so why rely on others for answers? Reach within and take distraction free time to listen to yourself.</li>
  <li>Self care to self validate: do activities that make you feel good, use self affirming thoughts, take care of yourself.</li>
</ol>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>Why: friends, family and close connections likely already acknowledge you by who you really are, or at least should. Why would they need you to wear a beauty product in order for you to feel seen? Therefore the remaining target audience are acquaintances and strangers</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Transcript from the TV commercial: <em>(…) FDA approved to temporarily make frown lines crow’s feet and forehead lines look better. The effects of Botox Cosmetic may spread hours to weeks after injection causing serious symptoms alert your doctor right away as difficulty swallowing, speaking, breathing, eye problems, or muscle weakness may be a sign of a life-threatening condition. Do not receive Botox Cosmetic if you have a skin infection. Side effects may include allergic reactions, injection site pain, headache, eyebrow, eyelid drooping and eyelid swelling. Tell your doctor about your medical history muscle or nerve conditions and medications including botulinum toxins, as these may increase the risk of serious side effects. So get that “just saw a puppy look”! (…)</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[48 Laws of Power: Lessons]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/08/48-laws-of-power-lessons.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/08/48-laws-of-power-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently finished Robert Greene’s <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Laws-Power-Robert-Greene-Collection/dp/1861972784">48 Laws of Power</a>, a controversial, yet useful book. The information it shares makes one better prepared to navigate our complex and perilous world of influences, power and subtle manipulations.</p>

<p>I found it to be an eye-opener on some fronts, but mostly as providing different perspectives on things that on the surface, appear obvious. </p>

<p>I can recommend this book to just about anyone. Its information, just like a knife, can be used for useful, enriching and productive endeavours (like cutting vegetables for a family dinner), or for nefarious activities (such as inflicting harm upon others). It’s ones responsibility to use it correctly and morally.</p>

<p>Below are my key takeways, segmented by <strong>Behaviour</strong>, <strong>Resources</strong>, <strong>Relationships</strong>, <strong>Strategies</strong> and <strong>How you Show Up</strong>.</p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="behaviour">Behaviour</h1>

<h2 id="attitude-and-behaviour">Attitude and Behaviour</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Be royal in your demeanor. How you present and carry yourself tells the people how they should treat you. As seen in Columbus, son of a cheese maker, who behaved like royalty, as someone who deserved to be treated well. He amazed the Portuguese king, and eventually got the Spanish royalty to get him what he wanted: a fully paid expedition, except for a lifetime 10% profit shares for him and his descendants. They felt like he was one of them. Even though he knew less about navigation than any of his sailors and was a bad leader, he still got what he wanted, because of how he carried himself.</li>
  <li>Beware of venerating a new seductive culture that is not your original one. Don’t despise and look down upon the culture that raised you and provided you gifts, for it will grow resentment of the ones that follow it.</li>
  <li>Boldness over timidity. Both are acquired behaviours. Timidity gives others time to think and plan. Makes even the tamest prone to attack when they sense blood in the water.</li>
  <li>Only the weak rest on their laurels and dote on past triumphs.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="in-victory-dont-go-past-your-mark">In victory, don’t go past your mark</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Success is intoxicating and dangerous. The moment of victory is the moment of greatest peril. Do not allow success to come to your head. Set a goal, and when you reach it, stop.
    <ul>
      <li>Know when to stop and consolidate wins, instead of persisting in pushing forward.</li>
      <li>When success is attained, step back, and reflect upon the conditions that led to it. Don’t simply repeat the same actions again and again.</li>
      <li>History is littered with corpses and fallen empires who did not know when to stop.</li>
      <li>There is a Japanese saying that Furuya Sensei was fond of, “Katte kara kabuto no o wo shime yo” which means After victory, tighten your helmet. Never let your guard down even if you think you have won. That just might be what your opponent wants you to think.</li>
      <li>The moment when you stop has great dramatic importance. What comes last sticks in the mind as an exclamation point. Best time to stop is after a victory. Keep going, and it will lessen it’s effect, or even reverse it.</li>
      <li><em>“Nothing can be more important than to close your examination with a triumph. So many lawyers succeed in catching a witness in a serious contradiction; but, not satisfied with this, go on asking questions, and taper off their examination until the effect upon the jury of their former advantage is lost altogether. “Stop with a victory” is one of the maxims of cross-examination”</em> - <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/40781/40781-h/40781-h.htm">Francis L. Wellman, The Art of Cross Examination</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Bad luck teaches you patience, timing and the need to be prepared for the worst. Good luck deludes you into making you think your brilliance will carry you forward. And when inevitably misfortune comes you will lack adequate preparation.</li>
  <li>As it’s taught in riding school: you have to be able to control yourself, before your can control the horse.
    <ul>
      <li>And even when you can control yourself, there will be people forcing you to push forward. Be careful, and manage them. Feed them with small victories, but don’t allow yourself to be engulfed in the momentum and go all in.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><em>“A man famed for his tree-climbing skills once directed another to climb a tall tree and cut branches. While the fellow was precariously balanced aloft, the tree-climber watched without a word, but when he was descending and had reached the height of the eaves the expert called to him, ‘Careful how you go ! Take care coming down !’. ‘Why do you say that ? He’s so far down now that he could leap to the ground from there,’ I said. ‘Just so,’ replied the tree-climber. ‘While he’s up there among the treacherous branches I need not say a word – his fear is enough to guide him. It’s in the easy places that mistakes will always occur.’ Lowly commoner though he was, his words echoed the warnings of the sages.”</em> - Yoshida Kenkō, Essays in Idleness</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="dont-appear-too-perfect-dont-boast">Don’t appear too perfect. Don’t boast.</h2>
<ul>
  <li>By making others aware of their inferior position, you are only stirring an unhappy admiration, this is, envy.
    <ul>
      <li>To show envy, is to admit your inferiority, and that is why people don’t normally admit it.</li>
      <li><em>“Of all the disorders in the soul, envy is the only one no one confesses to.”</em> -  Plutarch</li>
      <li>Cosimo de’ Medici avoided such issues by being simple on the outside, and only showing his wealth, elegance and opulence on the inside (of his house, for example).
        <ul>
          <li><em>“There is in the garden a plant which one ought to leave dry, although most people water it. It is the weed called Envy.”</em> - Cosimo de’ Medici</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Kierkegaard believed that the creator of envy is as much to blame as the person who feels envy. Don’t crow about your victories and superiority.
    <ul>
      <li>The naturally perfect are the ones that need to work the most to hide their features. One does not require innate characteristics to aquire money and power, in contrast to bearing sharp natural intellect and bodily features considered to be beautiful.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>A sudden increase in power or promotion are dangerous. Downplay them, don’t flaunt them, and attribute them to luck, since luck is possible to all.</li>
  <li>Be careful of false modesties that can be seen through. Put on a good act. Otherwise it will only create more envy.</li>
  <li>People cannot envy power that they themselves have bestowed upon a person.
    <ul>
      <li>When Ivan the Terrible died, Boris Godunov knew he was the only one on the scene who could lead Russia. But if he sought the position eagerly, he would stir up envy and suspicion among the boyars, so he refused the crown, not once but several times. He made it point for people insist that he take the throne. George Washington used the same strategy to great effect, first in refusing to keep the position of Commander in Chief of the American army, second in resisting the presidency. In both cases he made himself more popular than ever.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>If needed, pay a high price to keep envy in check.</li>
  <li><em>“Envy is the tax which all distinction must pay”</em> - Thoreau</li>
  <li><em>“It takes a great talent and skill to conceal one’s talent and skill”</em> - La Rochefoucauld</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="rationality-and-control">Rationality and Control</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the face of a hot headed enemy, an excellent response is no response.</li>
  <li>Nothing is as infuriating as a man who keeps his cool, when others are losing theirs.</li>
  <li>Petulance is not power, it is a sign of helplessness.</li>
  <li>Only use raging tirades if you are in control of them, with precision, and very rarely. They are a (dangerous) tool.</li>
  <li><em>“Wise men [should be] like coffers with double bottoms: which when others look into, when opened, they see not all that they hold.”</em> - Sir Walter Raleigh</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="use-your-words-and-actions-wisely">Use your words and actions wisely</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Once your words are out, you cannot take them back. Keep them under control and be particularly careful about sarcasm. The momentary satisfaction you get from your biting words will be <a href="https://medium.com/@praisenicholas/the-art-of-shutting-up-9bc7d08799a2">outweigh by the price you pay</a></li>
  <li><em>“Oysters open completely when the moon is full; and when the crab sees one it throws a piece of stone or seaweed into it and the oyster cannot close again so that it serves the crab for meat. Such is the fate of him who opens his mouth too much and thereby puts himself at the mercy of the listener.”</em> - Leonardo Da Vinci</li>
  <li><em>“If you are not in danger, do not fight”</em> - Sun Tzu</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="be-strategic-in-your-approach">Be strategic in your approach</h2>
<ul>
  <li>When in a position of power, don’t be completely predictable, as that could be exploited. when is a position of serving others, be careful when doing that, because it might make you be seen as unreliable, or even having a psychological pathology.</li>
  <li>Attach yourself to the real decision maker, not people with titles. As seen for Richelieu, who attached himself to King Louis XIII’s mother, instead of the king himself, since she was the one calling the shots. As a result, Richelieu rose quickly through the ranks.</li>
  <li>Winston Lord had worked on a report for days, which Kissinger handed back with the notation “Is this the best you can do?”. Lord rewrote and polished and finally resubmitted it; back it came with the same curt question. After redrafting it one more time–and once again getting the same question from Kissinger–Lord snapped, “Damn it, yes, it’s the best I can do.”. To which Kissinger replied: “Fine, then I guess I’ll read it this time.”</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_North_Wind_and_the_Sun">North wind and the Sun</a> made a bet on who could make a man take off his coat. First, the North wind gushed one him, but that only made the man hold on to it more tightly. Then, the Sun provided a warm heat that made the man take off top coat, and then blazing heat which made the man strip and bath in the river. Persuasion is more effective than force.</li>
  <li><em>“MAN: Kick him-he’ll forgive you. Flatter him-he may or may not see through you. But ignore him and he’ll hate you”</em> - Idries Shah</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>

<h3 id="focus-your-energies">Focus your energies</h3>
<ul>
  <li>What’s concentrated, coherent, and connected to it’s past, has power.</li>
  <li>Concentrate your forces: Intensity beats extensity every time. You gain more by finding a rich mine and digging it deeper, than by fleeting from one shallow mine to another</li>
  <li>Dispersion can be a good strategy when your opponents are stronger.</li>
  <li>Caveat: if the sole person providing you power dies or leaves the scene, you will be in trouble. Protect yourself against that risk by having different concentrated sources of power. As seen with Cesare Borgia’s transgression of this, who derived his power mainly from his father, the Pope, who gave him armies to fight with. When his father died, he was as good as dead.</li>
  <li>Do not spend time, attention or energy on things you cannot have. Your attention, or lack of, is a form of power. When King Louis wanted to punish someone on their court, he would just ignore them and cut them off.</li>
  <li><a href="https://isaacjeffries.com/blog/2020/6/25/the-goose-and-the-horse">“I had far rather be confined to one element, and be admired in that, than be a Goose in all.”</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="focus-on-the-important-things">Focus on the important things</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Paranoia over small ticket issues are often destructive in the end. As seen when Kissinger made a recommendation to create a group to “plug the leaks” after the publication of the Pentagon Papers. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_House_Plumbers">Plumbers</a>, as they became known, eventually broke into the Democratic Party offices in the Watergate Hotel, setting off the chain of events that led to Nixon’s downfall.</li>
  <li>When you make a mistake, treat it lightly. When a petty enemy attacks you, make none of it, show contempt. Show contempt publicly, but keep track of it privately. Don’t let a small problem or foe become a cancerous cell that gains power and overtakes you. Deal with them as appropriate.</li>
  <li><em>“To disregard, is to win regard”</em> - Italian proverb</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-value-of-time">The value of Time</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Time is a human construct. Perception of time is subjective. Younger people feel like time is going slowly. Older people feel like time is whizzing by.</li>
  <li>Three types of time: Long, Forcing, and End Time:
    <ul>
      <li>Long Time: happening on a years time scale, and must be managed with patience and gentle guidance. Key is to not react impulsively, and wait for the right opportunity.</li>
      <li>Forcing Time: when people are indecisive, give them a deadline. Never give them time. As seen with successful art dealer Joseph Duveen, who when dealing with indecisive clients, would mention that another tycoon would be interested, something happened and he had to leave the country, etc. This strategy works as long as the party does not know what you are up to.</li>
      <li>End Time: when a plan must be executed with speed and force.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patience is worthless if it doesn’t conclude with action. A period of waiting that does not lead into an action is a sign of indecision and procrastination. Timing is important.</li>
  <li><em>“Space we can recover. Time, never”</em> - Napoleon Bonaparte</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="despise-the-free-lunch">Despise the free lunch</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Nothing is more costly than something given free of charge.</li>
  <li>What is worth, is worth paying for. Always pay the full price, there is no cutting corners to excellency, for bargains are often accompanied by a complicated psychological price tag.</li>
  <li>Generosity is a sign, and a magnet for power. Keep money in constant circulation.</li>
  <li>The powerful understand they need to protect their most precious resources. Indepence, time, energy and room to maneuver. By paying the full price they keep themselves free of dangerous engagements and worries.</li>
  <li>Avoid bargain demons (who only consider the explicit price tag, and not the cost in time, energy, dignity and peace of mind), the money sadists (who abuse their payer position power, by for example making you wait for a payment), the indiscriminate givers (who likely are looking qualm a emotional need, are emotional drains, and want to be loved; if they give to everyone, why should you feel special?)</li>
  <li>The powerful must have have grandiosity if spirit, and should never reveal any pettiness. Money is the most visible arena in which to display either grandior or pettiness.</li>
  <li>And if you want to meddle with the work of the creative people you hire, at least pay them well. Your money will more easily buy their decision, rather than your shows of power.</li>
  <li>Powerful people give freely, buying influence, rather than things.</li>
  <li>Consider strategic generosity: give when you are about to take.</li>
  <li>A one time gift given at a sudden unexpected time, bears more force and impact. It will not spoil your children, but rather keep them under your thumb.</li>
  <li>The more the money you spend on gifts and acts of generosity that <a href="https://medium.com/bouncin-and-behavin-blogs/banksy-fushimiya-and-the-value-of-a-teacup-f6b2904d799f">play with sentiment, the more powerful they are.</a></li>
  <li>Don’t give in to greedy and inconsequent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Dorado">“El Dourado”</a>s that will only exhaust your time and energy.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="relationships">Relationships</h1>

<h2 id="perils-of-isolation">Perils of Isolation</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Do not create a fortress around you, it will make you detached from the world and make you an easy target, since it will be easy to know where you are, and be attacked.</li>
  <li>Pontormo, a painter who spent 11 years secluded inside a chapel painting for his patron. Terrified of being copied by others and growing more and more afraid of fellow humans, he died, and his paintings / frescos did not survive him. Vesari, who saw his paintings, described them as being embodied by madness. Perspective flaws, too many characters, several compositional flaws, figures that overlapped one another. Pontormo obsessed over details, and lost track of the composition.</li>
  <li>Shakespeare was well known because many people knew about his works, he didnt work in isolation.</li>
  <li>Isolation is good to gather one’s thoughts and escape the claws of conformity by society, but this should be done judiciously.</li>
  <li>The more time you spend isolated, the harder it is to come back to society. Make sure you always have a way to come back to society.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="enemies-and-friends">Enemies, and Friends</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Without enemies we grow lazy. Having enemies sharpens our wits. If you don’t have enemies, find them</li>
  <li>Without a worthy opponent, a man, woman or group cannot grow stronger.</li>
  <li>You are better having declared opponents, instead of not knowing where they lie.</li>
  <li>You need people who deliver results, not that appease you.</li>
  <li>Men are more ready to repay an injury than a benefit. Gratitude is felt as a burden, revenge as a pleasure.</li>
  <li>A brahman, a great expert in Veda who has become a great archer as well, offers his services to his good friend, who is now the king. The brahman cries out when he sees the king, “Recognize me, your friend!”. The king answers him with contempt and then explains: “Yes, we were friends before, but our friendship was based on what power we had. I was friends with you, good brahman, because it served my purpose. No pauper is a friend to the rich, no fool to the wise, no coward to the brave. It is two men of equal wealth and equal birth who contract friendship and marriage, not a rich man and a pauper. An old friend—who needs him?” - The Mahabharata</li>
  <li><em>“To have a good enemy, choose a friend: They know where to strike”</em> - Diane De Poitiers, 1499-1566, Mistress of Henry II of France</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="succession">Succession</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The formulas used by the successful father worked well for him, because he had nothing to lose, and gave him his kingdom and fortunes. The son, who lives in a different set of circumstances, could have his father’s ways imposed onto him, in a domineering and oppressive way, imposing his lessons on the son. Instead of trying to put the son in a new direction, the father tries to put him on his own shoes, perhaps secretly wanting the son to fail, as he often <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/classics/2018/06/19/alexander-and-bucephalus">resents his youth and opportunities</a>. Resulting in the son to be cowed and cautions and fearful of losing what the father had gained.
    <ul>
      <li>Alexander the Great only wanted to outdo his father. To obliterate his name from history. He resented that his father conquered most of Greece, leaving not much for him to conquer. He wanted to out his successful father in the shadows, instead of the opposite. Which he did.</li>
      <li>As a young rebel grows older, his struggle with his father often wanes, and he gradually comes to resemble the very man he used to defy.</li>
      <li>The presence of the “father” must be constantly slain and kept in check. The old ways, the father, the comfort, are enemies of progression and power.</li>
      <li>Keep an eye on the young, since they will do the same to you. Identify them and keep them under control.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>It would seem easy for the son or successor to build on a grand foundation left for him. But in the realm of power, the opposite is true. The pampered indulged child, almost always squanders their inheritance, for it doesnt start with a need to fill a void. As seen with Louis XIV, XV, XVI. Louis XIV, while navigating through troubled times, built Versailles instead of taking over his father’s palace, the Louvre, and reigned for (mostly glorified) 55 years. The last years of his reign were difficult, but it was hoped that his child would develop into the kind of strong ruler who would reinvigorate the land and add to the firm foundation that Louis XIV had laid. Instead, his son, Louis XV gave himself over to pleasure. Worn out by debauchery, his country and his own finances were in horrible disarray. His grandson Louis XVI inherited a realm in desperate need of reform and a strong leader. But Louis XVI was even weaker than his grandfather, and could only watch as the country descended into revolution.
    <ul>
      <li><em>“Necessity is what impels men to take action, and once the necessity is gone, only rot and decay are left”</em> - Niccolò Machiavelli</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>In Sumatra, the king would be killed ritually in a brutal fashion, in order to limit his boundless power and give space for the new generations.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="strategies">Strategies</h1>

<h2 id="strike-the-shepherd-and-the-sheep-will-disband">Strike the Shepherd, and the sheep will disband</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Athenians found an effective way to deal with socially undesirable individuals. They didn’t fight, punish, or re-educate them. <a href="https://www.greekboston.com/culture/ancient-history/hyperbolus/">They ostracized them</a>.</li>
  <li>Cancer begins with a single cell. Be quick and swift to isolate bad seeds from the group, before they infect a critical mass.
    <ul>
      <li>It’s better to isolate them, rather than destroy them. It’s less brutal. For in a game power, isolation spells defeat. Ostracize, limit their power. Spare no time arguing with them.</li>
      <li>Swindlers isolate their targets from their normal social circles, making them more vulnerable to influence and manipulation. Apart from the void left I’m the sheep</li>
      <li>Lure the poisonous person away, while staying away from their attacks, as seen with Pope Boniface’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dante_Alighieri#Exile_from_Florence">isolation</a> of Dante from the “Whites”, leaving a power void upon their faction. As a resultm Florence was taken over by the “Blacks”.</li>
      <li><em>“If an injury has to be done to a man it should be so severe that his vengeance need not be feared”</em> - Niccolo Machiavelli, The Prince</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><em>“When the tree falls, the monkeys scatter”</em> - Chinese psroverb</li>
  <li>Alternate harshness with mercy to soften your target. Play on their fears, but also their loves. Target primary emotions: Love, hate, jealousy.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="mirror-effect">Mirror effect</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.lecturesbureau.gr/1/the-trick-of-the-mirror-helps-communication-2760/?lang=en">Dr. Milton H. Erickson</a>, when faced with a couple with problems in bed, Erickson observed the same dynamics when they talked how they liked to dine. He didn’t address the problem directly, but rather them to schedule a dinner where both would have their desires met (for one desired a slow pace, the other a big meal). It worked as expected, and they transferred the lessons aquired in the dining table into their bedroom.</li>
  <li>Addressing people head-on will often lead to conflict. Instead, mirror their actions so they can reflect at their own time and pace, and fix themselves without admitting fault. They will think to have achieved it on their own, without anyone realising it. But be careful when being too obvious, as it will make them think you are manipulating them, undermining your efforts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="reformation-perils">Reformation Perils</h2>
<ul>
  <li>People know that change is needed, and are ok with superficial changes, but are deeply troubled when the changes are deep and affect their core beliefs, structures and habits.
    <ul>
      <li>Change is upsetting to the human animal, even when it’s for the good. If change is needed, find ways to disguise it. Sweeten the poison.</li>
      <li>As seen from Cromwell’s beheading due to his role in the overly ambitious reform and <a href="https://www.cambridge-news.co.uk/news/history/thomas-cromwells-disastrous-fall-favouritism-23904583">uprooting of Roman Catholicism</a>.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>When you destroy the familiar, you create a void that people will rush fill. The past is powerful. Borrow from its legitimacy to create a comforting and familiar presence. It will sustain your actions with a familiar and romantic feel, cloaking the nature of the changes you are attempting.
    <ul>
      <li>Because the past is buried and dead, it gives you the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criticize_Lin,_Criticize_Confucius">flexibility to interpret it as you see fit</a>.</li>
      <li>The Roman used this when transforming monarchy to republic</li>
      <li>Romans used this device when they transformed their monarchy into a republic. They may have installed two consuls in place of the king, but since the king had been served by twelve lictors, they retained the same number to serve under the consuls. The king had personally performed an annual sacrifice, in a great spectacle that stirred the public; the republic retained this practice, only transferring it to a special “chief of the ceremony, whom they called the King of the sacrifice.” These and similar gestures satisfied the people and kept them from clamoring for the monarchy’s return.</li>
      <li>When Romans declared Christianity to be Rome’s official imperial religion, the evocation of light and fertility (Saturnalia, Festival of Lights, Germanic celebrations of the re-birth of the Sun which all happened in December) could not be ignored. In 354 AD, the Christian church co-opted the birthday of Mithras (the Aryan god of light), and declared December 25th to be the birthday of Jesus Christ.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The ones that finish a revolution are rarely the bones who started it.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="how-you-show-up">How you Show Up</h1>

<h2 id="be-flexible-assume-formlessness">Be flexible, assume formlessness</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Just like an animal’s shell protects them from dangers, it also makes them slower and inflexible to change. Same can be said for governments and systems that build protections that ultimately make them more rigid and vulnerable to change.
    <ul>
      <li>Rigidity heightens the desire for change.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>In a Chinese tale, a farmer observed a hare running straight into a tree, breaking it’s neck. Afterwards, he waited in front of the tree waiting for the same thing to happen. He never caught another one, and was ridiculed. Same could be said for someone who tries to govern using the same strategies as those of early kings. They would be acting no differently than the tale’s farmer.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="presence-dilution">Presence dilution</h2>
<ul>
  <li><em>“Love never dies of starvation, but often of indigestion”</em> - Ninon de Lenclos</li>
  <li><em>“Absence diminishes small passions, and inflames greater loves. Just as wind douses a candle, and fans a fire.”</em> - François de La Rochefoucauld</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="reputation-and-respect">Reputation and Respect</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Be the master of your fate, and your reputation.</li>
  <li>Reputation is a critical resource. When you have it, protect it.</li>
  <li><em>“When the great lord passes, the peasants bow deeply and silently fart”</em> - Ethiopian proverb</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="symbology">Symbology</h2>
<ul>
  <li>A symbol is a powerful form of expression that summaries several concepts
    <ul>
      <li>For example, the Sun King symbology created for Louis XIV which symbolized his provider god like status.</li>
      <li>Or Diana the mistress of king Henri II of France, who dodged the common fate shared by many other elder mistresses of abandonment, by scattering around the reign multiple symbols related to her (Diana’s favorite colours [black and white] imprinted  in several buildings and images, associations with goddess of hunt Diana), and creating a motif intertwining her initials and the king’s, which king Henri disseminated widely. There was no escaping her presence. Until his death, in 1559, he remained faithful to her.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>A symbol is a shortcut of expression, containing in itself several dozen meanings. Symbols are generally subtler and less threatening than words, which can be too incisive.</li>
  <li>Primacy of sight amongst the senses: <em>“Truth is generally seen, rarely heard”</em> - Baltasar Gracián</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons from Roman History]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/10/13/lessons_roman_history.html"/>
    <updated>2024-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/10/13/lessons_roman_history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Keeping up with the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/12/interview_learnings_cia.html">theme</a> on capturing lessons from content I consume, I’ve recently seen an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DyoVVSggPjY">interview from Lex Fridman to Gregory Aldrete</a>, an historian specializing in ancient Rome and military history, in which Gregory eloquently spoke about many of the fascinating details on the rise and fall of ancient rome. Here are my takeaways from it.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="rise-and-fall-of-rome">Rise and Fall of Rome</h1>

<h2 id="romans-were-obsessed-with-the-past">Romans were obsessed with the past</h2>

<p>Romans were absolutely obsessed with the past, especially with their own family.</p>

<p>Entering an aristocrat Roman’s house, the first thing you would see would be a big wooden cabinet with several rows of wax death masks. These masks were imprints of Roman aristocrats at the time of their death.</p>

<p>Every child in the family had obsessively memorized every accomplishment of every one of those ancestors: their career, what offices they held, what battles they fought in, what they did.</p>

<p>At a funeral, people would talk about all the things their ancestors had done. The children would take out these masks, tie them onto their own faces, and wear them in the funeral procession. They were wearing the face of their own ancestors. You, as an individual, weren’t important. You were just the latest iteration of that family, and was a huge weight to live up to the deeds of their ancestors.</p>

<h2 id="brutus-honors-the-past-kills-julius-caesar-roman-republic-dawns">Brutus honors the past, kills Julius Caesar, Roman Republic dawns</h2>

<p>Rome started out as a monarchy. They had kings and were not happy with their kings. Around 500 BC, they held a revolution and they kicked out the kings, and the Roman Republic started at that point. One of the people who played a key role in this was a man named Lucius Junius <em>Brutus</em>.</p>

<p>500 years later, Julius Caesar<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> came along as the culmination of a sequence of generals trying to overtake Rome and declare themselves as kings. Even though he was populist who provided entertainment to the state, Julius Caesar was arrogant, didn’t hide his power, ignored the senate, and got several people angry. Romans don’t like kings.</p>

<p>Just so happens that one of Caesar’s best friends is Marcus Junius Brutus. People went to Brutus’ house and wrote graffiti saying “Remember your ancestor” or “You are no real Brutus”. He had no choice. He forms a conspiracy, and on the Ides of March, 44 BC, he and 23 other senators take daggers, stick them in Julius Caesar, and kill him for acting like a king.</p>

<p>Brutus killed his best friend because of something his late ancestor did.</p>

<h2 id="filling-julius-caesars-power-void">Filling Julius Caesar’s power void</h2>

<p>Julius Caesar and left a power void. There are many contenders for filling it up:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Mark Antony: a relative and supporter of Julius Caesar. Most expected him to be the new Ceaser.</li>
  <li>Lepidus: another of Caesar’s lieutenants.</li>
  <li>Senate: which wants to reassert its power, to become the dominant force in Rome again.</li>
  <li>Assassins who killed Caesar: Led by Brutus and Cassius.</li>
  <li>Pompey’s son: Pompey was Caesar’s great rival. Pompey’s son, Sextus Pompey, was at the time a warlord who seized control of Sicily, one of the richest provinces, and amassed a whole navy.</li>
  <li>Octavian: Julius Caesar’s 18-year-old kid grand nephew. When Caesar’s will was opened after his death, he posthumously adopted Octavian as his son.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="octavian-emerges-victorious">Octavian emerges victorious</h2>

<p>By now being Caesar’s son, Octavian gets to rename himself Gaius Julius Caesar Octavianus, and it just so happened that in the Mediterranean, there were about 12 legions full of hardened soldiers following the orders of a man named Gaius Julius Caesar.</p>

<p>As such, Octavian inherits an army overnight and becomes a player in this game for power, and a civil war starts.</p>

<p>Octavian emerges from it as the victor. He wasn’t a good general and lost almost every battle, but was politically savvy and very good at manipulating public image and propaganda. Octavian waged a propaganda war against Antony, portraying Antony as a foreign aggressor allied with an enemy queen, Cleopatra, and who was an official enemy of the Roman state). Octavian takes what’s a civil war and makes it look like a war against a foreign enemy.</p>

<h2 id="octavian-is-the-king-but-cant-act-like-one">Octavian is the “king”, but can’t act like one</h2>

<p>Octavian now becomes the sole ruler, essentially a king, but could not take the same approach as Julius Caesar, otherwise he would end up murdered all the same.</p>

<p>Instead, he was very modest, lived in an ordinary house like other aristocrats, wore just a plain toga, was respectful to the Senate, and ate simple foods. He’s someone who cared about the reality of power, not its external trappings. He wanted real power, not the appearance of it.</p>

<p>In terms of government, everything seemed the same from the outside, but in reality Octavian was able to retain absolute power. He did by resigning from all public offices to give that appearance, but at the same time got voted to have the powers of a consul, by which he could command armies, he got tribune power, to control meetings at the Senate, he could veto anything, and got several other powers.</p>

<p>Each year elections are held, and notionally, these people are in charge. But floating off to the side, there Octavian, who can just appear and say that “I don’t like this, let’s change it”</p>

<h2 id="nor-can-he-be-named-like-a-king">Nor can he be named like a king</h2>

<p>Octavian wondered what to call himself. He couldn’t call himself a king, or anything that could suggest it, so instead he picked ambiguous names, that when joined an interpret in a certain way, would proved to be powerful:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Augustus: Augustus could mean that someone is very pious, or could mean that something is divine.</li>
  <li>Princep<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>: Meaning, first citizen. Could be interpreted as a citizen just like everybody, or the first citizen, superior to all the others.</li>
  <li>Imperator: traditionally something that soldiers shout at a victorious general who’s won a battle. Octavian took this as a permanent title, implying he was a good general<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-being-roman-meant">What being Roman meant</h2>

<p>It’s wonderful to contemplate how the roman empire in about 100 AD overlaps with the regions <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MapPorn/comments/zpm0h4/hi_everyone_i_made_this_map_showcasing_the/#lightbox">where olives could be grown</a>. Romans consumed olives, grapes, wheat. Barbarians meat, dairy, beer. When you are a farmer, you tend to stay in the same place, when you raise cattle you follow them around. They are two fundamental forms of living. Diet was a big part of their culture and one of characteristics that was considered fundamentally Roman. Not having their diet was barbaric.</p>

<h2 id="roman-empire-crumbles">Roman empire crumbles</h2>

<p>There are many factors that could explain the fall of Rome, and there is not a single clear cut explanation. Even the date of the empire fall is debated. </p>

<p>Geography, climate, religion, disease (there were a whole series of waves of plague that started to hit under Marcus Aurelius and continued after him, which seemed to caused real serious death and economic disruption), Marcus Aurelius leaving is succession to his child (who turned out to be deranged), instead of picking the best suited person for that role <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, as it was done on the previous 80 years, which is often regarded as the high point of the Roman Empire.</p>

<h1 id="power-of-the-past">Power of the past</h1>

<h2 id="no-way-to-escape-the-power-of-the-past">No way to escape the power of the past</h2>

<p>Gregory and his wife wife wrote <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Long-Shadow-Antiquity-Gregory-Aldrete/dp/144116247X">The Long Shadow of Antiquity: What Have the Greeks and Romans Done for Us?”</a>, where they provide several examples of things that we think are just in truly unique parts of our culture or things that we think are just innate to human nature, that are actually rooted in the past, such as government, education, art, architecture, language / words, culture, medicine, habits, law, the way we get married, the calendar (Julius Caesar was the one who basically came up with the 365 days, 12 months, leap years).</p>

<p>We’re the accumulation of the knowledge of several generations that have come before us. Everything we do is based on that. Otherwise, we’d all just be starting at ground zero.</p>

<h2 id="understanding-the-past-to-mold-the-future">Understanding the past to mold the future</h2>

<p>It’s vital to have some understanding of the past in order to make competent decisions in the present. Not just in your own life, but it’s in understanding others. You need to understand where they’re coming from, where they came from, and what shaped them, and what forces affect them.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The study of history is the best medicine for a sick mind; for in history you have a record of the infinite variety of human experience plainly set out for all to see: and in that record you can find for yourself and your country both examples and warnings: fine things to take as models, base things, rotten through and through, to avoid.</p>

  <p><em>― Livy, The History of Rome</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>People from antiquity had different environments, technologies, and information available, but were just as sharp as we are nowadays. They were not stupid. Even though it might seem that many concepts and ideas were invented by our contemporaries, many lessons, successes and mistakes were already discovered in the past <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>. The real challenge is to incorporate them into our own lives.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Gregory Aldrete portrayed several of these concepts beautifully, so some passages of this article are literal paraphrasing of his discourse.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>Kaiser, Tsar, Tzar, Czar. These are based on the word Caesar.<a href="#fnref:6" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Princep is the reason why we have “Princes” and “Princesses” afterwards. Everyone wanted to be like Octavian.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>It’s from the imperator that we get the word emperor and empire.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>How did these emperors pick the best suited person for that role, while still sticking with the tradition of leaving succession to the emperor’s children? By adopting middle aged men that they considered fit for the role.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>For example, Cicero (assassinated on the orders of Octavian and Marc Antony) is considered one of the prime examples of a good orator, and wrote at length about it. Many of his experiences, skills and tricks are still used nowadays by several orators.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Connection with reality]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/15/connection_with_reality.html"/>
    <updated>2024-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/15/connection_with_reality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
  <div class="youtube-player" data-id="wk2DwbfgmMU" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>As we experience an increase of massive amounts of AI generated content, this note will go through the role and added value that a connection with reality and nature brings not only to your business and craft, but also to yourself.</p>

<h2 id="striking-a-balance">Striking a balance</h2>

<p>Walking or hiking has been a recurrent weekly habit of mine for several years, and its one of my favorite activities.</p>

<p>I find it essential to have a walk outside the office / home and be in contact with the surrounding world, be it in nature or around the city. This is especially relevant for those, like me, who have their daily jobs working at the computer.</p>

<p>I love to be enthralled in the digital world, think about abstract concepts, and use digital devices to, for example, communicate this content to you. But like anything else, a balance needs to be kept, and a balance between the digital and real domains seems essential.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="the-added-value-of-connecting-with-reality">The added value of (connecting with) reality</h2>

<p>As generative models get better, more and more people will just assume that a given piece of text, image or video is likely fake, and I believe there will be an increased demand for a connection with the real world through experiences such as in-person events, travel, spirituality, or consumption of digital content by certified entities.</p>

<p>Businesses and creators that prove their connection with the real world and real people, will likely have an edge and rise against the noise.</p>

<p>So if you’re creating a business, a piece of content, anything really, think how it relates with the real world. Ask yourself: how can you provide that connection? How can you provide <em>reality as a service</em>?</p>

<h2 id="keep-yourself-connected-with-reality">Keep yourself connected with reality</h2>

<p>Apart from all this, and just as important, it’s for <em>you</em> to maintain <em>your</em> contact with reality.</p>

<p>So if you feel you spend too much time around the internet, digital devices, TV series, etc, I invite you to the outdoors, the world outside. It’s free, it’s accessible. You just need to open the door and step out, provided you are fortunate enough to have the required physical capabilities. I’m pretty sure that it will make your life much better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview Learnings from former CIA Intelligence Officer]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/12/interview_learnings_cia.html"/>
    <updated>2024-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/12/interview_learnings_cia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
  <div class="youtube-player" data-id="vlFAvIOUFCk" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>I’ve been getting into the habit of writing down what I learned from content I consume and I’ve recently seen an interview with Andrew Bustamante,
a former CIA intelligence officer on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QVVe2rCHtN0">Diary of a CEO with Steven Bartlett</a>.</p>

<p>Andrew Bustamante is a former covert CIA intelligence officer, US Air Force combat veteran, and Fortune 10 corporate advisor, who founded Everyday Spy, where individuals and teams are trained to leverage influence, intelligence and intent. Techniques once reserved for elite spy agencies can now serve everyday people in their pursuit of personal and professional objectives.</p>

<p>Andrew shared his candid and unfiltered views on the human condition and how his previous CIA intelligence officer (commonly known as a spy) can be leveraged towards gaining an advantage in business and everyday life, and in this article I will share some of the highlights and learnings from this interview. Here are my key takeaways:</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="do-an-action-any-action">Do an Action, Any Action</h2>

<p>For you to be a step ahead of everyone else just do an action, any action, and you’ll already be ahead of everyone. Even if you fall, you’ll already be four steps ahead of everyone else.</p>

<h2 id="two-kinds-of-people">Two kinds of people</h2>

<p>There are two kinds of people:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Those who fall victim to their fears and will be stuck on a cycle of consumption, he calls them the cogs, the bobbleheads. He mentions that we actually need them, because they are needed by the kind.</li>
  <li>Those who face their fears and produce the things that the cogs want, but fear of doing. So they exploit them.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="motivation--manipulation">Motivation &amp; Manipulation</h2>

<p>Motivation and manipulation are two sides of the same coin.</p>

<p>Using motivation just exploits something that people are already prone to do, and we just give them something that they want.</p>

<p>If they’re not motivated, then we use manipulation, so they can actually give us what we want.</p>

<h2 id="moral-flexibility">Moral Flexibility</h2>

<p>Moral Flexibility is a gateway for manipulation, which makes something acceptable in one context, but unacceptable in another context.</p>

<h2 id="public-private-and-secret-spheres">Public, Private and Secret Spheres</h2>

<p>Then there are three spheres: the public, the private and the secret.</p>

<h3 id="public-sphere">Public Sphere</h3>

<p>The public sphere is the safe zone:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It’s what you wear</li>
  <li>It’s what you say in Instagram</li>
  <li>It’s what you state to everyone</li>
  <li>It’s the identity that you want other people to perceive</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="private-sphere">Private Sphere</h3>

<p>The private sphere is what the people in your inner circle see:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They know your birthday</li>
  <li>They know your favorite ice cream</li>
  <li>They are the ones that really know you</li>
</ul>

<p>So it’s small by definition. This makes you feel good and special, and you have this elite group which is distinct from the public.</p>

<h3 id="secret-sphere">Secret Sphere</h3>

<p>The secret sphere is where all of your secrets lie:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It’s the affair you’re having</li>
  <li>It was the molestation you had as a kid</li>
  <li>It’s all of your dark thoughts</li>
</ul>

<p>To move from one person’s public to secret sphere, you need to pass by the private one first.</p>

<p>We want to have someone to tell our secrets, but we don’t have enough trust on the people that are in our private sphere.</p>

<p>Once you get to someone’s secrets, they’ll trust you so much that even if you break their heart. They’ll resist leaving you, because it is very rare to find someone who we can tell our secrets to.</p>

<h2 id="core-motivations">4 Core Motivations</h2>

<p>About the four core motivations, they are described by RICE: Reward, Ideology, Coercion and Ego</p>

<ol>
  <li>Ideology is the biggest driver. This could be politics, values, morals, etc</li>
  <li>Ego comes next. Even showing yourself to the world for people to see and to validate how you want to be seen is ego. Andrew mentioned that Madre Teresa wanted to be seen as someone who is a martyr.</li>
  <li>Reward: Money, sex, alcohol, drugs, etc</li>
  <li>Coercion: this is the negative one, and includes things like blackmailing</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="questions-1-validation">2 Questions, 1 Validation</h2>

<p>If you want to get information from a person, then you can ask two questions and then follow up with the validation.</p>

<p>For example, if the other person mentioned that they have an issue with their wife, then you ask:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Oh what happened?”</li>
  <li>After their reply you ask: “Did she really do that?”</li>
  <li>Again, after their reply, you do a validation, so it doesn’t sound like an interrogatory, by saying for example “Yeah, I had a girlfriend that did the same thing”</li>
  <li>After their reply, you then ask another two questions, and so on and so forth.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="doors-and-windows">Doors and Windows</h2>

<p>Use windows instead of doors when leading a conversation.</p>

<p>Opening a door is when you change the topic completely. For example, if the conversation is about the weather and all of a sudden you ask about someone’s income. The analogy is that you’re breaking through someone’s door.</p>

<p>Instead you’ll want to open a window, which is to leave a hint for the other party that will organically lead them towards a new ramification of the conversation. You open a window by giving a queue, a suggestion, or an implicit conversation seed.</p>

<h2 id="volunteered-information">Volunteered Information</h2>

<p>People will also volunteer information to you, and you can actually assess that by the information that they give you through their statements.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-questions">The Power of Questions</h2>

<p>The person that is asking the questions has the power over the conversation, and not the person who is saying the most words. For example, in the interview it was agreed by both  that Steve was the interviewer, so Steve had the power there.</p>

<h2 id="sadrat-in-business">SADRAT in Business</h2>

<p>Andrew mentioned how the SADRAT methodology can be used in business. SADRAT stands for: spotting, assessing, development, recruiting, agent handling and termination.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Spotting is finding the client, this is, you need to kiss a lot of frogs to get to the prince.</li>
  <li>Recruit means you provide a given product in exchange for their money.</li>
  <li>Assess is about finding if someone is going to be a good productive client, so you can place your Investments on the clients that give you the return on the time span that you want. This can be known through their common traits, their profile, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="detecting-lies">Detecting Lies</h2>

<p>In order to know if someone is a liar, you need to first establish a baseline. Once that is acquired, you need to put pressure on them to see if they react differently.</p>

<p>The difference between good liars and bad liars is that bad liars tend to twitch and turn, as if they were in a hot seat when they get exposed to pressure.</p>

<p>Good liars, on the other hand, they occlude all of these signals. Good liars tend to be the ones at parties that ask a lot of questions, and you felt like they were so friendly, but in reality you know nothing about them.</p>

<h2 id="perception-vs-perspective">Perception vs Perspective</h2>

<p>Perception is your gut view. Perspective is seeing the event through other lenses.</p>

<p>You should not trust your perception, because most of the time it is wrong and it is emotion based. You need to use your rational side to process challenging situations.</p>

<p>To achieve that, you need to be inoculated by getting exposed to small doses of something you fear. For example, asking someone if you’re overweight. You’ll get the physical fear arousal, but once it’s over no real harm was done.</p>

<p>You can train yourself to not respond to that physical jolt to make your emotional part slower, and your rational part faster.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Obsidian Encrypted Backup - Google Drive, Dropbox, OneDrive]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/11/obsidian-backup.html"/>
    <updated>2024-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/11/obsidian-backup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After several years using Evernote, I’ve eventually migrated all my notes into Obsidian, which allowed me to have full control of my notes, in a format that I could use, move, or <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html">leverage upon</a>. As a consequence, my notes would no longer live in the cloud and my personal device, so any redundancy and backups would need to be guaranteed by me, via my personal periodic backups.</p>

<p>Having more than a decade’s worth of notes relying on a single redundancy made me somewhat uneasy, so the options I could think of were either:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Subscribe to <a href="https://obsidian.md/sync">Obsidian’s Sync service</a>, which would recurrently cost $4 every month, <em>every month</em>. My encrypted notes would be tethered to Obsidian’s cloud service</li>
  <li>Have a custom solution that leverage’s Obsidian’s outstanding customizability, compress and encrypt all my notes, and use a cloud service to host this archive. I would have the flexibility to choose any cloud provider I would desire.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’ve chosen option 2., using the Google Drive cloud service, and in this note will share how you can too.</p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="how-to-do-it">How to do it</h1>

<p>The idea is simple: use the <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?search=obsidian-shellcommands">obsidian-shellcommands</a> shell plugin to run a custom script, whenever Obsidian quits. This event is configurable, but I find the application quit event to have the necessary periodicity for my use case, since I often sporadically open Obsidian, write on it, and exit the application straight after.</p>

<h2 id="step-1-custom-script-that-encrypts-and-backs-up-all-notes">Step 1. Custom script that encrypts and backs up all notes</h2>

<p>First, save the below script into a folder in your computer (for example, at <code>/Users/yourunixname/backups/my_backup_script.sh</code>), and update it with your own Obsidian, backup destination folders and your own archive password:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>#!/bin/zsh

obsidian_notes_folder=&quot;&lt;your_obsidian_folder&gt;&quot; ; # For example, /Users/yourusername/Library/Application Support/obsidian
obsidian_notes_tar_archive=&quot;${obsidian_notes_folder}/obsidian_backup.tar.gz&quot; ;
backup_folder=&quot;&lt;folder_where_the_final_encrypted_backup_will_be_placed&gt;&quot;; # For example, /Users/yourusername/Library/CloudStorage/GoogleDrive/MyDrive/backup_folder

echo &quot;Starting to compress obsidian notes...&quot; ;

# Create a .tar archive that contains all the contents inside the obsidian folder
tar -czf ${obsidian_notes_tar_archive} ${obsidian_notes_folder}/obsidian_backup

# Compress the .tar archive into an encrypted .7z with password &quot;PasswordOfYourChoosing&quot;
# In this example, 7za installed from the nix package manager is used (https://nixos.org/), but you can use 7za from any other reputable source
/Users/yourusername/.nix-profile/bin/7za a -tzip -mem=AES256 -mx=0 -mmt=12 -pPasswordOfYourChoosing ${obsidian_notes_folder}/obsidian_backup.7z ${obsidian_notes_tar_archive} ;

# Move the .7z file into the the backup folder (e.g. your Google Drive / Dropbox / OneDrive folder)
mv ${obsidian_notes_folder}/obsidian_backup.7z ${backup_folder}/obsidian_backup.7z ;

echo &quot;Finished compressing and moving to backup folder&quot;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>(Download this <a href="https://gist.github.com/lopespm/fcfceebc311d8ba364919cdf4fa61e8d">script from GitHub Gists</a>)</em></p>

<p>The comments are mostly self-explanatory, but essentially this is what the script does:</p>

<ol>
  <li>First create a .tar archive that contains all the contents inside the obsidian folder</li>
  <li>Compresses the .tar archive into a password encrypted <code>.7z</code> file. Remember to update the password with your own private password</li>
  <li>Moves the <code>.7z</code> file into the destination folder, which could be the folder used by your cloud storage sync folder of choice (e.g. your Google Drive / Dropbox / OneDrive folder).</li>
</ol>

<p>Since the final file name on <code>3.</code> is always the same, it will be re-written, but likely your cloud storage sync will keep track of the different versions, as they change, which could progressively inflate your quota usage. If that is a problem, just purge them periodically using your cloud storage interface.</p>

<p>You can test drive your script by granting execution privileges to your script (<code>chmod +x &lt;script_file_name&gt;</code>), and running <code>./&lt;your_script_name&gt;</code>. Your final encrypted archive should appear on the final <code>backup_folder</code></p>

<h2 id="step-2-run-the-script-when-obsidian-quits">Step 2. Run the script when Obsidian quits</h2>

<p>Now that we have the script ready, it makes our life easier if it is run automatically, upon a given Obsidian event, such as when Obsidian quits. Running a shell script upon a given Obsidian event is made easy by using the <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?search=obsidian-shellcommands">obsidian-shellcommands</a>. These are the steps to set it up:</p>

<p><strong>1.</strong> Go to Obsidian -&gt; Settings. Then select the “Community Plugins” option.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Community Plugins">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p0.webp" aria-label="Community Plugins" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p0.png" aria-label="Community Plugins" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p0.png" aria-label="Community Plugins" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>1.1.</strong> On the “Community Plugins” option, click “Browse”. There, search for “Shell”. The one you want to install is <a href="(https://obsidian.md/plugins?search=obsidian-shellcommands)">Shell Commands by Jarkko Linnanvirta</a></p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Browse for Shell Commands">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p2.webp" aria-label="Browse for Shell Commands" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p2.png" aria-label="Browse for Shell Commands" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p2.png" aria-label="Browse for Shell Commands" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Selected Shell Commands Plugin by Jarkko Linnanvirta">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p3.webp" aria-label="Selected Shell Commands Plugin by Jarkko Linnanvirta" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p3.png" aria-label="Selected Shell Commands Plugin by Jarkko Linnanvirta" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p3.png" aria-label="Selected Shell Commands Plugin by Jarkko Linnanvirta" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>2.</strong> Now that the plugin is installed, go again to Obsidian -&gt; Settings. You should see in the bottom left, under the “Community plugins” pane, an option named “Shell commands”. Click it.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Shell Commands Plugin entrypoint">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p4.webp" aria-label="Shell Commands Plugin entrypoint" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p4.png" aria-label="Shell Commands Plugin entrypoint" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p4.png" aria-label="Shell Commands Plugin entrypoint" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>3.1.</strong> On the “Shell commands” plugin, select the “Shell commands” tab, and inside it, click “New shell command”, and the created row, click its respective cog icon. This will show you a new modal with several tabs.</p>

<p><strong>3.2.</strong> On this command modal, select the “Environments” tab and insert on the “Default shell command” something like this: <code>zsh /Users/yourunixname/backups/my_backup_script.sh</code>. This assumes that your script is located at <code>/Users/yourunixname/backups/my_backup_script.sh</code></p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="New shell commands on the Environment tab">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p5.webp" aria-label="New shell commands on the Environment tab" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p5.png" aria-label="New shell commands on the Environment tab" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p5.png" aria-label="New shell commands on the Environment tab" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>3.3.</strong> Still on this command modal, select the “Events” tab. There you can choose when should the script execution be done. For example, search for “Obsidian quits”, and enable it (there is a toggle in the right)</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="New shell commands on the Events tab">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p6.webp" aria-label="New shell commands on the Events tab" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p6.png" aria-label="New shell commands on the Events tab" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p6.png" aria-label="New shell commands on the Events tab" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="How Shell Commands looks like when everything is configured">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p7.webp" aria-label="How Shell Commands looks like when everything is configured" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/obsidian_backup/p7.png" aria-label="How Shell Commands looks like when everything is configured" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/obsidian_backup/p7.png" aria-label="How Shell Commands looks like when everything is configured" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p><br /></p>

<p>All done! After performing these steps, your backup script will run whenever you chose to, and the encrypted backup will be created and placed in the location that you chose on <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/11/obsidian-backup.html#step-1-custom-script-that-encrypts-and-backs-up-all-notes">Step 1.</a> above 🎉</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment Tracker - Free Spreadsheet Template]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html"/>
    <updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Your current net worth?</li>
  <li>How much money do you have in the bank?</li>
  <li>Which are your most profitable investments?</li>
  <li>Which investments do you currently have?</li>
  <li>How much of your revenue (e.g. salary) contributes to your wealth?</li>
  <li>How did the above evolve over time?</li>
</ul>

<p>If coming up with the above answers is hard, or their values are fuzzy, then it might be time to revamp your <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/08/26/uk-investment-guide.html">investment</a> tracking.</p>

<p>This article will:</p>

<ul>
  <li>share a Google Spreadsheet template to track your investments, and explain it</li>
  <li>provide a guide on how to use it</li>
  <li>suggest a simple process to make sure the above questions will not be a problem anymore</li>
</ul>

<div>
  <div class="youtube-player" data-id="dX2UVWU97vc" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="the-template">The Template</h1>

<h2 id="get-it">Get it</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Download / copy the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1cR0oOcvwQIXsdOEbtFBoneOfdzrVYB_QkADc1h0BTBk/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheet Template here</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#how-to-use-it">How to use it</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-it-is-structured">How it is structured</h2>

<p>The template has several sheets, which are built to have the essential tracking elements that can be immediately used, while also allowing for extensibility for your own custom case.</p>

<h3 id="dates-sheet">Dates sheet</h3>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Dates Sheet">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/pdates.webp" aria-label="Dates Sheet" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/pdates.png" aria-label="Dates Sheet" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/investment-tracker/pdates.png" aria-label="Dates Sheet" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p>The entire sheeet revolves around these dates. Each of these represents the temporal <em>snapshot</em> of all your assets. All the other sheets use these dates as the starting point for their values, and this would be first thing you would add whenever entering a new series of entries</p>

<h3 id="revenue-sheet">Revenue sheet</h3>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Revenue Sheet">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/prevenue.webp" aria-label="Revenue Sheet" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/prevenue.png" aria-label="Revenue Sheet" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/investment-tracker/prevenue.png" aria-label="Revenue Sheet" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p>Represents all the resources <em>coming in</em>, which are not a result of your investments. This could be the income from your salary, side-hustle, the app you are selling on the app store, etc.</p>

<h3 id="account-sheet">Account sheet</h3>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Account Sheet">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/paccount.webp" aria-label="Account Sheet" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/paccount.png" aria-label="Account Sheet" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/investment-tracker/paccount.png" aria-label="Account Sheet" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p>There are two example account sheets provided with the template, each representing a different account on your portfolio, but you can add how many you would need. These could be your bank account, transaction broker, private pension, etc. To create a new one, grab one of the example account sheets, and copy it into a new spreadsheet.</p>

<p>On the template, the <em>Example Account1</em> shows how a bank account could roughly look like, and <em>Example Account2</em> how an investment platform (such as Vanguard) could look like.</p>

<p>Each of the account sheets is structured in the following way:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Current status: a look at the present, and comparison with the last update
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Date Column</strong>: referenced from the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#dates-sheet">dates sheet</a>, representing the date of this current <em>snapshot</em></li>
      <li><strong>Top up movement</strong>: any money that you deposited in this account since the last date, would be accounted for here. For example, salary that is deposited, on deposits made in an investment broker. The objective here is to keep track of the money coming into a specific account, so that its performance doesnt look better than it really is.</li>
      <li><strong>Not Invested</strong>: all uninvested money sitting in the account. For example, money in a bank account which does not yield interest.</li>
      <li><strong>Invested</strong>: all money invested in this account. For example, the amount of money invested in a transaction broker, which is currently invested in stocks or ETFs.</li>
      <li><strong>Investment Delta</strong>: the investment difference between the current date and the last date.</li>
      <li><strong>Investment Delta, minus topup</strong>: the investment difference between the current date and the last date, minus the top up. This value attempts to represent how much money was actually generated by the investment since the last date.</li>
      <li><strong>Total</strong>: the total invested and not invested amount in the account.</li>
      <li><strong>Total Delta</strong>: total difference between current date and last date.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Expected gains: predictions of investment gains
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Expected Yearly Growth % (Gross)</strong>: for example, if overall the invested money is in a Fixed Term Deposit, this value would represent the gross yearly interest accrued from it, pre-taxes.</li>
      <li><strong>Expected Yearly Growth % (Net)</strong>: this value represents the actual expected gains from this investment. For example, taking the Fixed Term Deposit example above, this would be the expected yearly interest, after taxes.</li>
      <li><strong>Expected gains 6 months / 1 year / etc</strong>: taking into consideration the <em>Expected Yearly Growth % (Net)</em>, which would accrue gains from the investment over these time spans.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="summary-sheet">Summary sheet</h3>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Summary Sheet">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/psummary.webp" aria-label="Summary Sheet" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/investment-tracker/psummary.png" aria-label="Summary Sheet" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/investment-tracker/psummary.png" aria-label="Summary Sheet" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<p>This is where it all comes together. All the accounts are summed up, resulting in these new relevant columns:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Total</strong>: the total across all investments, for a given date</li>
  <li><strong>Total Delta</strong>: total difference between current date and last date.</li>
  <li><strong>Total Delta minus Revenue (i.e. profit / loss)</strong>: the aim of this column is to roughly represent how much of your net worth is being eaten up by your expenses:
    <ul>
      <li>If this value is negative, it means that either your costs are too high, your investments are not yielding yet high values, or both.</li>
      <li>If this value is neutral, it means that your overall investments are completely covering your costs.</li>
      <li>If this value is positive, it means that your overall investments are not only covering your costs, but are also increasing your net worth on top.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-to-use-it">How to use it</h2>

<h3 id="set-up">Set up</h3>

<ol>
  <li><a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#get-it">Copy the template</a>, by opening it and clicking on <em>File -&gt; Make a Copy</em></li>
  <li>Go to the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#dates-sheet">dates sheet</a>, and leave only the top two dates. The first date would be the previous month, and the second would be the current month. Delete the rest.</li>
  <li>Go to the other sheets, and delete all the rows which don’t have a date now</li>
  <li>Zero out the first line on each of the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#account-sheet">account sheets</a> for <em>Top up Investment</em>, <em>Not Invested</em> and <em>Invested</em>.</li>
  <li>Zero out the first line of the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#revenue-sheet">revenue sheet</a>; or add your revenue from that month.</li>
  <li>Use the existing example accounts to host your own accounts. If a new account is needed:
    <ul>
      <li>Copy one of the account sheets, by right clicking on the sheet’s tab, and selecting <em>Duplicate</em></li>
      <li>Add a new column to the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#summary-sheet">summary sheets</a>, representing the new account. Change its formula’s value to get the information from your new sheet. You can do this by selecting the cell and changing the name of the referenced sheet, to the name of your new sheet. For example, from <code>'Example Account 2'!G2</code> to <code>'Monzo Bank Account'!G2</code>.</li>
      <li>Still in the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#summary-sheet">summary sheets</a>, double click the chart, select the <em>Setup</em> tab, and add the range of the new column to the list. For example, if the new column was on the <em>D</em> column, then the data range would change from <em>H7,A2:A1000,B1:B1000,C1:C1000,G1:G1000</em> to <em>H7,A2:1000,B1:B1000,C1:C1000,<strong>D1:D1000</strong>,G1:G1000</em>. Then, on the <em>Series</em> section of the <em>Setup</em> tab, click on <em>Add Series</em> and add the one from your new account.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="recurrent-workflow">Recurrent workflow</h3>

<p>Once you have the above set up, I suggest that on the first days of every month, right after your main source of income is deposited (e.g. salary), that the sheet is updated with the current values of each of the accounts. This is key, and using a recurrent calendar event will help you make sure this is done. If this update is not made periodically, eventually there will be gaps in the tracking, and its data will lose relevance. The process would look something like this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Add the current date to the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/09/01/investment-tracker.html#dates-sheet">dates sheet</a></li>
  <li>On each the the accounts, expand the date to the new one, and fill in the current <em>Top up Investment</em>, <em>Not Invested</em> and <em>Invested</em> values</li>
  <li>All done!</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h1>

<p>Feel free to expand and customize the above tracker to your needs, and let me know how it could be improved and which was its impact on your investment tracking. Would love to hear your thoughts about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UK Investment Guide]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/08/26/uk-investment-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2024-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/08/26/uk-investment-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The sooner investments are made, the more profound their results will be, and if you are living in the United Kingdom and not taking advantage of its welcoming investment opportunities to put your money to work for you, you’re missing out. Don’t postpone it.</p>

<p>This article provides concise, practical, straight to point suggestions on how to kick start your investment journey.</p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h1>

<ul>
  <li>I am not a qualified licensed investment advisor. The contents in this article are not financial advice.</li>
  <li>I will not and cannot be held liable for any actions you take as a result of anything you read here.</li>
  <li>Always do your own research and seek independent financial advice when required.</li>
  <li>When investing, your capital is at risk. Investments can rise and fall and you may get back less than you invested. Past performance is no guarantee of future results. Other fees may apply.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="foundation">Foundation</h1>

<h2 id="why">Why</h2>

<p>Growing wealth has been vilified and correlated with the unscrupulous and greedy. Far from that, money is more than a number and currency: it provides options. The option to say <em>no</em> to that task / job you don’t want to do; options to provide for your family and close ones; options to give back to society and the world; options to support your health, well being and comfort. There is nothing wrong with that.</p>

<p>So why would you consider investing your hard earned money? Why do it as early as possible?</p>

<p>Let’s say you are 20 years old, and have zero net worth. No money in the bank, no assets. After that point, every month, <strong>for the next 30 years, you invest £250 every month</strong> (roughly equating to £8.4 per day). Let’s assume that investment yields a yearly 7% return on investment every year, on average (which is viable assumption, considering the SP500 historical performance). By 50 years old, this would be the <a href="https://www.unbiased.co.uk/discover/personal-finance/savings-investing/compound-interest-calculator">result</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Contributions: £90,000 (250 * 12 * 30)</li>
  <li>Interest earned: £193,382 (thanks to compound interest you will gain this much. Einstein called compound percentages the 8th wonder of the world)</li>
  <li>Total: £283,382</li>
</ul>

<p>Imagine how much higher these values could get if the invested values are increased. You can use this <a href="https://www.unbiased.co.uk/discover/personal-finance/savings-investing/compound-interest-calculator">calculator</a> to have an idea.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Investment returns over 30 years">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/uk_investment_strategy/investment_30_years.webp" aria-label="Investment returns over 30 years" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/uk_investment_strategy/investment_30_years.png" aria-label="Investment returns over 30 years" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/uk_investment_strategy/investment_30_years.png" aria-label="Investment returns over 30 years" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<h2 id="long-term-game">Long term game</h2>

<p>Forget about get rich quick schemes. Going down that path would be comparable to buying lottery ticket and wish for a winning prize, but the odds of getting struck by lightning are nearly <a href="https://www.accuweather.com/en/leisure-recreation/powerball-mega-millions-or-a-lightning-strike-which-has-better-odds/882156">20,000 times higher</a> than hitting the winning numbers for the next Powerball jackpot.</p>

<p>Building wealth is a long term game which requires discipline, structure and time.</p>

<h1 id="methodology">Methodology</h1>

<h2 id="create-an-emergency-fund">Create an emergency fund</h2>

<p>Make sure you have the equivalent of about 6 liquid months worth of your income available. Life is unpredictable, so make sure you have a reachable safety net which you can rely on and use promptly.</p>

<h2 id="pay-off-your-consumer-debts">Pay off your (consumer) debts</h2>

<p>Compound investment works both ways:  the more you invest, the more your wealth “snowball” will pick up along the way, growing exponentially. On the other hand, if you have debts that require you to pay interest, the inverse applies, progressively eating into your wealth.</p>

<p>As such, gather all your debts, order them by their interest rate, and make sure to pay the ones with the highest interest rate first. Prioritize non-equity based debts, such as credit card debts. Mortgages are equity based, so a portion of your payments goes towards your equity, so they would have less priority compared with pure consumer debt, but make sure they will not overburden you.</p>

<h2 id="budget">Budget</h2>

<p>Budgeting doesn’t mean living in extreme frugalness. Budgeting is about knowing what you <em>need</em> and <em>want</em>, and how much of your income would you be willing to allocate to them. Budgeting makes it easier to reason about your expenses, and having control over them, rather than them controlling you.</p>

<p>Make it as simple or complicated as you would want. You can start by putting in a sheet your monthly income, and subtract from it your fixed (e.g. rent, mortgage, internet bill) and variable expenses (e.g. entertainment, electricity bill, travel). In the end, the objective is that you have a better grasp of how much comes in / goes out. This will inform you on how much disposable income you will have available towards investments.</p>

<h2 id="automate">Automate</h2>

<p>Unless you are a professional trader, you don’t want to spend the entirety of your (limited) time and energy maintaining your investments. If so, that becomes a chore / job by itself. The whole point is to make money work for you, not the contrary.</p>

<p>So automate everything as much as possible. What you can’t automate, make it into a well defined process that requires minimal effort.</p>

<p>I suggested you review / maintain your investments only once per month, <em>every month</em>. If you are an employee, make this shortly after your paycheck comes in.</p>

<h2 id="systematize-know-where-your-assets-are-visit-them">Systematize. Know where your assets are. Visit them.</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Every month, invest as much as possible from your income (this amount would be informed by your budget, and your risk appetite). You can also automate this process by scheduling a periodic amount from your bank account into your investment platform. I don’t particularly like this full automation strategy, since I prefer to adapt my investment amount to what I predict my spending will be on the following month, allowing for a tighter / more aggressive investment strategy. I personally prefer to have as little uninvested money as possible. YMMV.</li>
  <li>Make a spreadsheet. Doesn’t need to be fancy, just functional. It will only be used by you (in principle), so organize in however way you think it is best. Personally, I have different pages for each bank, trading platform, p2p platform, etc. Each of these pages has an history of the current invested amount in these platform, per month. Then an extra page summarizing / summing up all of these assets, with some optional graphs. Having this visual historical summary of all your assets in a single place is gratifying. Seeing how far you came on your investment journey, explicit in a graph, is incredibly fulfilling and powerful.</li>
  <li>Update this spreadsheet periodically, and re-balance your assets as needed. I recommend every month, right after you receive your salary. There are ways to do it automatically, but taking this time to go through all your assets provides visibility on any gaps and strategy changes that need to be done. Personally, this takes me one hour. That’s how long it takes to perform maintenance on my investments: <em>1 hour every month, that’s it</em>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="diversify-adapt-to-your-situation">Diversify. Adapt to your situation</h2>

<p>Having your investments diversified across different baskets allows you to balance your risks are diffuse your liabilities across different spaces, which ultimately protects you.</p>

<p>The strategy you would want to adopt for your investments in your 20s, likely won’t be the same as the strategy in your 60s. For example, later on in life, you might want to invest in safer investment vehicles, such as UK Government bonds (essentially, the country would need to go bankrupt for you to lose your money), savings accounts, cash ISAs and real estate.</p>

<h1 id="investment-vehicles">Investment Vehicles</h1>

<p>With our foundations in place, it’s time to dive into the nuts and bolts.</p>

<h2 id="max-out-your-workplace-pension">Max out your workplace pension</h2>

<p>Usually, if your are employed, your employer will make regular payments into your <a href="https://www.moneyhelper.org.uk/en/pensions-and-retirement/pensions-basics/the-different-pensions-you-can-get-if-you-live-and-work-in-the-uk">pension</a> pot on your behalf. And, depending on the plan you belong to, you may also make monthly contributions which will be taken from your salary. Some employers increase their contributions if you increase the monthly amount you put aside as well. This tends to be a direct match – if you put aside an extra 1%, they add an extra 1%, but there will be a maximum level they will match.</p>

<p>There are two allowances you should keep in mind:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Your annual allowance is the maximum level of total pension contributions to all of your pensions (made by yourself, your employer(s) or anyone else) that will receive tax relief in a tax year. It is currently £60,000, although could be lower if you have an adjusted income over £240,000 or you have already made a taxable withdrawal from any of your pension plans.</li>
  <li>The lump sum allowance (LSA) is the maximum amount of tax-free cash you can take from your pension savings in your lifetime. You can take 25% of your pot tax-free, as long as this amount is not higher than the LSA.  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="own-the-world-stocks-etfs">Own the World: Stocks, ETFs</h2>

<p>Google, Apple, Tesla, NVIDIA: what if you could own a part of them and profit from their earnings by receiving dividends from them and / or getting capital gains from their (hopefully) raising share prices? </p>

<p>Turns out, you can. Either by buying their individual stocks, or better yet, you can invest on a index fund, such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_S%26P_500_companies">S&amp;P 500</a>.</p>

<h3 id="sp-500">S&amp;P 500</h3>

<p>S&amp;P 500 contains the top 500 U.S.A. publicly traded companies with a primary emphasis on market capitalization. Most interestingly, this list isn’t manually curated by a human or an opaque heuristic. The list is based on the market capitalization only, and it is considered one of the best gauges of large U.S. stocks and even the entire equities market because of its depth and diversity. This dilutes the risk you are exposed to, and historically has provided a realistic yearly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S%26P_500">~7.5%</a> return on investment.</p>

<p>You can’t invest directly in the S&amp;P 500 because it’s an index but you can invest in one of the many funds that use it as a benchmark and track its composition and performance.</p>

<p>To make it easier, you can get a S&amp;P 500 Exchange-traded fund (ETF). ETFs and index funds are similar in many ways but ETFs are considered to be more convenient to enter or exit.  They can be traded more easily than index funds and traditional mutual funds, similar to how common stocks are traded on a stock exchange.</p>

<p>Here are two S&amp;P 500 ETFs, which have a low maintenance cost:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.vanguard.co.uk/professional/product/etf/equity/9503/sp-500-ucits-etf-usd-distributing">S&amp;P 500 UCITS ETF - Distributing (VUSA)</a>: the dividends are paid out to you, and you can choose to reinvest them, invest them elsewhere, or just cash them out.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.vanguard.co.uk/professional/product/etf/equity/9694/sp-500-ucits-etf-usd-accumulating">S&amp;P 500 UCITS ETF - Accumulating (VUAG)</a>: the dividends are automatically reinvested into the ETF, which makes the process more automatic, in case you want to reinvest your earnings (which likely, you should). Note that, even though these dividends are reinvested directly into the ETF, they are still <a href="https://monevator.com/income-tax-on-accumulation-unit/">considered as earnings by the HMRC</a>, so in the tax perspective, there is no difference between distributing and accumulating.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="other-etfs">Other ETFs</h3>

<p>Investing on a S&amp;P 500 is already a significant step up from plain low interest savings accounts, but you would be overly exposed to the U.S.A. market. As such, you can consider ETFs which further diversify your exposure, such as the <a href="https://www.vanguard.co.uk/professional/product/etf/equity/9679/ftse-all-world-ucits-etf-usd-accumulating">FTSE All-World UCITS ETF - (USD) Accumulating (VWRP)</a>, which is comprised of large and mid-sized company stocks in developed and emerging markets.</p>

<p>The above ETFs are provided by Vanguard (which tends to have low maintenance costs for their ETFs), and can be bought in several trading platforms, but there are many other reputable companies providing similar ETF, such as BlackRock.</p>

<h3 id="where-to-buy-these-stocks-and-etfs">Where to buy these Stocks and ETFs</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.justetf.com/uk/how-to/invest-in-uk.html">justetf</a>: is a great website to explore and get details on costs and performance of an ETF you are aiming to invest in</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.vanguardinvestor.co.uk/">Vanguard</a>: if you are starting out on your ETF investment journey, I strongly suggest this platform to invest in your ETFs. Making deposits and managing investments is straightforward and has the right amount of information and process, in order to not be overwhelming</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.interactivebrokers.co.uk/en/home.php">Interactive Brokers</a>: this platform has been around for a long time, is low cost, well-capitalized, provides for very low cost exchange rates, and allows you to invest in a large amount of available stocks and ETFs. The trade-off is that it takes longer to onboard, due to its interface complexity and wide range of tools and information.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.trading212.com/">Trading212</a>: commission-free platform that doesn’t apply any commission on trades, but does charge <a href="https://www.trading212.com/cards">0.15% on currency conversion fees</a>. Make sure to take these hidden costs into account.</li>
</ul>

<p>Vanguard, Interactive Brokers and Trading 212 are regulated in the UK by the FCA. I recommend you spread out your investments in different platforms, in order to reduce the risk / hassle in case any of them is shut down or rendered illiquid.</p>

<h2 id="isa">ISA</h2>

<p>Every time you sell the above ETFs or Stocks at a gain (for example, you bought £100 worth of an ETF, and then sold it for £150), and every time dividends are received (regardless if they are paid directly to you, or reinvested), you will need to pay taxes on them, unless you are still within their respective allowance. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>One way to not pay any of these taxes<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, is to use a stocks and shares ISA. The stocks and shares ISA is one of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/individual-savings-accounts">types of ISA</a>. Other ones being cash ISA (type of savings account that offers tax-free interest), innovative finance ISA (peer to peer lending with tax-free interest) and Lifetime ISA (tax-free savings account that gives a 25% bonus if used for retirement or to buy a first home).</p>

<p>As of the time of this writing, the maximum yearly amount allowed to be saved via ISAs is <a href="https://www.gov.uk/individual-savings-accounts">£20,000</a>. This means that across any of the above 4 types of ISAs you can only deposit in them up to £20,000. You can withdraw them at any point in time. <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>Some specifics on this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Creating a Stocks and Shares ISA is fairly straightforward. The above brokers (Vanguard, Interactive Brokers and Trading212), all allow for you to create a Stocks and Shares ISA account. This account is exactly the same as a normal / general account, except that it is tax sheltered. The ISA account would be separate from a general investment account you might want to create, in case you already reached your £20,000 limit, and want to continue investing (which I recommend).</li>
  <li>You can create ISA accounts in <a href="https://www.moneysavingexpert.com/savings/stocks-shares-isas/">multiple providers</a> of any types you choose, but remember there is a global £20,000 limit. For example, if you have a Cash ISA on HSBC where you deposited £15,000, and Stocks and Shares ISA on Vanguard, you can only deposit up to £5,000 in Vanguard’s Stocks and Shares ISA account. You can transfer your ISA account across providers, to avoid losing your tax free investments.</li>
  <li>If you deposit £18,000 on a ISA account and then withdraw all of it, you will only be able to deposit £2,000 on a ISA account after that (on the same tax year<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>)</li>
  <li>Every year, the annual ISA allowance will renew, and your investments from the previous year(s) will still have tax free gains. As such, avoid at all possible costs to withdraw your investments for these ISA accounts. Even if your ISA investment was made several years ago, their gains will still be tax free.</li>
  <li>Any capital gains and dividend gains yielded from your investments made in an ISA account will be tax free.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cashback">Cashback</h2>

<p>You can earn, while consuming. That is cashback.</p>

<p>The reason why this is possible in the first place, is because products are originally sold at a higher margin price, and cashback mechanisms are essentially a way to clawback part of that extra margin back to you. There are essentially two ways you can claim this: via credit cards (and bank accounts), cashback reward websites.</p>

<h3 id="credit-cards-and-bank-accounts">Credit cards (and bank accounts)</h3>

<p>There are several credit cards and bank accounts that allow you to gain cashback. Usually you can expect a 1% cashback rate, save from their respective promotional periods.</p>

<ul>
  <li>American Express (Amex) cards are overall the best when it comes to cashback rewards, such as the zero-fee <a href="https://www.americanexpress.com/en-gb/credit-cards/platinum-cashback-everyday-credit-card">Amex Cashback Everyday Credit Card</a>. Trade-off being that not every establishment accepts Amex cards, so you will need a fall back.</li>
  <li>Since Amex cards are not accepted on all establishments, it is a good idea to have a backup Mastercard or Visa card, which are widely accepted. Have a browse through these <a href="https://www.moneysavingexpert.com/credit-cards/best-credit-card-rewards/">top cashback cards</a> to have an idea of what is available.</li>
  <li>There are credit cards which have pre-conditions, such as having minimum spend, an associated bank account, maintenance fee, amongst others, so make sure to take these into consideration to calculate your bottom-line</li>
  <li>There are credit cards which collect Avios instead, such as the <a href="https://www.americanexpress.com/en-gb/credit-cards/ba-credit-card/">British Airways American Express® Credit Card</a>. Unless you plan to use them for travel, use their respective perks (e.g. lounge passes), and have spendings that are leveraged by these points, I would steer away from them. This is because there is an <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/b8d7743f-0c81-4406-ad2d-0f84a2cc78a5">associated monetary value</a> with each of these points, and personally I prefer to have these saving readily available on cash.</li>
  <li>Remember to pay your credit card spending every month <em>in full</em>, otherwise you will be hit by the gargantuan interest rates (about 30%).</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cashback-reward-sites">Cashback reward sites</h3>

<p>On top of the above credit card cashback rewards, you can clawback another layer of cashbacks via rewards sites. In the United Kingdom, the #1 site is <a href="https://www.topcashback.co.uk/">TopCashback</a>. To leverage it, just quickly search on their website if they offer rewards for a purchase you are about to make (e.g. hotel booking via Expedia, which easily gets you 10% cashback), use their link, and once you complete the purchase the reward will be available in a few weeks. This is incredibly powerful.</p>

<p>You can leverage other reward sites, such as the perks provided via Amex, that need to be activated, but personally, I wouldn’t bother too much with them.</p>

<h2 id="points--loyalty-cards">Points / loyalty cards</h2>

<p>Another level on top of the above cashback methods, is to use points cards on for your favorite merchants / supermarkets, which  can either provide you direct discounts, or accrue points that can be exchanged later on by discounts or perks. In general they are quick to set up, and their respective cards can be added to virtual wallets, so there is no need to carry their physical presence. For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.nectar.com/homepage">Nectar Card</a>: useful for Sainsbury’s purchases</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.waitrose.com/ecom/my-waitrose/become-a-member">Waitrose Membership</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://secure.tesco.com/clubcard">Tesco Clubcard</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="watch--phone-wallet">Watch / Phone Wallet</h2>

<p>With all of the above credit and points cards, a wieldy and secure way to have them at hand is to add them to your watch or phone. Google and Apple devices largely support these wallets, and adding them is overall straightforward. One aspect I particularly like about this approach, is that carrying around credit cards using wallet appears feels more secure than carrying a physical card, which if stolen, the mechanisms available to block are mostly leveraged via the card provider, whereas via a virtual wallet, apart from have the card’s access walled by the device’s default access (e.g. pin code), the device can also be remotely wiped, if needed.</p>

<h2 id="equity-investments">Equity investments</h2>

<p>Seed investment on companies (such as startups) is not restricted to angel investors and VCs. These investments are now widely available via crowdfunding platforms such as <a href="https://www.crowdcube.com/">Crowdcube</a> or <a href="https://europe.republic.com/">Seedrs / Republic</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>These platforms allow you to contribute towards a round of investment in a given company.</li>
  <li>This is a high risk, high reward / loss business proposition, since there are only very specific conditions in which you can withdraw your investment (e.g. company is acquired, gets IPOed). There is a high likelihood that these companies either take a long time span to <em>exit</em>, or that they will go bankrupt.</li>
  <li>Many of these are covered by a <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/venture-capital-schemes-tax-relief-for-investors">tax relief</a>, such as <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/venture-capital-schemes-apply-for-the-enterprise-investment-scheme">Enterprise Investment Scheme (EIS)</a>, meaning that you can deduce a percentage of your investment from your taxes. For example, if you invest £100 of a company under the EIS scheme, you will be able to deduce £30 (30% of £100) from your taxes (if you do not expect to pay that amount of taxes, then this would not be useful for you).</li>
  <li>Commonly there are associated perks provided by the companies, such as redeemable vouchers on their businesses.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="other-vehicles">Other vehicles</h2>

<p>Other investment vehicles you can consider are real estate (e.g. buy to let, REIT), commodity trading (e.g. silver, gold), forex trading (buying one currency and selling another while attempting to profit from the trade), crypto trading, p2p lending. Even though I have some experience with some of them, these are not my main focus of my investment strategy, so I’ll abstain from making many remarks on them.</p>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h1>

<p>The above guide is not extensive, by all means, and there are thousands of ways to put your money to work effectively, but it is important to not go overboard and over optimize, as too much time spent on these will eventually carve away from other meaningful areas of your life, such as overly obsessing over points optimizations. This is an eventual opportunity cost, and you should be aware that these methods are a means, not the end. Optimize just enough, automate as much as possible, reap the rewards, gain options, and enjoy your life to fullest!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://www.gov.uk/tax-on-dividends">Dividend gains allowances</a>, and <a href="https://www.gov.uk/trusts-taxes/trusts-and-capital-gains-tax">capital gains</a> allowances.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>ISA is a tax avoidance mechanism encouraged by the UK government. Tax avoidance is related to avoiding taxes using mechanisms that are legal and are expected to be used. Tax evasion, on the other hand, is the usage of illegal methods to circumvent and evade taxes.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Stocks and Shares ISA is very similar to its USA counterpart, the Roth IRA, which has a $6.5k yearly limit, and its withdrawal can only be made at age 59.5 tax free.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>A UK tax year runs from <a href="https://www.gov.uk/check-income-tax-current-year">6 April to the following 5 April</a>.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Local (Llama3 8B) LLM extended with WhatsApp + Obsidian Data]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html"/>
    <updated>2024-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog article will describe the implementation of a fully offline Llama3 8B LLM agent with access to WhatsApp Messages and Obsidian notes (or any other data sources), making it able to hold conversations about any of the topics present there. All data stays local, including the data from WhatsApp and Obsidian - it is in fact a <em>personal</em> assistant.</p>

<p>Source code for this project is <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#source-code">available on GitHub</a>.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Header image of Personal LLM">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/personal_llm/showcase_interaction3.webp" aria-label="Header image of Personal LLM" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/personal_llm/showcase_interaction3.png" aria-label="Header image of Personal LLM" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/showcase_interaction3.png" aria-label="Header image of Personal LLM" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<!--more-->

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="motivation--objective">Motivation &amp; Objective</h1>

<h2 id="why-was-this-project-assembled-in-the-first-place">Why was this project assembled in the first place?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I’ve built up a considerable personal database:
    <ul>
      <li>For more than 15 years I’ve been journaling and writing several notes, keeping them aggregated in the same place as I changed their hosting platform. From simple text files, passing by Evernote, and more recently into <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>, into which I migrated all of my written notes <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
      <li>Most of my relevant correspondence for almost 10 years has been made via WhatsApp, which stores all messages locally</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>I’ve realized how powerful it is to reflect on past events and approach them with the lenses of the new experiences and lessons I’ve been accumulating throughout life, but due to the considerable amount of content present in the above data stores, sometimes it is hard to reach and associate the relevant information I am looking for, even though I try to keep the above relatively organized.</li>
  <li>And of course, how great would it be to have a personal assistant with access to all of these, in a self-contained offline fashion?
    <ul>
      <li>Currently, state of the art Large Language Models (LLMs) such as <a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/meta-llama-3/">Llama3</a> are feasible to be run locally on a laptop, which is something that still blows my mind.</li>
      <li>Pre-trained LLMs can have their capabilities augmented (as we will see below) to serve different custom purposes</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>All of this combined meant that it would be feasible to host a state of the art LLM in my laptop, with potential access to my personal files, without requiring this sensitive information to be hosted or processed elsewhere, which was something that had quite an appeal for me.</p>

<h2 id="objective">Objective</h2>

<p>Build an offline assistant with access to WhatsApp messages and Obsidian notes (or any other data sources), using components that don’t fully abstract the process (similar to the approach I took when <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2016/10/06/deep-reinforcement-learning-racing-game.html">creating a deep reinforcement learning agent to play a racing game</a>), to learn more about how LLMs and their infrastructures work.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="building-blocks">Building Blocks</h1>

<h2 id="running-an-offline-llm">Running an offline LLM</h2>

<p>One of the crucial pieces is actually being able to run an LLM locally. Below we will explore the hardware requirements, and software we can use.</p>

<h3 id="the-more-gpu-cores-and-vram-the-better">The more GPU cores and VRAM, the better</h3>

<p>When running LLMs on a personal computer, there are two main factors that influence its inference performance and overall capability to even being able to run them: number of GPU cores, and available VRAM (video RAM, this is, memory available to the GPU).</p>

<ul>
  <li>The more GPU cores available, the more operations can be processed, and machine learning algorithms are all about just finding patterns in numbers</li>
  <li>The more (VRAM) memory available, the bigger the model can be stored in memory and be efficiently processed. For example, if we consider Llama3 with 8 billion parameters (more information in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cpYqED1q6ro">this video</a>) <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:
    <ul>
      <li>One 32 bit float value = 32 bits of memory, this is, 4 bytes (1 byte = 8 bits)</li>
      <li>8 billion parameters = 8.000.000.000 * 4 bytes = 32.000.000.000 bytes ≈ 32GB VRAM, for a full precision model (32 bit float)</li>
      <li>If we would use a quantized model, this is, using lower precision floats to represent the parameters:</li>
      <li>Using half precision 16 bit float parameters: 16 GB VRAM</li>
      <li>Using quarter precision, 8 bit float parameters: 8 GB VRAM</li>
      <li>And if we would use Llama 70 billion parameters, it would amount to 280 GB VRAM (float32), 140 GB VRAM (float16), 70 GB VRAM (float8), 35 GB VRAM(float4)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I personally own a MacBook Pro M3 Max with 40 GPU cores and 128GB of unified RAM (meaning that this memory is available to the CPU and GPU), and it just so happens that Apple Silicon computers (M1, M2, M3 chips) are very capable machines to run inference on LLMs, such as Llama3 8B (full precision), or even 70B models (I’ve personally tested the 70B 4bit model <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> on this machine, and can attest that it runs well and in bounds of memory available, as seen on the calculations above)</p>

<h3 id="running-the-inference">Running the inference</h3>

<p>There are several methods or libraries that can be used for running a LLM in a personal computer. One of the most approachable ones is <a href="https://www.ollama.com/">ollama</a>, which effortlessly allows you (after a quick installation step), to run Llama 3, Phi 3, Mistral, Gemma offline on your computer.</p>

<p>Another possible way is to load the model’s definition from Hugging Face (think of it roughly as a GitHub for machine learning models), and run them via the <a href="https://pypi.org/project/transformers/">transformers</a> library, which vividly encourage you to explore. The amount of freely available pre-trained models to perform tasks on different modalities such as text, vision, and audio is inspiring, to say the least.</p>

<p>For this project, a third option was picked, which was using <a href="https://pypi.org/project/mlx-lm/">mlx_lm</a> library, that essentially still leverages the Hugging Face Hub to provide the models, but optimizes execution by leveraging <a href="https://unfoldai.com/mlx-ml-on-apple-silicon/">MLX</a>, an array framework crafted specifically for harnessing the power of Apple silicon, which was developed by Apple’s machine learning research team.</p>

<h2 id="augmenting-the-llms-knowledge">Augmenting the LLM’s Knowledge</h2>

<p>Now that our LLM is running locally, the question that follows is: how to make it aware of all the contents present in Obsidian notes and WhatsApp messages? We have a few options:</p>

<h3 id="retrain--fine-tune-a-pre-trained-llm">1. Retrain / fine tune a pre-trained LLM</h3>

<p>The idea here is to retrain / fine tune the entire model, or parts of it, to make it knowledgeable about our contents.</p>

<p>A pre-trained LLM comes with the advantage of common probabilistic knowledge about a language or set of languages that can be leveraged upon, which was a result of a long and costly training process. As such, a full retraining of the model that would not retain information about its trained parameters would be out of the question. Instead, there are several ways we can leverage it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Freeze the existing LLM layers (all or a selection of them), add also add new trainable layer layers on top of the existing LLM layers, and only train the trainable and unfreezed ones.</li>
  <li><a href="https://llama.meta.com/docs/how-to-guides/fine-tuning/">Fine tune</a> the existing pre-trained LLM, which essentially modifies all parameters of the model with a low training rate, in order to retain as much existing knowledge and capabilities as much as possible, and avoid <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2402.18865v1">catastrophic forgetting</a>. Because these models are so massive, they are not particularly sensitive to any given parameters being off by a lot, or a little. Their overall size and complexity make up for it, so we can mostly get away with rough updates. To fine tune a model, there are essentially two ways to go about it:
    <ul>
      <li>Load all of the model’s parameters into memory, and modify them directly during the learning process</li>
      <li>Take advantage of the fact that you can multiply two small matrices to get a larger matrix (which is the main bread and butter of deep learning models), so we can try to find out the two smaller matrices instead, meaning that we only need to maintain those in memory. All the parameters of the model are still modified during training, but we don’t need to hold them all in memory at once. That’s what Low-Rank Adaptation (<a href="https://www.entrypointai.com/blog/lora-fine-tuning/">LoRA</a>) fine-tuning method does, and it is one of the most popular ways to fine tune LLMs, along with its QLoRA counterpart (which uses a data type that reduces by 4x the already lower LoRA memory footprint).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Some important aspects of these techniques:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We are compressing our documents into the LLMs internal knowledge, and we have less control of how precisely these models retain the most accurate information. These could lead to hallucinations.</li>
  <li>If the data we want to augment our LLM with is dynamic in nature (which for our case, I would prefer it to be, so that the assistant can have access to the most relevant information when used), this would mean that the model would need to be fine tuned every time an update should be made.</li>
  <li>The training data needs to be structured in a way that makes sense for the model to be used. For example, WhatsApp messages and Obsidian notes would need to be transformed into a sensible training set that would fit the tone I would aim to have for the assistant.</li>
</ul>

<p>Given that I would want to experiment with different types of assistants and different ways to leverage and explore the data in a conversational way, and have access to the most up to date information available, which could be available in several different formats (for example, let’s say I would like to augment the LLMs knowledge with historical CO2 readings of my apartment), retraining / fine tuning the model was not a very inviting approach.</p>

<h3 id="insert-all-documents-into-the-prompt-as-context">2. Insert all documents into the prompt, as context</h3>

<p>The idea here is to provide all the context that LLM needs, in the <a href="https://llama.meta.com/docs/how-to-guides/prompting/">prompt’s context</a>. For example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
&lt;|begin_of_text|&gt;&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;system&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;

You are a AI assistant which answers the user's question based on your prior knowledge
and a collection of the user's documents.

Each of the documents has the format &lt;&lt;document:||document_name||&gt;&gt;||content||.
||document_name|| represents the document name. ||content|| represents the
document's content. Don't show the &lt;&lt;document:||document_name||&gt;&gt; portion to the user.

For example, for: &lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:hello world&gt;&gt;This is an interesting
description of hello.
- ||document_name|| is &lt;obsidian&gt;:hello world
- ||content|| This is an interesting description of hello.

These are the user's documents:
----------
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:lamas running down the street&gt;&gt;The content for lamas
going down the street
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:alpacas running down the street&gt;&gt;That time when I saw a
alpaca running down the street.
----------

&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;user&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;Tell me about that time I've seen animals
running down the street&lt;|eot_id|&gt;

</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
This would be the most convenient approach, but the context window available to a LLM, the number of tokens it can use at one time to generate a response, is limited.</p>

<p>Llama3 8B for example, allows for a 8K token context window, and there have been attempts to extend it further to <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.19553">80K</a> or <a href="https://huggingface.co/gradientai/Llama-3-8B-Instruct-262k">262K</a>, and Google’s Gemini 1.5 Pro can handle a <a href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-gemini-next-generation-model-february-2024/#architecture">1 million token context window</a>, for example.</p>

<p>Given that my Obsidian notes total around 8M characters in content, and my WhatsApp messages around 16M, even if we assume that an average of 1 <a href="https://x.com/karpathy/status/1789590397749957117">token</a> per 4 characters, just the Obsidian notes would clock around 2M tokens, which makes this method infeasible</p>

<h3 id="rag-retrieval-augmented-generation">3. RAG (Retrieval Augmented Generation)</h3>

<p>To navigate around the context window limitation, instead of inserting all the documents into the prompt’s context in one go, we can instead be selective on the information we want to provide on the prompt, depending on the user’s request(s).</p>

<p>For example, if the user asks the AI assistant “what do you think about that gaming project I did 4 years ago?”, behind the scenes we can query a database, and ask it the most relevant results about gaming projects that happened about 4 years ago, and then use those documents content into the prompt’s context.</p>

<p>That’s the overall idea of RAG.</p>

<p>Now, many questions come up:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>Transforming a conversation into a query:</em> How do we transform the user’s prompt + the context of the conversation, into a query that asks our database exactly what the main LLM needs to provide a contextual reply?</li>
  <li><em>Fetching contents related to a query:</em> How can the content database know which are the most relevant content related to a given query?</li>
</ol>

<p>Let’s explore these in the next section.</p>

<h2 id="what-makes-rag-tick">What makes RAG tick?</h2>

<h3 id="transforming-a-conversation-into-a-query">1. Transforming a conversation into a query</h3>

<p>In order to produce a query that transforms an entire conversation into a concise sentence that can be used to get the documents in the database that are most similar to it, we can feed in the conversation into a LLM specialized in creating summarized queries. Here is an example of prompt we can use for it:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>&lt;|begin_of_text|&gt;&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;system&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;   
You are the user's document keeper that has access to all the documents for the user.
Based on the entire conversation only, you will only reply with the question you
will ask to query the appropriate user documents, in order to get all the relevant
user's documents related to the conversation.
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;

&lt;&lt; entire conversation &gt;&gt;

&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;document keeper&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
This is how it would it would look like with actual information about the conversation:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>&lt;|begin_of_text|&gt;&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;system&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;   
You are the user's document keeper that has access to all the documents for the user.
Based on the entire conversation only, you will only reply with the question you
will ask to query the appropriate user documents, in order to get all the relevant
user's documents related to the conversation.
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;

&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;assistant&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
Hi there! I\'m a helpful AI assistant with access to your documents. What can I do for you today?
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;
&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;user&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
What is the name of the first steam game I developed?
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;
&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;assistant&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
Survival Ball, which you published in 2018
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;
&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;user&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
which interesting things could you tell me about it?
&lt;|eot_id|&gt;

&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;document keeper&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
This LLM’s reply would be <code>Which are interesting facts about Survival Ball, a game developed in 2008?</code>.</p>

<h3 id="fetching-contents-related-to-a-query">2. Fetching contents related to a query</h3>

<p>Now that we have a query, such as “Which are interesting facts about Survival Ball, a game developed in 2008?”, how can we get the documents (Obsidian notes and/or WhatsApp messages) that are most relevant with that query?</p>

<p>One possible way would be to perform a custom decomposition of the query phrase, and attempt to look for documents that most referenced similar words to the query. This custom search would be brittle, require careful heuristics to match these, and would not completely take into account what that sentence means, and therefore the matching between query and documents would be likely unreliable.</p>

<p>Instead, we have a much more powerful concept at our disposal, which will help us perform this matching: text embeddings.</p>

<h4 id="text-embeddings">Text embeddings</h4>

<p>The idea behind text embeddings is that if we transform a given piece of text into a vector that is in close proximity to other vectors that have a similar meaning, then from a given query text we can get the most conceptually similar pieces of text to it. <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>For example, if the vectors representing our text were trained to be closer together when they rhyme, then close to the word “dog”, we might have the word “fog” closer to it, but “cat” further away; and conversely, if we trained these to represent their conceptual meaning, then for the word “dog”, we might see the word “cat” nearer to it, but “floor” further away <sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>A mind-boggling implication is that we can perform algebraic expressions on these vectors. For example, if our vectors were trained to represent the meaning of the text we could have the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The classical example is that if grab the vectors for king, woman and man, and perform this operation: <code>(king + woman) - man</code>, the closest vector could be <code>queen</code></li>
  <li><code>(London + Japan) - England -&gt; Tokyo</code></li>
  <li><code>(boat - fly) - airplane -&gt; sail</code></li>
  <li><code>(cow - oink) - pig -&gt; moos</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Likewise, if we probe which are the closest pieces of text related to <code>dog</code>, we could get <code>dogs, puppy, pit_bull, pooch</code></p>

<p>These examples were takes from an actual working <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word2vec">word2vec</a> model that was trained on a google news dataset, which I invite you to explore in this <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1qxnNUojAzIniOXwFZi4y7NlWk4cTzIMZ?usp=sharing">Google Colab notebook</a>.</p>

<center>
  <div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/personal_llm/google_colab_word2vec.png')"></div>
  </div>
  <figcaption class="media-caption" style="margin-top: -7px; margin-bottom: 24px;"> Exploring the above examples using a <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1qxnNUojAzIniOXwFZi4y7NlWk4cTzIMZ?usp=sharing">word2vec model in Google Colab</a></figcaption>
</center>

<p>For our project’s objective, the most relevant property is the latter one. Given query text, we would transform it into a vector, and get the closest vectors in our document (vector) database, which in our project will be supported by a PostgreSQL database using the <a href="https://github.com/pgvector/pgvector">pgvector</a> extension. More about this below.</p>

<h1 id="putting-it-all-together">Putting it all together</h1>

<p>With the prior knowledge for the previous section, we are now in a position to build an system architecture that would best fit our objective:</p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/architecture.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/architecture.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Personal LLM Architecture </figcaption></figure>

<p>The overall idea is that we have a Llama3 8B LLM powering the main AI assistant, which has its knowledge augmented via RAG (Retrieval Augmented Generation) by using another Llama3 8B LLM to generate queries used to retrieve documents from a vector database powered by PostgreSQL. These retrieved documents are then added to the main LLM’s context, and the LLM generates a response based on the retrieved documents + user’s prompt + ongoing conversation. Below are further details for these.</p>

<ol>
  <li>First <em>prepare documents and store them</em> in a vector database.</li>
  <li>and then, when using the chat interface, <em>evaluate the user’s input and conversation</em>, query the vector database for relevant documents, add them as context into the main LLMs prompt, which will output the response that the user will see.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="document-preparation-and-storage">Document preparation and storage</h2>

<p>Before anything else, all Obsidian notes and WhatsApp messages are exported, parsed, transformed into text embeddings, and inserted into the vector database.</p>

<h3 id="exporting-the-data-sources">1. Exporting the data sources</h3>

<p>No export procedure is required for Obsidian, since it stores its text contents inside markdown (<code>.md</code>) files, we just need to point directly to the folder we want to target, which can be a vault’s root folder, for example.</p>

<p>For WhatsApp messages, a <code>result.json</code> holding a structured JSON dump of all messages and their respective metadata, is generated via an open source exporting utility which extracts all messages from the local WhatsApp database present in the mobile device; and a <code>contacts.csv</code> is exported from all Google contacts, in order to enrich the context of the aforementioned messages. A step-by-step process to generate these is described <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm?tab=readme-ov-file#setup-of-data-sources">in the repo’s Readme</a></p>

<h3 id="parse-vectorize-and-persist">2. Parse, vectorize and persist</h3>

<p>With our data sources ready, we can now start extracting relevant information, transforming the relevant content into a vector, and then persist into a vector database. The entire process is made by running:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>$ python create_and_persist_embeddings.py
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Each of the separate Obsidian note paragraphs and WhatsApp messages are accumulated into a single entry, so that locally close contextual content can be readily available and provided to the main LLM AI assistant, when retrieved, so that it has better immediately relevant contextual information about a given topic. It was chosen to accumulate a set of note paragraphs / messages that in total would not surpass the maximum content length of the model used to vectorize the content, which in this case has a maximum content length of 514 (see how to get the maximum content length <a href="https://gist.github.com/lopespm/342bd297f0cd6a2819f69a1ea10e7777">here</a>).</p>

<p>All of these are <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/create_and_persist_embeddings.py#L7">batch processed</a>, so that vector embedding creation can be done much more efficiently. Given that in total there were 25M characters worth of content across these two data sources, these optimizations make a substantial change in the processing run time. Further optimizations could be made in optimizing <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/create_and_persist_embeddings.py#L33-L36">DB insertion commits</a> and streaming each of the data sources contents, instead of storing them entirely into memory.</p>

<h4 id="obsidian">Obsidian</h4>

<p>The python script calls into a <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/obsidian_to_embeddings.py">custom module</a> that traverses through all the markdown (<code>.md</code>) files inside Obsidian’s root folder and its respective descendent folders, and accumulate a group of lines in a given file into a distinct entry.</p>

<p>For example, a Obsidian note called <code>Survival Ball TV.md</code> with this content</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>Only had to take OUYA project, change some resources to match Android TV controllers, detect Nexus Remote.
Test on the Nexus Player
Delete all OUYA related resources
Most of the time was spent (...)
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Would be broken down into to two separate database entries <sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Entry 1.
    <ul>
      <li>DB ID of the entry</li>
      <li>Content: <code>Only had to take OUYA project, change some resource (...)</code> - these would be first lines of the note</li>
      <li>Source: <code>&lt;obsidian&gt;:Survival Ball TV</code></li>
      <li>Embedding: the vector representation the content text (content attribute above)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Entry 2.
    <ul>
      <li>DB ID of the entry</li>
      <li>Content: <code>Unity is pretty great, and has tons of really great stuff (...)</code> - the lines coming after the ones in Entry 1. above</li>
      <li>Source: <code>&lt;obsidian&gt;:Survival Ball TV</code></li>
      <li>Embedding: the vector representation of the content text (content attribute above)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/obsidian_db_entry2.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/obsidian_db_entry2.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Sample Obsidian entries in the vector database <sup>6</sup> </figcaption></figure>

<h4 id="whatsapp">WhatsApp</h4>

<p>Likewise, the script also calls into a <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/whatsapp_to_embeddings.py">custom module</a> that traverses all the messages, and similarly to the approach taken above for Obsidian notes, a set of messages are aggregated into a single entry.</p>

<p>For example, a WhatsApp conversation on the “Deeper Conversations” chat group would be broken down into several different entries, such as [^6]:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Entry 1.
    <ul>
      <li>DB ID of the entry</li>
      <li>Content: <code>message from "Deeper Conversations 💭" to me, on 2021-06-26 10:15:44: And that’s absolutely normal (...)</code> - several lines of the conversation would be aggregated here</li>
      <li>Source: <code>&lt;whatsapp&gt;:xxxxxxxx-yyyyyyyy@t.as</code> (the numbers were redacted)</li>
      <li>Embedding: the vector representation of the content text (content attribute above)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Entry 2.
    <ul>
      <li>DB ID of the entry</li>
      <li>Content: <code>message from "Deeper Conversations 💭" to me, on 2021-07-04 18:37:54: Challenge yourself (...)</code> - another group of several lines of the conversation would be aggregated here</li>
      <li>Source: <code>&lt;whatsapp&gt;:xxxxxxxx-yyyyyyyy@t.as</code> (the numbers were redacted)</li>
      <li>Embedding: the vector representation of the content text (content attribute above)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Entry 3., 4., etc would have a similar structure to the ones above</li>
</ul>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/whatsapp_db_entry.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/whatsapp_db_entry.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Sample WhatsApp entries in the vector database <sup>6</sup> </figcaption></figure>

<h3 id="storage-vector-database">3. Storage (Vector Database)</h3>

<p>The storage of the above entries is handled by a PostgreSQL database using the <a href="https://github.com/pgvector/pgvector">pgvector</a> extension, which allows PostgreSQL to store and query vector attributes, and notably for our project, it provides tha capability to query for the closest vectors / entries related to a given query vector via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosine_similarity">cosine similarity</a> <sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The database is hosted via a docker container, which makes it easily encapsulated and quick to set up and run.</p>

<h2 id="embedding-model">Embedding model</h2>

<p>As we <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#text-embeddings">discussed above</a>, embedding models can be trained have their embedding representation to be optimized and better suit the problem at hand. In general, there are several types of tasks a embedding can be better or worse at, so testing each single model against our problem would certainly inefficient.</p>

<p>Fortunately, a Massive Text Embedding Benchmark was been made and its results are freely available <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/mteb/leaderboard">in this dashboard</a>, which compares several models against capabilities such as classification, clustering and reranking.</p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/text_embedding_model_leaderboard.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/text_embedding_model_leaderboard.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Massive Text Embedding Benchmark (MTEB) Leaderboard </figcaption></figure>

<p>The model used for this project is <a href="https://huggingface.co/intfloat/multilingual-e5-large"><code>intfloat/multilingual-e5-large</code></a><sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" rel="footnote">8</a></sup>, which was chosen for its:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reasonable embedding dimensions (1024), which essentially means of many dimensions will the embedding vector have, allowing for a reduced database footprint and faster retrieval when compared to higher dimension models (such as GritLM-8x7B with 4096 dimensions)</li>
  <li>Good average score across the all tasks (ranking 20th overall)</li>
  <li>And most notably support 100 different languages, <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1911.02116">one of them being Portuguese</a>, which is quite relevant since my notes and messages are largely a mix of English and Portuguese, with some sprinkles of other languages (which this model also supports)</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Related (source code <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/embedding_generator_multilingual.py">here</a>)</em></p>

<h2 id="evaluation-phase">Evaluation phase</h2>

<p>Having all the documents vectorized and available in a database, we can now jump into the evaluation phase, in which we leverage upon these on chat conversation with an AI assistant.</p>

<p>To start the chat session, we only need to activate the respective conda environment <sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" rel="footnote">9</a></sup> and execute:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>$ python main.py
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="the-main-ai-assistant-llm">1. The main AI Assistant LLM</h3>

<p>Upon starting the above script, a Llama3 8B model (<a href="https://huggingface.co/mlx-community/Meta-Llama-3-8B-Instruct-4bit">mlx-community/Meta-Llama-3-8B-Instruct-4bit</a>) is loaded into memory and is instructed to behave as AI assistant / philosopher / psychotherapist (or any other role one so wishes, as <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#results">seen below</a>, and the user is greeted with an initial message, and is able to start inserting a prompt.</p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/greeting.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/greeting.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Greeting message from the AI assistant </figcaption></figure>

<p>This will be LLM having the conversation with the user.</p>

<h3 id="transform-conversation-into-db-query">2. Transform conversation into DB query</h3>

<p>Once the user inserts their prompt, the entire conversation is provided to an auxiliary “document keeper” LLM, which has only one job: transform the entire conversation the user is having with the main AI assistant into concise sentence that aims to represent the information we are interested to provide as context on the upcoming reply.</p>

<p>The document keeper LLM produces a query sentence <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#transforming-a-conversation-into-a-query">using the previously described process</a> (related <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/formulate_query_for_retrieving_content.py">source code</a>), and then transforms it into a vector using the <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#embedding-model">embedding model</a>.</p>

<p>Now we have everything we need. Using this vector representation of the query, we can ask the database which are the top 10 entries which have their respective vectors closest to the query vector.</p>

<p>So for example, if the text query created by the “document keeper” LLM is <code>Which are interesting facts about Survival Ball, a game developed in 2008?</code> (resulting in a vector representation of [1.3, 4.2, 3.3, etc]), then a <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/retrieve_related_content_from_db.py">SQL query such as this one would be made against the DB</a>:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="class">SELECT</span> id, content, source, <span class="integer">1</span> - (embedding &lt;=&gt; [<span class="float">1.3</span>, <span class="float">4.2</span>, <span class="float">3.3</span>, etc]) <span class="keyword">AS</span> cosine_similarity
<span class="keyword">FROM</span> items
<span class="keyword">ORDER</span> <span class="keyword">BY</span> cosine_similarity <span class="directive">DESC</span> LIMIT <span class="integer">10</span>,
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="retrieved-entries-are-added-as-context-on-the-main-ai-llm-prompt">3. Retrieved entries are added as context on the main AI LLM prompt</h3>

<p>Now that we have the retrieved a set of relevant entries we want the main AI assistant LLM to consider towards its reply, we now can add them as context for the prompt for the main AI assistant LLM, very similarly to what was <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html#insert-all-documents-into-the-prompt-as-context">described above</a>:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
&lt;|begin_of_text|&gt;&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;system&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;

You are a AI assistant which answers the user's question based on your prior knowledge
and a collection of the user's documents.

Each of the documents has the format &lt;&lt;document:||document_name||&gt;&gt;||content||.
||document_name|| represents the document name. ||content|| represents the
document's content. Don't show the &lt;&lt;document:||document_name||&gt;&gt; portion to the user.

For example, for: &lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:hello world&gt;&gt;This is an interesting
description of hello.
- ||document_name|| is &lt;obsidian&gt;:hello world
- ||content|| This is an interesting description of hello.

These are the user's documents:
----------
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:lamas running down the street&gt;&gt;The content for lamas
going down the street
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;obsidian&gt;:alpacas running down the street&gt;&gt;That time when they saw a
alpaca running down the street.
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;whatsapp&gt;:aaaaaaa-bbbbbbbb@t.we&gt;&gt;message from &quot;Thy Table Turner&quot; to me, on 2024-03-26 13:15:44: I've just seen a alpaca shuffling down the street
&lt;&lt;document:&lt;whatsapp&gt;:aaaaaaa-bbbbbbbb@t.we&gt;&gt;message from me to &quot;Thy Table Turner&quot;, on 2024-03-26 13:16:32: Pretty sure it was lama though
----------

&lt;|start_header_id|&gt;user&lt;|end_header_id|&gt;Tell me about that time I've seen animals
running down the street&lt;|eot_id|&gt;

</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<h3 id="output-from-the-ai-assistant-llm-presented-to-the-user">4. Output from the AI assistant LLM presented to the user</h3>

<p>We now have everything we need, and the prompt is ready to be <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/main.py">evaluated by the main LLM</a>.</p>

<p>Once the prompt is evaluated by this LLM, we present the output to the user, and then we cycle through the entire evaluation phase again once the user submits their request.</p>

<h1 id="results">Results</h1>

<center>
 <div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"><div class="video-wrapper-two">
  <div class="youtube-player video-frame-two" data-id="QOpAox8iXAc"></div></div>
   <p class="media-caption media-caption-two">Example interaction with the AI LLM, having its role as &#8220;AI assistant&#8221;</p>
 </div>
  </center>

<p>Overall, I’ve found interactions with this AI to be quite interesting, even though sometimes it can output blobs of information that could be cleaner or have better answers. The former can be addressed by tweaking the prompts (i.e. prompt engineering) having increased efficacy towards the behavior I aim the Ai to have, and the latter by either cleaning Obsidian notes directly, or improving the data processing and extraction. Regardless, I find these results to be quite pleasing, useful and even amusing.</p>

<p>For example, the code allows you to choose the AI’s persona by changing <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/main.py#L8-L10">this constant</a></p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/ai_role.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/ai_role.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> The AI&#8217;s persona is customizable </figcaption></figure>

<p>When choosing the AI’s persona to be of a AI “psychotherapist”, this happens <em>(disclaimer: please consult a professional if you require therapy, this agent is meant for pedagogical / entertainment / utilitarian uses only)</em>:</p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/ai_psycotherapist.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/ai_psycotherapist.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> Example interaction with the AI LLM, having its role as &#8220;AI assistant&#8221;  </figcaption></figure>

<h1 id="final-notes">Final Notes</h1>

<h2 id="adding-other-data-sources">Adding other data sources</h2>

<p>This project focuses on using Obsidian notes and WhatsApp messages to augment the main LLM, but virtually any piece of content could be used to augment it. CO2 historical readings, tax documents, financial statements, diplomas, official documents, calendar events, etc. Sky is the limit.</p>

<p>Doing so in practice would be as straightforward as adding an <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm/blob/main/create_and_persist_embeddings.py">additional module to this script</a>, and have it return the pieces relevant pieces of content, and then re-run:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>$ python create_and_persist_embeddings.py
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="inspiring-wealth-of-possibilities">Inspiring wealth of possibilities</h2>

<p>This type of assistant has been something I’ve been daydreaming for a long time, and having the peace of mind that I have full control and customization of it is something that profoundly satisfies me. Not only that, this entire project has an immense learning opportunity for me, and as I researched through it and pieced the puzzle pieces together, I’ve felt humbled and inspired by the explosive amount of possibilities that these models provide.</p>

<p>For example, just browsing through the <a href="https://huggingface.co/models">wealth of freely available models</a>, ready to be used, combined and assembled into different scenarios, leaves me at awe:</p>

<figure class="image"><center><a href="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/hugging_face_models.png"><img src="https://lopespm.com/files/personal_llm/hugging_face_models.png" /></a></center><figcaption class="media-caption"> A sample of different classes of models available in Hugging Face. Each of those having dozens of models, sometimes thousands. All freely available. </figcaption></figure>

<h2 id="further-references">Further references</h2>

<p>I find it fulfilling to learn about a subject by fundamentally understanding its core components, hence the usage of several lower level components, <a href="https://lopespm.com/machine_learning/2016/10/06/deep-reinforcement-learning-racing-game.html">similar to how I previously built a deep reinforcement learning agent</a>), but there are several readily available tools and libraries that handle a lot of the heavy lifting:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.langchain.com/">LangChain</a>: framework designed to simplify the creation of applications using large language models (LLMs). As a language model integration framework, LangChain’s use-cases largely overlap with those of language models in general, including document analysis and summarization, chatbots, and code analysis. This could have been used to abstract most, if not all, of the RAG heavy lifting, which is quite useful.</li>
  <li>Other Vector Databases: although PostgreSQL worked great for this project, there are other possible, such as <a href="https://www.pinecone.io/learn/retrieval-augmented-generation/">Pinecone</a> (this is a externally hosted DB, hence why it was not considered), <a href="https://qdrant.tech/">Qdrant</a>, <a href="https://www.trychroma.com/">chroma</a>, <a href="https://github.com/facebookresearch/faiss">faiss</a> or <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/resources/basics/retrieval-augmented-generation">MongoDB</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://replicate.com/">Replicate</a>: Similarly to Hugging Face, Replicate is a platform that collects various open-source large language models (LLMs), offering AI models for a variety of purposes, including AI text generation, AI image generation, and AI video generation. Developers can use these models through Replicate’s API.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="source-code">Source code</h1>

<p>All source code is available on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm">https://github.com/lopespm/personal_llm</a></p>

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Obsidian is an amazing platform / app which I vividly recommend. I’ve recently migrated all of my notes from Evernote into Obsidian, and couldn’t be happier. Obsidian stores all of the notes in plain <code>.md</code> files that are yours to keep, and allows you to completely customize it to your heart’s desire. For example, I created a custom script that packages all of the notes, encrypts it, and stores that vault into my Google Drive. I would be happy to provide more details about this in a posterior note.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Note that these calculations are based on loading + inference for a batch size of 1. Training a model required far more VRAM<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Specifically, I’ve used the model available on hugging face at <a href="https://huggingface.co/mlx-community/Meta-Llama-3-70B-Instruct-4bit">mlx-community/Meta-Llama-3-70B-Instruct-4bit</a><a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>The process of how these embedding models are trained is a fascinating topic by itself. The idea behind it is that you place a given piece of text on the model’s input and on its corresponding contextual word on the output, and then train the model to attempt to correctly predict the output text. For example, if using a word2vec skip-gram architecture, the input is a single word and the output is trained to be the words around it. The model’s number of weights is lower than the number of pieces of text in the dictionary, so that the model is forced to compress these associations into its weights. Once the model is trained, we use its learned weights to generate an embedding for a given piece of text. When a model is trained on large swathes of text, this simple method yields incredible results.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>In practice, representing these vectors as being closer together when they rhyme, vs when they are conceptually closer, can be achieved by training the embedding model on poetry books and giving higher emphasis on the last words of each line for the former, and training the embedding model on more generic text datasets, such as wikipedia, and using samples around the seed word uniformly as target words (using a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word2vec">skip-gram</a> architecture for example) for the latter.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>These screenshots were taken from <a href="https://dbeaver.io/">DBeaver</a>, and open source universal database tool which is incredibly powerful and well designed.<a href="#fnref:6" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>The pgvector extension supports L2 distance, inner product, cosine distance, L1 distance, Hamming distance, and Jaccard distance.<a href="#fnref:7" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8">
      <p>Related backing “Multilingual E5 Text Embeddings: A Technical Report” paper for this model is available in <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.05672">arxiv</a><a href="#fnref:8" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9">
      <p>Conda provides for a self-contained and easy way to manage packages and environments. Whereas pip is a package manager and virtualenv is an environment manager, conda is both. Here is an <a href="https://docs.conda.io/projects/conda/en/latest/commands/index.html#conda-vs-pip-vs-virtualenv-commands">illustrative comparison table</a><a href="#fnref:9" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aloof]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/06/09/aloof.html"/>
    <updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/06/09/aloof</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="einsteins-rambles">Einstein’s rambles</h2>

<p>I’ve been listening to the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Einstein-Life-Universe-Walter-Isaacson/dp/1847390544">“Einstein: His Life and Universe”</a> audiobook, from Walter Isaacson, which recounts a series of curious stories of how he carried himself through his life.</p>

<p>Einstein was often known to be aloof and lost in this thoughts, so much so that when sailing his clunky 15-foot sailboat named Tinef (Yiddish for “worthless” or “junk”), he often found himself to being rescued more than once by locals near to his rented a summer cottage overlooking Cutchogue Harbor.</p>

<p>Another delightful story was when he lived in Princeton, where occasionally, he would take rambling walks on his own. One day, called into the Institute for Advanced Study, where he worked, and asked to speak to a particular dean. When the secretary said that the dean wasn’t available, he hesitantly asked for Einstein’s home address. That was not possible to give out, he was informed. His voice then dropped to a whisper. “Please don’t tell anybody,” he said, “but I am Dr. Einstein, I’m on my way home, and I’ve forgotten where my house is.”</p>

<h2 id="thinking-in-safety">Thinking, in safety</h2>

<p>Over the past years, I’ve made a habit of having at least one long walk / hike every weekend. I take immense joy - if I happen to go by myself and I’m not actively listening to an audio book or am concentrating on some task - to just wander around and immerse myself in random thoughts, think about hard problems, strategise, and attempt to arrive at sound conclusions. This mental wandering, almost like a meditation, I am sure that happens for most of us, in several instances. Maybe when waking up, during the shower, during a walk, during a boring talk, when contemplating art or nature, etc.</p>

<p>Since we are not omniscient and omnipresent, we have several limitations in knowing how a given action will translate into a set of consequences, so we use probabilistic models and heuristics in our thought processes to discern which are the most likely actions that will help us arrive at a desirable outcome. And the more relevant information and time we have to process our thoughts, the better our results will be.</p>

<p>In all of these, I believe there is one common denominator that is fundamental for that process to happen: safety.</p>

<h2 id="the-influence-of-ones-environment">The influence of one’s environment</h2>

<p>Let’s assume you live with access to information and resources (food, money, shelter, etc), but are living in a situation where your surrounding environment requires you to keep alert and attentive to hazard to your physical / mental wellbeing, or you are in a situation where your social stability is dependent on incapacitating amounts of your energy and time. This could be due to living in a dangerous neighborhood, having overly demanding peers, an abusive household, etc.</p>

<p>Even though there might be a series of limited actions one could take to improve their situation, the constant fight-or-flight severely restricts the opportunities where these action plans can be considered, which eventually leads to reactive actions that could have a number of possible outcomes (good or bad), rather than surgical long term actions that would pave the path towards positive outcomes.</p>

<h2 id="the-takeaway">The takeaway</h2>

<p>While many many situations are not under our control, such as our initial conditions, birth place, etc, which place a default upper bound on any possible outcomes, we do have agency over some parts of our life, and that is what we can focus on. The path to unwanted consequences is a slippery slope made of several small decisions, some under our control, others not. But for the ones we have the opportunity to control, we should.</p>

<p>For example, the peers one <em>choses</em> to have around, the <em>choice</em> to avoid short term pleasures that have a high long term cost, the <em>choice</em> of which country or neighborhood to live in, the <em>choice</em> of which job offer to strive for, etc.</p>

<p>Do notice that the italics are intentional. The <em>choices</em> above assume that those are options you have under your control to pick, which I am conscious that is not always the case.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let me tell you a story]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/05/05/let-me-tell-you-a-story.html"/>
    <updated>2024-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/05/05/let-me-tell-you-a-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
  <div class="youtube-player" data-id="EVn6VGlig1s" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You could never convince a monkey to give you a banana by promising him limitless bananas after death in monkey heaven. How do you cause people to believe in an imagined order such as Christianity, democracy or capitalism? First, you never admit that the order is imagined.</p>

  <p><em>― Yuval Noah Harari</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Take a minute to think of what a nation is. Let’s say the United States of America. What makes someone American? Is it their physique, genetic traits, family lineage, pheromones? No, it’s a concept in their head, which stems from a mix of identity, ideology, personal gains from abiding to that concept (say, gaining currency via a job or a company, that allows you to acquire things you desire), perceived protection and support from peers because they believe you are commonly aligned on core beliefs / concepts.</p>

<p>The same can be said of a company. A company is not a physical being, it’s a shared idea in our imagination. As Yuval mentions in <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Sapiens-Humankind-Yuval-Noah-Harari/dp/0099590085">Sapiens</a>, Peugeot does not really exist, except in our minds. It doesn’t have a body, mind, anything. We have the common belief that Peugeot exists, because we also have the common belief of what a company means, we are aligned on how it should be represented and who can represent it, we recognize it as an entity with rights and duties, and which laws it should abide by.</p>

<p>Laws, as well, are worth nothing if only one person believes in them. They are powerful because a large group of people believe in them, and they expect others to do so as well. That’s why we have courts, prisons, and educational systems for that matter. They are ways to punish, format, and incentivise for the entire group to have the required level of consistency, and keep rowing in the same direction.</p>

<p>That’s why complete anarchy loses its edge on a large scale. It extinguishes the biggest thing Humans have going for them: the ability for large numbers of people to rally in common goals, even though they don’t personally know most of their fellow believers.</p>

<p>As N. K. Humphrey suggests, these ideas, behaviors, or styles that spread by means of imitation from person to person within a culture, also known as memes, could even be considered as living structures, not just metaphorically. The generational propagation of a meme outweighs the lifespan of the Human who created it, so in a way, <em>“we are living inside the dreams of dead people”</em>, as Yuval puts it.</p>

<p>That being said, how do we align on a common concept or belief?</p>

<h2 id="stories">Stories</h2>

<p>We’ve seen above how powerful and valuable having a broad range of concepts aligned within a group of people. They bring value to the whole, but also to the individual.</p>

<p>You can force someone to abide to a given concept via force (coercion, blackmailing, etc), but since they see little value going on for them, they don’t have the incentive to grow that concept inside them, or to propagate that concept to others</p>

<p>Stories however, allow you to describe a world to others that they can interpret in their head, and they can see by themselves how it would benefit them, and the ones around them. It’s an information passage mechanism that allows Humans to communicate and agree on a given concept, and they are everywhere:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Children’s bedtime stories - notice how several of these transmit moral values, this is, expectations of how one should behave in a given situation, in order to be in alignment with the overall group / society</li>
  <li>Novels, biographies, movies</li>
  <li>When interviewees tell you a story of their childhood, how they created their company, how they achieved X, what happened during their struggles, etc</li>
  <li>When a leader, such as a CEO, convinces others of their vision / story, and that future prospects that would derive from working in a certain direction</li>
  <li>When meeting someone, when you talk about your background and your goals</li>
  <li>When you sell you employee skills to an employers, giving a summary of your professional trajectory</li>
  <li>When politicians portray their vision on how they want to improve their nation</li>
  <li>The lore of a nation, tribe, family, and their laws / duties / rights</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="being-a-good-storyteller-is-a-powerful-skill">Being a good storyteller is a powerful skill</h3>

<p>As a species, one of our biggest distinguishing factors is that we are able to goal on highly abstract concepts that only exist in our minds, such as the concept of a company, a nation, a mission, an ideology, an intellectual relationship, the concept of money. As Yuval puts it, <em>“We are the only species with the ability to use language—not just to describe things we can see, taste, and touch, but also to invent stories about things that don’t exist.”</em></p>

<p>A magical thing happens when a group of people interpret and value that concept in the same way, and are highly aligned on it. Narrative is the first and most crucial step for leaders who want to solve big problems and shape the world for the better. After all, a person can have the greatest idea in the world, but if they fail to rally others to make that idea come alive, nothing gets done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Banishing mobile phones from bedroom]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom.html"/>
    <updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-problem--why">The Problem / Why</h2>

<p>When <a href="https://youtu.be/K2tGt2XWd9Q?si=h-xh-X90JWxwF1KU&amp;t=2229">asked</a> about which practices supported Chris Williamson into his current position, Chris mentioned that sleeping with his phone outside of the bedroom and getting a plain alarm clock was his number one change.</p>

<p>I found that statement interesting, especially because I had grown a habit of seeing the occasional video before sleep and being engaged with random distractions shortly after waking up.</p>

<p>Overriding these behaviors required a good amount of self discipline and willpower to be overridden, and fundamentally deviated my focus from what I would want to accomplish on a given day, from the book I had been putting off, or to simply wind down.</p>

<h2 id="alternative-alarm-and-note-taking">Alternative Alarm and Note Taking</h2>

<p>Even though my phone sponsored my distractions, it was also my trusty alarm and favorite way to write down notes and reflections that crossed my mind outside my work desk. So to make the leap of keeping my mobile phone at the bedroom door, I would need to replace the alarm clock, and find a new way to write down my notes.</p>

<h3 id="alarm">Alarm</h3>

<p>This seems like an easy step, but it turns out the selection of alarms is immense, and many of them either do too much, or don’t tick all the boxes.</p>

<p>Essentially, I needed a trustworthy, low maintenance, alarm with essential functionalities that would not flood my dark bedroom with blue light when I wanted to check the time during night.</p>

<p>I essentially browsed through:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.lumie.com/">Lumie alarms</a>: had the enticing proposition of science-backed approach of waking up via warm light or soothing sounds, but didn’t have the basic functionality of having recurrent alarms on the models I was interested in, and required a mains connection, meaning that upon a power outage it could only support itself for a limited amount of time.</li>
  <li>White brand alarm clocks: the selection is immense on <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/s?k=alarm+clock">Amazon</a>, and even though they come in at relatively cheap prices, some require a mains connection, or have short battery life, or need to be recharged every so often, or do too much (like having a bluetooth connection) or use noisy clock dials.</li>
</ul>

<p>After several searches, I’ve stumbled upon Braun alarm clocks. These have been around for decades, and I recalled that Steve Jobs was inspired more than once by products made by Braun when creating his Apple products, due to Braun’s thoughtful approach on how everyday products were designed.</p>

<p>I’ve settled with the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Braun-Digital-Compact-Negative-Crescendo/dp/B083KMCHRH">Braun BC08B</a>. No moving parts, a single AAA battery apparently lasts more than half a year, small, simple, easy to operate, and the beeping sound is not brain drilling. The one aspect I am not fully satisfied is its screen light, which when activated is too strong on a dark bedroom (my mobile phone far excels in this aspect, due to its less intrusive always on black and white display).</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Braun BC08B">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.webp" aria-label="Braun BC08B" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.png" aria-label="Braun BC08B" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.png" aria-label="Braun BC08B" />
           </picture>
         </center>
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="note-taking">Note Taking</h3>

<p>These were the alternatives I found for writing down notes, and jotting down diagrams (as a plus):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Physical Notebook:
    <ul>
      <li>Pros: Easy to use, low cost, no distractions, low maintenance (no battery to recharge, software updates, etc)</li>
      <li>Cons: My handwriting is appalling and my character output is much lower when compared to typing; extra step needed to transfer it a digital means; harder to organize</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>E-Ink Devices:
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://remarkable.com/">Remarkable 2</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: well thought out, clean and focus driven, great writing experience; allows for handwriting to text conversion</li>
          <li>Cons: Able to connect to a Google Drive for free, but works storage rather than syncing, so it is cumbersome to iterate on notes and diagrams between it and other devices</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://supernote.com/">Supernote</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: clean and focus driven, great writing experience; allows for handwriting to text conversion; open <a href="https://trello.com/b/l0COP24j/supernote-a5-x-a6-x-nomad-software-roadmap-2024">roadmap</a> and ideology; easy repair and upgrade</li>
          <li>Cons: As with Remarkable, it does not provide real file syncing, but file copy to Google Drive</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Kindle-Scribe-the-first-Kindle-for-reading-writing-journaling-and-sketching/dp/B09BS26B8B">Kindle Scribe</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: Writing experience seems to be good and on-device handwriting recognition to convert notes into actual text</li>
          <li>Cons: No Google Play apps, meaning that Google Keep and Google Docs would not be available, and no Google Drive sync; the device caters more to readers, rather than writers in my opinion</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/BOOX-Tablet-Note-Air3-ePaper/dp/B0CP3CGG8P">Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: it can use Google Keep and Google Docs apps, since can do almost everything a normal Android table can, but since it uses a e-ink screen and has limited processing capabilities, it does not make a good fit for browsing the web or seeing videos (which is actually a good thing); the default experience and drawing app are bloated offer too many distractions (<a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html">see here how to debloat it</a>); allows for handwriting to text conversion within Onyx drawing app</li>
          <li>Cons: noticeable lag when writing; if not using Onyx’s cloud, it requires extra steps to export and share a diagram / drawing</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.apple.com/uk/ipad-pro/">iPad Pro</a>: even though this device is amazing, it made it too easy to access the same distractions I was trying to avoid, and it also sports an invasive backlit screen that provides too much stimulus while in bed. A hard no.</li>
</ul>

<p>Given the options above, I picked the Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W. Note that the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/BOOX-Tablet-Note-Air-ePaper-Dark-grey-green/dp/B0CHF423CP">color screen version of this tablet</a> is available, but I did not pick it because of Air C’s reduced battery life from the always-on BSR (Boox Super Refresh Technology). BSR allows for a smoother and more responsive experience when writing for example, but that is not actually a problem since I mainly use the Boox to write long streams of text / braindumps, rather than text editing; and BSR also takes it a step closer to a general purpose tablet non-eink display, which starts to defeat the initial purpose. Apart from that, I have a personal preference towards the black and white screen feel.</p>

<p>Learn more on how I customized my Boox Air3 <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html">here</a>.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
           </picture>
         </center>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2>

<p>I have now transitioned to not having any mobile phones in my bedroom, and only having the Boox Air 3, the Braun alarm clock, physical books and my Kindle. I am pretty satisfied with this change, which I’ve noticed to provide more focus time after waking up, more time to think, plan my day, reflect, write my thoughts, read, and wind down.</p>

<p>The most fundamental aspect was having more time to focus on my plan for the day, which translated into a substantial improvement on how productive and consequential my days have become. I welcome anyone to give it a try!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W Setup]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html"/>
    <updated>2024-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom.html">plan to banish mobile phones with access to instant rewards from my bedroom</a>, I’ve acquired a Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, which is a Android tablet with a black and white e-ink screen that is focused on writing and reading <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="house-rules">House Rules</h2>

<p>First of all, <em>why</em> I did get the device in the first place? This was in order to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reduce distractions before going to sleep and after waking up, increase focus on the things that really mattered, block out all other noise, and make it really hard to have access to instant gratification and rewards (such as video consumption)</li>
  <li>Register any ideas and thoughts that occur to me before and after going to sleep, which is one of my most proficuous times for such, and then have them available on other devices</li>
</ul>

<p><em>How</em> to achieve this using the BOOX:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Only two functionalities should be easy and quick to use:
    <ul>
      <li>Write text and notes (via Google Keep and Google Docs)</li>
      <li>Write diagrams and mental maps (via the device’s main app, which has the snappiest performance)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Getting to above functionalities should be as fast as possible, and they should be fast</li>
  <li>The cost to get to other apps and functionalities should be high</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="focusing--debloating">Focusing &amp; Debloating</h2>

<p>The Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W is not an incredibly fast device, and comes with several functionalities, apps, and a launcher that increase the distraction degree, and also slow down the device.</p>

<h3 id="google-play-google-keep--docs">Google Play, Google Keep &amp; Docs</h3>

<p>The first step towards the objective above was to install Google Play (see <a href="https://help.boox.com/hc/en-us/articles/8569260963732-Google-Play-Store">guide here</a>, and afterwards installed these apps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Google Keep</li>
  <li>Google Docs</li>
  <li>Android Hidden Settings - this app provides access to several hidden settings, that allow the access of settings such as enabling the Developer Options in Android (useful in the debloating process described below)</li>
  <li>Lawnchair (see below)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="new-launcher-lawnchair">New Launcher: Lawnchair</h3>

<center>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"><div class="video-wrapper-two">
   <center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now" />
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>Before:</b> Default BOOX Launcher <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> </p>
</div>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"> <div class="video-wrapper-two">
	<center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before" />
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>After:</b> Using Lawnchair Launcher<br class="video-br-end" /></p>
</div>
</center>

<p>The default device’s launcher was replaced by <a href="https://lawnchair.app/">Lawnchair</a>, which is a lightweight, open-source, highly customizable launcher for Android.</p>

<p>What was added to the Lawnchair’s home screen:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Keep</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Docs</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Onyx Launcher - for any custom changes that are only accessible on the device’s default launcher, which are are in practice, so this was eventually something I removed from the home screen as I wrote this note</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Calendar - to add any events or reminders</li>
  <li>A widget to Onyx Sketch app, which is one the only way I found to have that app directly accessible from the Lawnchair home screen, without having to use Onyx’s launcher to do so. The widget can be added by long pressing on the home screen, then select “Widgets”, and then on the “ContentBrowser” section select one of the “Notes” widgets</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="disabling-bloatware">Disabling bloatware</h3>

<p>With all of the above in place, we could start disabling non-essential apps and services, to prevent them from running in the background.</p>

<p>Here are the steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The first step is to enable “Developer Options”, by accessing the system settings via the “Android Hidden Settings” app above, and then finding the <a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/debug/dev-options">Build Number</a> in order to click it enough times to eventually enable “Developer Options”.</li>
  <li>Connect the BOOX to the computer</li>
  <li>On the computer’s terminal run the below commands</li>
</ol>

<p>In general, these are the commands one can run via the terminal to manage bloat apps:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>// See all packages
$ adb shell pm list packages

// See all disabled packages
$ adb shell pm list packages -d

// Disable a package
$ adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 &lt;package_to_disable&gt;

// Re-enable a package
$ adb shell pm enable &lt;package_to_disable&gt;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
And these are the specific ones I used in my BOOX to disable bloatware, without any relevant side effects for my usages:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.appmarket
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.floatingbutton
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.dict
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.mail
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.igetshop
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.easytransfer
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.kime
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.android.ksync
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.calculator
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The commands above should be enough to remove all bloatware, and if you wish to learn more, <a href="https://www.kaspersky.co.uk/blog/how-to-disable-and-remove-android-bloatware/26993/">this article</a> and <a href="https://digitaluncoded.com/cpu-usage-android">this article</a> provide a good overview.</p>

<h2 id="using-an-external-keyboard">Using an external keyboard</h2>

<p>Given that this device is meant to be used in bed, and since it is quite unwieldy to write on the on-screen display, I was looking for an external keyboard that could be somehow attached to the BOOX, that would bestable, low-maintenance and allowed for flexibility on the writing position.</p>

<p>From the keyboards and keyboard stands I’ve researched, the most elegant solution I found was to use <a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-gb/products/keyboards/k480-multi-device-wireless.html">Logitech K480</a>, a bluetooth keyboard with an in-built cradle, detachable batteries (i.e. zero issues related internal battery becoming faulty), incredible battery span (some users reported this to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EoH2bXoNEE0">in the order of years</a>), and wonderful typing experience.</p>

<p>One caveat is that the BOOX slides backward and falls when using the cradle without any other aid. A very simple fix is to get a piece of cardboard, and place it behind the BOOX (see picture below) to create a better fit. It works remarkably well.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
           </picture>
         </center>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="writing-and-drawing">Writing and Drawing</h2>

<h3 id="writing">Writing</h3>

<p>Writing is my main use case for the device, and even though it has some lag when doing it, it works great for me, because I tend to write long streams of ranting text, rather than editing it.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="bYENTrabzXw" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The best mode I’ve found for writing was the “A2” Mode. It has ghosting, but is responsive enough for this use case.</p>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard" />
           </picture>
         </center>
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="drawing">Drawing</h3>

<p>To draw, I use the default Onyx’s Sketch app due to its responsiveness, even though I would have preferred to have a more customizable UI interface and faster ways to share the drawing.</p>

<p>Sharing is one of the downsides of the Onyx Sketch app. You need to either use their cloud service, or export the image in order to get the sketch easily accessible on other devices. I’ve opted to use the export functionality, which allows to directly share the image to a Google Keep note, which fits well into my workflow. I would prefer to not have this extra step, but still, it works well enough.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="iW3IZ9MnFL8" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>This has been one of the most satisfying devices I’ve added to my routines, and it’s incredibly satisfying to write on this device, almost distraction free. It allows enough customizability for it to be tailored to my use case, but is also limited enough to deter me from falling prey to distractions.</p>

<p>I hope this was useful towards your journey - do let me know your tips for distraction free environments!</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">

  <ol>
	<li id="fn:1">
  	<p>The BOOX Note Air3 B/W is a very capable device, able to do most of the things one would expect from an Android Tablet, but its screen refresh rate, speed and screen drag make it less suited for fast browsing and video usage for example. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
	<li id="fn:2">
  	<p>The screenshot is from BOOX Tablet Note Air 3 C, the color counterpart of Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, but the layout is the same, save from the color display <a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
    
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Musk's biography: why it's interesting]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography.html"/>
    <updated>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been hearing the <a href="https://amzn.to/3I97bBi">latest Elon Musk biography</a> <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> on audiobook, and just like Ashlee Vance’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3I5hUNu">book</a><sup>1</sup>, I’m finding it incredibly interesting. Here’s why:</p>

<h2 id="possibilities-monty-python-costs-whys-and-whos">Possibilities, Monty Python, costs, whys and whos</h2>

<h3 id="the-action-on-potential">The action on potential</h3>

<p>I find his path inspiring. It makes me want to create and do things, and shows that many things that are thought to be impossible, are actually achievable. There is a whole realm of opportunities waiting to be grabbed, and his life demonstrates just that.</p>

<p>There is a cost though. If it were that easy, everyone would do it.</p>

<h3 id="the-defining-characteristics">The defining characteristics</h3>

<p>The book goes deeper into the unique aspects that allow Musk to be an extreme overachiever, but also the personal and professional costs those same aspects inflict.</p>

<p>Musk’s capacity to take pain, risk, stress and adversity is staggering. I’ve been reading several biographies over the past years and met quite a few people throughout my life. I can only find a handful of them that are even comparable.</p>

<p>The relentless pursuit, sometimes maniacal, of product quality, functional and non-wasteful design, and effective manufacturing. All in the name of a greater objective, larger than any single human being or corporation.</p>

<h3 id="the-relationships">The relationships</h3>

<p>The book dives into the relationships that shaped Musk (for the better, for the worse, or both), the types of relationships he consistently attracted (which resonated with his personality and upbringing), and essential relationships that allowed him and his projects to thrive.</p>

<p>They come to further prove that no man or woman is an island. You can’t succeed by your own.</p>

<h3 id="the-humor">The humor</h3>

<p>Consistently throughout Musk’s life, there is a balance between dark and light, between lighthearted comedy and downright hell.</p>

<p>I’ve had a good laugh with some of the humorous sides though, such as when <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grA5XmBRC6g">eels and hovercrafts</a> were catered to one of his marriages, or when Blue Origin filed a formal protest against SpaceX to prevent the company from having exclusive use of a NASA launchpad, to which Musk <a href="https://spacenews.com/37389musk-calls-out-blue-origin-ula-for-phony-blocking-tactic-on-shuttle-pad/">replied</a> that <em>“if they do somehow show up in the next  5 years with a vehicle qualified to NASA’s human rating standards that can dock with the Space Station, which is what Pad 39A is meant to do, we will gladly accommodate their needs. Frankly, I think we are more likely to discover unicorns dancing in the flame duct.”</em></p>

<p>Shortly after, a SpaceX employee bought dozens of inflatable unicorns and took a picture of them standing in a flame duct 🦄</p>

<h2 id="musks-algorithm">Musk’s algorithm</h2>

<p><em>“The Algorithm”</em>, is a distillation of lessons learned while relentlessly increasing production capacity, which Musk repeatedly preached on his enterprises:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Question every requirement</li>
  <li>Delete any part of the process you can</li>
  <li>Simplify and optimize</li>
  <li>Accelerate cycle time</li>
  <li>Automate</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="questioning-requirements">1. Questioning requirements</h3>

<p>It can be summarized into this: <em>“The only rules are the ones dictated by the laws of physics. Everything else is a recommendation.”</em>. It’s a recurrent theme.</p>

<p>Doesn’t come without a cost though: it is often associated with conflict and chaos.</p>

<h3 id="about-2-delete-any-part-of-the-process-you-can">About 2. Delete any part of the process you can</h3>

<p><em>“Delete, delete, delete”</em></p>

<p>Optimization many times goes hand in hand with deletion. Deleting is hard. It requires letting go of past achievements, comfort, and acceptance that something is not coming back. Almost like a breakup.</p>

<h3 id="simplify-and-optimize">3. Simplify and optimize</h3>

<p>Goes hand in hand with deletion.</p>

<h3 id="accelerate-cycle-time">4. Accelerate cycle time</h3>

<p>This is where intensity and being “hard core” are most leveraged, in my view. Again, with their pros and cons.</p>

<h3 id="automate">5. Automate</h3>

<p>A more obvious one. Put a machine to do it. Easier said than done though.</p>

<h2 id="data-points---cause--effect-probabilities">Data points -&gt; cause &amp; effect probabilities</h2>

<p>I’m fond of biographies because they provide several data points that I can later use in my life. This is, which set of actions preceded a given consequence. Of course the context matters, and surely no same action will lead to the same consequence, specially if made by different people.</p>

<p>But patterns start to emerge, and their respective probabilities. These help me solidify my own personal theories and strategies. Learning from others is important. It allows for “shortcuts” similar to the ones provided by good mentors.</p>

<p>To build these, I need data points, a lot of them.</p>

<p>That is why I like Isaacson’s biographies so much <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This is this third book I read (or hear) from Walter Isaacson, and one of the things I enjoy most about his writing is how deep he goes into the details of someone’s story. I believe that details are important when portraying someone’s life. Sometimes, the smallest of events make an immense difference over someone’s path.</p>

<h2 id="just-read--hear-it">Just read / hear it</h2>

<p>Love him, or hate him, I recommend Musk’s biography to just about anyone.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This link is an affiliate link, and as an Amazon Associate I earn from qualifying purchases whose commissions help this small establishment, <u>at no additional cost to you</u></em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>Except <a href="https://amzn.to/48m3D9u">Steve Jobs Biography</a> <sup>1</sup>, which I could not bear to finish. Jobs personality was a bit too much for me to handle</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Planning Framework]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/01/27/project_planning_framework.html"/>
    <updated>2024-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/01/27/project_planning_framework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
  <div class="youtube-player" data-id="TfbYWb8YCyo" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Different goals require different roadmapping and planning techniques.</p>

<p>In this post, a simple framework is proposed to classify a goal using three axes, in order to inform the approach taken towards reaching that goal. The three axes are:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: how much leeway is there to extend the deadline to deliver a goal?</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: how many steps are needed to reach the goal?</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: how sure are we that a given step will move us toward the goal?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="example-of-how-to-apply-the-framework">Example of how to apply the Framework</h2>

<h3 id="scenario-1-reach-compliance">Scenario 1: Reach Compliance</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>An external entity (let’s say, government or partner company), has made a set of requirements for which your team must provide compliance for on a fixed, non-negotiable timeline, with limited team capacity. The “definition of done” is well defined by this entity, and there is a low amount of unknowns of how to reach the goals.</p>

<h4 id="axes">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: High</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: Low</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach">Approach</h4>

<p>This goal has sensitive timelines and is archetypal top-down. The deadline will be reached in one way or the other, so all hands are needed on deck to tackle this goal. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Use a Gant-style chart, where there is a heavy emphasis on the timeline</li>
  <li>Apply stricter project management, more process driven</li>
</ul>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<h3 id="scenario-2-increase-effectiveness-of-a-user-flow">Scenario 2: Increase Effectiveness of a User Flow</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement-1">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>Your team supports a user flow, such as a check-out flow, for which the goal is the increase the conversion amount by <em>X</em>. There are known levers you have available to drive this metric, but also many others which are unbeknownst and would need experimentation and research. This increase is not business critical, so there is an underlying lenience in case the goal is not hit.</p>

<h4 id="axes-1">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: High</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach-1">Approach</h4>

<p>Unlike Scenario 1, which is exploitation heavy, this scenario favors an approach which is exploration heavy, due to the high amount of uncertainty of which projects will be able to move the needle towards the successful completion of the goal. To de-risk and address this goal, a high level of adaptability will be needed, and several opportunities will need to be created to discover which levers can be used. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Have open ended brainstorming sessions</li>
  <li>Leverage user research and focus groups</li>
  <li>Apply looser project management, to allow for quick and less trashier pivots</li>
</ul>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<h3 id="scenario-3-unification-of-several-systems-into-one">Scenario 3: Unification of Several Systems into One</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement-2">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>Your team is tasked to unify several internal systems into a single one, where several dependencies between different projects exist, and the time each project will take ranges from certain to unknown.</p>

<h4 id="axes-2">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: High</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: Low / Medium</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach-2">Approach</h4>

<p>The focus here should be on making clear which are the dependencies between different projects, and allow some leniency towards the completion of each of the projects, while actively managing the team’s capacity to focus on the projects which are discovered to require a heavier lift. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Build a full dependency graph, allowing for each of the projects timelines to have some leeway where needed</li>
  <li>Incentivize structured system design documents and discussions, making sure that all involved parties are aligned on a given approach, and engineers are able to explain not only the system they own, but also other systems involved in their unification</li>
</ul>

<center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/unification.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems" />
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/unification.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems" />
             <img src="https://lopespm.com/files/project_planning_framework/unification.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems" />
           </picture>
         </center>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>The framework above is quite simple and could potentially be used for several other different use cases. It might also be missing some essential parameters that are relevant for your specific context. Let me know if you find these, I would be happy to review the framework accordingly. Regardless, hope the above can be useful on your next roadmapping / planning cycle!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
