<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2024-03-25T00:35:19+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://lopespm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html"/>
    <updated>2024-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the plan to banish mobile phones with access to instant rewards from my bedroom (more on this in an upcoming post), I’ve acquired a Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, which is a Android tablet with a black and white e-ink screen that is focused on writing and reading <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="house-rules">House Rules</h2>

<p>First of all, <em>why</em> I did get the device in the first place? This was in order to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reduce distractions before going to sleep and after waking up, increase focus on the things that really mattered, block out all other noise, and make it really hard to have access to instant gratification and rewards (such as video consumption)</li>
  <li>Register any ideas and thoughts that occur to me before and after going to sleep, which is one of my most proficuous times for such, and then have them available on other devices</li>
</ul>

<p><em>How</em> to achieve this using the BOOX:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Only two functionalities should be easy and quick to use:
    <ul>
      <li>Write text and notes (via Google Keep and Google Docs)</li>
      <li>Write diagrams and mental maps (via the device’s main app, which has the most snappier performance)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Getting to above functionalities should be as fast as possible, and they should be fast</li>
  <li>The cost to get to other apps and functionalities should be high</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="de-bloating">De-bloating</h2>

<p>The Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W is not an incredibly fast device, and comes with several functionalities, apps, and a launcher that increase the distraction degree, and also slow down the device.</p>

<h3 id="google-play-google-keep--docs">Google Play, Google Keep &amp; Docs</h3>

<p>The first step towards the objective above was to install Google Play (see <a href="https://help.boox.com/hc/en-us/articles/8569260963732-Google-Play-Store">guide here</a>, and afterwards installed these apps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Google Keep</li>
  <li>Google Docs</li>
  <li>Android Hidden Settings - this app provides access to several hidden settings, that allow the access of settings such as enabling the Developer Options in Android (useful in the debloating process described below)</li>
  <li>Lawnchair (see below)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="new-launcher-lawnchair">New Launcher: Lawnchair</h3>

<center>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"><div class="video-wrapper-two">
   <center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>Before:</b> Default BOOX Launcher <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> </p>
</div>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"> <div class="video-wrapper-two">
	<center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>After:</b> Using Lawnchair Launcher<br class="video-br-end" /></p>
</div>
</center>

<p>The default device’s launcher was replaced by <a href="https://lawnchair.app/">Lawnchair</a>, which is a lightweight, open-source, highly customizable launcher for Android.</p>

<p>What was added to the Lawnchair’s home screen:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Keep</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Docs</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Onyx Launcher - for any custom changes that are only accessible on the device’s default launcher, which are are in practice, so this was eventually something I removed from the home screen as I wrote this note</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Calendar - to add any events or reminders</li>
  <li>A widget to Onyx Sketch app, which is one the only way I found to have that app directly accessible from the Lawnchair home screen, without having to use Onyx’s launcher to do so. The widget can be added by long pressing on the home screen, then select “Widgets”, and then on the “ContentBrowser” section select one of the “Notes” widgets</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="disabling-bloatware">Disabling bloatware</h2>

<p>With all of the above in place, we could start disabling non-essential apps and services, to prevent them from running in the background.</p>

<p>Here are the steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The first step is to enable “Developer Options”, by accessing the system settings via the “Android Hidden Settings” app above, and then finding the <a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/debug/dev-options">Build Number</a> in order to click it enough times to eventually enable “Developer Options”.</li>
  <li>Connect the BOOX to the computer</li>
  <li>On the computer’s terminal run the below commands</li>
</ol>

<p>In general, these are the commands one can run via the terminal to manage bloat apps:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>// See all packages
$ adb shell pm list packages

// See all disabled packages
$ adb shell pm list packages -d

// Disable a package
$ adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 &lt;package_to_disable&gt;

// Re-enable a package
$ adb shell pm enable &lt;package_to_disable&gt;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
And these are the specific ones I used in my BOOX to disable bloatware, without any relevant side effects for my usages:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.appmarket
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.floatingbutton
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.dict
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.mail
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.igetshop
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.easytransfer
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.kime
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.android.ksync
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.calculator
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The commands above should be enough to remove all bloatware, and if you wish to learn more, <a href="https://www.kaspersky.co.uk/blog/how-to-disable-and-remove-android-bloatware/26993/">this article</a> and <a href="https://digitaluncoded.com/cpu-usage-android">this article</a> provide a good overview.</p>

<h2 id="using-an-external-keyboard">Using an external keyboard</h2>

<p>Given that this device is meant to be used in bed, and since it is quite unwieldy to write on the on-screen display, I was looking for an external keyboard that could be somehow attached to the BOOX, that would bestable, low-maintenance and allowed for flexibility on the writing position.</p>

<p>From the keyboards and keyboard stands I’ve researched, the most elegant solution I found was to use <a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-gb/products/keyboards/k480-multi-device-wireless.html">Logitech K480</a>, a bluetooth keyboard with an in-built cradle, detachable batteries (i.e. zero issues related internal battery becoming faulty), incredible battery span (some users reported this to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EoH2bXoNEE0">in the order of years</a>), and wonderful typing experience.</p>

<p>One caveat is that the BOOX slides backward and falls when using the cradle without any other aid. A very simple fix is to get a piece of cardboard, and place it behind the BOOX (see picture below) to create a better fit. It works remarkably well.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h2 id="writing-and-drawing">Writing and Drawing</h2>

<h3 id="writing">Writing</h3>

<p>Writing is my main use case for the device, and even though it has some lag when doing it, it works great for me, because I tend to write long streams of ranting text, rather than editing it.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="bYENTrabzXw" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The best mode I’ve found for writing was the “A2” Mode. It has ghosting, but is responsive enough for this use case.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h3 id="drawing">Drawing</h3>

<p>To draw, I use the default Onyx’s Sketch app due to its responsiveness, even though I would have preferred to have a more customizable UI interface and faster ways to share the drawing.</p>

<p>Sharing is one of the downsides of the Onyx Sketch app. You need to either use their cloud service, or export the image in order to get the sketch easily accessible on other devices. I’ve opted to use the export functionality, which allows to directly share the image to a Google Keep note, which fits well into my workflow. I would prefer to not have this extra step, but still, it works well enough.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="iW3IZ9MnFL8" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>This has been one of the most satisfying devices I’ve added to my routines, and it’s incredibly satisfying to write on this device, almost distraction free. It allows enough customizability for it to be tailored to my use case, but is also limited enough to deter me from falling prey to distractions.</p>

<p>I hope this was useful towards your journey - do let me know your tips for distraction free environments!</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">

  <ol>
	<li id="fn:1">
  	<p>The BOOX Note Air3 B/W is a very capable device, able to do most of the things one would expect from an Android Tablet, but its screen refresh rate, speed and screen drag make it less suited for fast browsing and video usage for example. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
	<li id="fn:2">
  	<p>The screenshot is from BOOX Tablet Note Air 3 C, the color counterpart of Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, but the layout is the same, save from the color display <a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
    
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Musk's biography: why it's interesting]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography.html"/>
    <updated>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been hearing the <a href="https://amzn.to/3I97bBi">latest Elon Musk biography</a> <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> on audiobook, and just like Ashlee Vance’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3I5hUNu">book</a><sup>1</sup>, I’m finding it incredibly interesting. Here’s why:</p>

<h2 id="possibilities-monty-python-costs-whys-and-whos">Possibilities, Monty Python, costs, whys and whos</h2>

<h3 id="the-action-on-potential">The action on potential</h3>

<p>I find his path inspiring. It makes me want to create and do things, and shows that many things that are thought to be impossible, are actually achievable. There is a whole realm of opportunities waiting to be grabbed, and his life demonstrates just that.</p>

<p>There is a cost though. If it were that easy, everyone would do it.</p>

<h3 id="the-defining-characteristics">The defining characteristics</h3>

<p>The book goes deeper into the unique aspects that allow Musk to be an extreme overachiever, but also the personal and professional costs those same aspects inflict.</p>

<p>Musk’s capacity to take pain, risk, stress and adversity is staggering. I’ve been reading several biographies over the past years and met quite a few people throughout my life. I can only find a handful of them that are even comparable.</p>

<p>The relentless pursuit, sometimes maniacal, of product quality, functional and non-wasteful design, and effective manufacturing. All in the name of a greater objective, larger than any single human being or corporation.</p>

<h3 id="the-relationships">The relationships</h3>

<p>The book dives into the relationships that shaped Musk (for the better, for the worse, or both), the types of relationships he consistently attracted (which resonated with his personality and upbringing), and essential relationships that allowed him and his projects to thrive.</p>

<p>They come to further prove that no man or woman is an island. You can’t succeed by your own.</p>

<h3 id="the-humor">The humor</h3>

<p>Consistently throughout Musk’s life, there is a balance between dark and light, between lighthearted comedy and downright hell.</p>

<p>I’ve had a good laugh with some of the humorous sides though, such as when <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grA5XmBRC6g">eels and hovercrafts</a> were catered to one of his marriages, or when Blue Origin filed a formal protest against SpaceX to prevent the company from having exclusive use of a NASA launchpad, to which Musk <a href="https://spacenews.com/37389musk-calls-out-blue-origin-ula-for-phony-blocking-tactic-on-shuttle-pad/">replied</a> that <em>“if they do somehow show up in the next  5 years with a vehicle qualified to NASA’s human rating standards that can dock with the Space Station, which is what Pad 39A is meant to do, we will gladly accommodate their needs. Frankly, I think we are more likely to discover unicorns dancing in the flame duct.”</em></p>

<p>Shortly after, a SpaceX employee bought dozens of inflatable unicorns and took a picture of them standing in a flame duct 🦄</p>

<h2 id="musks-algorithm">Musk’s algorithm</h2>

<p><em>“The Algorithm”</em>, is a distillation of lessons learned while relentlessly increasing production capacity, which Musk repeatedly preached on his enterprises:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Question every requirement</li>
  <li>Delete any part of the process you can</li>
  <li>Simplify and optimize</li>
  <li>Accelerate cycle time</li>
  <li>Automate</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="questioning-requirements">1. Questioning requirements</h3>

<p>It can be summarized into this: <em>“The only rules are the ones dictated by the laws of physics. Everything else is a recommendation.”</em>. It’s a recurrent theme.</p>

<p>Doesn’t come without a cost though: it is often associated with conflict and chaos.</p>

<h3 id="about-2-delete-any-part-of-the-process-you-can">About 2. Delete any part of the process you can</h3>

<p><em>“Delete, delete, delete”</em></p>

<p>Optimization many times goes hand in hand with deletion. Deleting is hard. It requires letting go of past achievements, comfort, and acceptance that something is not coming back. Almost like a breakup.</p>

<h3 id="simplify-and-optimize">3. Simplify and optimize</h3>

<p>Goes hand in hand with deletion.</p>

<h3 id="accelerate-cycle-time">4. Accelerate cycle time</h3>

<p>This is where intensity and being “hard core” are most leveraged, in my view. Again, with their pros and cons.</p>

<h3 id="automate">5. Automate</h3>

<p>A more obvious one. Put a machine to do it. Easier said than done though.</p>

<h2 id="data-points---cause--effect-probabilities">Data points -&gt; cause &amp; effect probabilities</h2>

<p>I’m fond of biographies because they provide several data points that I can later use in my life. This is, which set of actions preceded a given consequence. Of course the context matters, and surely no same action will lead to the same consequence, specially if made by different people.</p>

<p>But patterns start to emerge, and their respective probabilities. These help me solidify my own personal theories and strategies. Learning from others is important. It allows for “shortcuts” similar to the ones provided by good mentors.</p>

<p>To build these, I need data points, a lot of them.</p>

<p>That is why I like Isaacson’s biographies so much <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This is this third book I read (or hear) from Walter Isaacson, and one of the things I enjoy most about his writing is how deep he goes into the details of someone’s story. I believe that details are important when portraying someone’s life. Sometimes, the smallest of events make an immense difference over someone’s path.</p>

<h2 id="just-read--hear-it">Just read / hear it</h2>

<p>Love him, or hate him, I recommend Musk’s biography to just about anyone.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This link is an affiliate link, and as an Amazon Associate I earn from qualifying purchases whose commissions help this small establishment, <u>at no additional cost to you</u></em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>Except <a href="https://amzn.to/48m3D9u">Steve Jobs Biography</a> <sup>1</sup>, which I could not bear to finish. Jobs personality was a bit too much for me to handle</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Planning Framework]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/01/27/project_planning_framework.html"/>
    <updated>2024-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2024/01/27/project_planning_framework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Different goals require different roadmapping and planning techniques.</p>

<p>In this post, a simple framework is proposed to classify a goal using three axes, in order to inform the approach taken towards reaching that goal. The three axes are:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: how much leeway is there to extend the deadline to deliver a goal?</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: how many steps are needed to reach the goal?</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: how sure are we that a given step will move us toward the goal?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="example-of-how-to-apply-the-framework">Example of how to apply the Framework</h2>

<h3 id="scenario-1-reach-compliance">Scenario 1: Reach Compliance</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>An external entity (let’s say, government or partner company), has made a set of requirements for which your team must provide compliance for on a fixed, non-negotiable timeline, with limited team capacity. The “definition of done” is well defined by this entity, and there is a low amount of unknowns of how to reach the goals.</p>

<h4 id="axes">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: High</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: Low</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach">Approach</h4>

<p>This goal has sensitive timelines and is archetypal top-down. The deadline will be reached in one way or the other, so all hands are needed on deck to tackle this goal. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Use a Gant-style chart, where there is a heavy emphasis on the timeline</li>
  <li>Apply stricter project management, more process driven</li>
</ul>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance">
             <img src="/files/project_planning_framework/compliance.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for reaching compliance">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<h3 id="scenario-2-increase-effectiveness-of-a-user-flow">Scenario 2: Increase Effectiveness of a User Flow</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement-1">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>Your team supports a user flow, such as a check-out flow, for which the goal is the increase the conversion amount by <em>X</em>. There are known levers you have available to drive this metric, but also many others which are unbeknownst and would need experimentation and research. This increase is not business critical, so there is an underlying lenience in case the goal is not hit.</p>

<h4 id="axes-1">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: High</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach-1">Approach</h4>

<p>Unlike Scenario 1, which is exploitation heavy, this scenario favors an approach which is exploration heavy, due to the high amount of uncertainty of which projects will be able to move the needle towards the successful completion of the goal. To de-risk and address this goal, a high level of adaptability will be needed, and several opportunities will need to be created to discover which levers can be used. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Have open ended brainstorming sessions</li>
  <li>Leverage user research and focus groups</li>
  <li>Apply looser project management, to allow for quick and less trashier pivots</li>
</ul>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness">
             <img src="/files/project_planning_framework/effectiveness.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for increasing effectiveness">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<h3 id="scenario-3-unification-of-several-systems-into-one">Scenario 3: Unification of Several Systems into One</h3>

<h4 id="goaling-statement-2">Goaling Statement</h4>

<p>Your team is tasked to unify several internal systems into a single one, where several dependencies between different projects exist, and the time each project will take ranges from certain to unknown.</p>

<h4 id="axes-2">Axes</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Timeline sensitivity</strong>: Low</li>
  <li><strong>Dependency level between goals / projects</strong>: High</li>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty of which steps will drive the goal forward</strong>: Low / Medium</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="approach-2">Approach</h4>

<p>The focus here should be on making clear which are the dependencies between different projects, and allow some leniency towards the completion of each of the projects, while actively managing the team’s capacity to focus on the projects which are discovered to require a heavier lift. In specific:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Build a full dependency graph, allowing for each of the projects timelines to have some leeway where needed</li>
  <li>Incentivize structured system design documents and discussions, making sure that all involved parties are aligned on a given approach, and engineers are able to explain not only the system they own, but also other systems involved in their unification</li>
</ul>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/unification.webp" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/project_planning_framework/unification.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems">
             <img src="/files/project_planning_framework/unification.png" aria-label="Project planning diagram for unification of systems">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>The framework above is quite simple and could potentially be used for several other different use cases. It might also be missing some essential parameters that are relevant for your specific context. Let me know if you find these, I would be happy to review the framework accordingly. Regardless, hope the above can be useful on your next roadmapping / planning cycle!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make the meme transcend its host]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/12/31/meme-transcending-host.html"/>
    <updated>2023-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/12/31/meme-transcending-host</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is an ephemeral nature to everything. That includes me, you and this blog. This blog is currently <a href="https://github.com/lopespm/lopespm.github.com">hosted in GitHub</a>, and nothing guarantees that after I’m long gone, or even before, GitHub might cease to exist. How to account for that?</p>

<p>One way to keep these writings alive, would be to assign a third person with the task of keeping this establishment online. What happens when that person is gone though? It’s turtles all the way down.</p>

<p>Another way would be to find a self sustainable digital mechanism to keep this blog alive, ie, a bot. That has its own issues as well, since technologies change and distributed systems like <a href="https://ipfs.tech/">IPFS</a> come and go.</p>

<p>The other option to extend the lifespan of these digital contents is to have these writings persisted into a physical medium. A book. No maintenance required. As long as it can be kept safe from unfortunate <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_burning">book burning events</a>, the probability that a single copy remains alive, and can be made accessible (such as a public library) to someone and hopefully improve their life, increases.</p>

<h2 id="no-input-no-output">No Input, No Output</h2>

<p>The jump from a humble blog to a book is quite a leap. Outrageous even. Perhaps doable.</p>

<p>Some of the books I’ve recently read gave me some guidance and ideas on how to take that germinal idea into fruition (<em>note that the following links are affiliate links, and as an Amazon Associate I earn from qualifying purchases whose commissions help this small establishment, <u>at no additional cost to you</u></em>):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Rolf Dobelli’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3NJ12is">The Art of the Good Life</a> is a collection of 52 articles that Dobelli wrote for a newspaper column.</li>
  <li>Dobelli also previously wrote <a href="https://amzn.to/3NGItvC">The Art of Thinking Clearly</a> (I did not read this one), which reveals the most common errors of judgment, and how to avoid them, throughout 99 short chapters. Although the idea the idea of 99 chapters seems to have been <a href="https://www.fooledbyrandomness.com/dobelli.htm">original to Nassim Taleb’s</a> project to publish “99 (convex) heuristics”</li>
  <li>Steven Bartlett shares on his <a href="https://amzn.to/3vbDNas">Diary of a CEO book</a> that at 21 years old, he made a promise to himself that every day at 7PM, he would write a tweet or make a video delivering a single idea, and then post it online at 8PM, which Steven claims to have been the habit the most difference to advance his knowledge and skills. It completely changed his life trajectory, and consequently it’s the piece of advice Steven most strongly urges for anyone looking to be a better thinker, speaker, writer, or content creator. The key here was that he made it a daily obligation, not just an interest.
    <ul>
      <li>From this, I assume that this habit was foundational to his <a href="https://stevenbartlett.com/the-diary-of-a-ceo-podcast/">Diary of a CEO podcast</a>, which eventually resulted in the book above</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>After listening to <a href="https://amzn.to/3GYxlq6">Benjamin Franklin’s biography</a> on audiobook, I’ve came to learn that not only was Franklin a statesman, diplomat, scientist and inventor, but also a prolific writer, printer and publisher, which were unbeknownst to me. As a publisher, Benjamin Franklin wrote several dissertations and essays <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> (such as the ones under the pen name of Silence Dogood), which I’m sure to have fed into Franklin’s books, which brought many interesting ideas to a large population, like his own <a href="https://amzn.to/4aG58ly">autobiography</a>, which could be seen as a compilation of several of his ideas and reflections / writings (these go hand in hand).</li>
</ul>

<p>Apart from finding the above points inspirational, they also make me think that creating a discipline where I consistently share my reflections and experiences via writing or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_VHNCq3yGJrLn82VsdONOg">videos</a>, not only helps me <a href="/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking.html">solidify my thoughts</a> and provides more immediate feedback on how valuable these are to its viewers / readers (which allows me to course correct and iterate <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>), but also provides the building blocks to put together a hopefully meaningful and concise book to help surpass the limited lifespan of the digital medium that hosts this blog and my YouTube videos.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>No Input, No Output</p>

  <p><em>― Joe Strummer, lead singer of The Clash</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-path-towards-physical-persistence">The Path Towards Physical Persistence</h2>

<p>Given the above, here are some action points to put the wheels in motion towards building “physical persistence” via a book, and give better chances for its memes to transcend their host <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>My low priority 2024 <a href="/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html">goal</a> is continuing to publish blog notes and videos. The numeric goal I’ve set for myself is to publish 12 blog notes, about once per month. From these, make the respective <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_VHNCq3yGJrLn82VsdONOg">YouTube videos</a>, but this would be a stretch sub-goal (albeit, one that I really enjoy)
    <ul>
      <li>This was a consequence of my recent “personal performance” review for this year’s personal goals, which was a good opportunity to reflect on what went well, what went less well, what was achieved, and what was missed. One of the aspects that I aim to implement for the <a href="/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html">upcoming year’s goals</a> is to use numeric goals, where applicable.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Once 50 or 99 meaningful blog notes are written, attempt to compile them into a book.
    <ul>
      <li>Why 50 or 99? Upon reaching 50 notes, I might feel that not enough substantial content was generated to be distilled into a book. Once 99 notes are reached however, it would be more certain that enough meaningful content was accumulated (hopefully). I would expect the distillation process to remove several notes that would be deemed to have less quality.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Looking forward to 2024! 🎉</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>On the extensive range of writings that Benjamin Franklin did, there are also hilarious examples such as <a href="https://amzn.to/3TErk9B">Fart Proudly</a>, an essay about flatulence written while he was living abroad as United States Ambassador to France</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>One the learnings from <a href="/2019/02/06/survival-ball-making-the-game.html">making the Survival Ball video game</a>, was that the lack of exposure throughout it’s development process lead to less visibility to the ones who might be interested in it, and less immediate feedback on what worked and what didn’t work, which could have possibly have helped to craft an better product, by virtue of allowing faster / less painful pivots</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><em>Coined by the British evolutionist Richard Dawkins in his book <a href="https://amzn.to/48vVG20">The Selfish Gene (1976)</a>, a <a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/acref/9780195120905.001.0001/acref-9780195120905-e-187">meme</a> is a unit of culture—such as “tunes, ideas, catch‐phrases, clothes fashions, ways of making pots or building arches.” In humans, memes have supposedly taken over much of the evolutionary burden of the traditional units of heredity, the genes. Dawkins introduces them because in his opinion the rate of human cultural evolution is far too rapid to be simply a function of gene‐centered evolution</em>.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York City Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/12/25/nyc.html"/>
    <updated>2023-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/12/25/nyc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_194118475_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>I was recently in NYC. It was one of the most interesting experiences I’ve ever had.</p>

<p>Each one has their own perspectives when visiting the city, and I’ve asked several people about theirs before the trip, which helped immensely when planning out my itinerary. Now it’s my time to pay it forward. Here is my guide / personal perspective of New York.</p>

<h2 id="maps">Maps</h2>

<p>Having a pre-curated list of points of interest on Google Maps was one of the most useful and time efficient aspects of the entire trip. This allowed me to quickly improvise and make the most of my surroundings, since I could just look at the map to check which nearby places I could visit at any given time.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/e6z91pon4Lco8r6F8">Points of Interest Map</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/swXwxeps7uAJWcno9">Restaurants Map</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pmap.png')"></div>
</div>

<h2 id="museums">Museums</h2>

<p>I didn’t consider myself to be an excessive photographer. I’ve discovered on this trip that I was probably wrong. I can’t recall the last time I took so many photos, it was like I was in an outstanding candy store of visual goodies.</p>

<h3 id="intrepid-museum">Intrepid Museum</h3>

<p>Let’s start with fashion. I’ve been pointed out that my glasses make me look nerdy / square / too serious / too much like an engineer. Well, thanks to this museum piece, I can now say they were developed for space walks:</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_162525852_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>Oh, and look back and you will also see the Space Shuttle <em>Enterprise</em>, the first orbiter of the Space Shuttle system:</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_161516492_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_163236552_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_162820076_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_162348213_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>You can find these glasses, the space shuttle, sit inside the Mercury capsule or A-6 Intruder cockpit, see real life jet planes like the Lockheed A-12, in the Intrepid museum.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_160040171_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_173618225_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_173602131_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>Where is the Intrepid museum? The museum is an World War II–era aircraft carrier. Yes, the vessel <em>is</em> the museum. You can explore several of it’s interior sections, including the bridge, living quarters, gun and bomb bays, go through the same narrow escalator that pilots took to the flight deck, all of these throughout several floors and different explorable rooms</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_154908796_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_155153393_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_163920354_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_164301932_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>Right beside the Intrepid lies USS Growler, a diesel powered submarine retrofitted to deliver Regulus nuclear missiles, as a form of nuclear deterrence during Cold War. You can go inside the submarine and get an intimate experience of how it’s lived throughout their 2 month patrols, where they faced the constant scenario of being called upon to launch a nuclear missile onto Russian soil, destroying not only their target, but most likely kill themselves on the process, since the process to launching / reloading Regulus missiles was long and would expose this submarine to enemy reconnaissance.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Since it was a diesel submarine, it required to be at surface or near surface level (it was not possible to push out their exhaust gasses when deep in the ocean) to enable a set of its 3 engines to charge its on-board batteries that would power the submarine and its electric motors.</li>
  <li>It also needed to be periodically refueled, so the submarine ran a long circular patrol in the Pacific Ocean to refuel to eventually sit near Russian enemy lines for dozens of days.</li>
  <li>The crew had to maintain absolute secrecy about their mission, and none of their partners knew the context of it</li>
  <li>The families of the crew members knew nothing about their mission, and that if they did launch a nuclear missile, they would be exposed, and most likely be killed as they expose themselves to launch the nuclear load (not to mention the annihilation that comes from the nuclear warhead)</li>
</ul>

<p>I found the underlying story and details of this submarine and this mission to be so interesting, that right after the tour, I went immediately in search of staff members to ask a series of questions that came about during the visit. They very kindly and patiently took the time to answer them, and one of the ladies even asked me if I was an engineer. I’m not sure what gave that away. It was either the questions, or my glasses :)</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_182454873_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_180812250_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_182222204_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_175706573_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="met">MET</h3>

<p>MET, or Metropolitan Museum of Art, has two locations: the museum in Fifth Avenue is the most famous one and is often referred to when mentioning MET. The other lesser known branch is in Upper Manhattan, the MET Cloisters.</p>

<h4 id="met-fifth-avenue">MET: Fifth Avenue</h4>

<ul>
  <li>If you like the British Museum, you will love MET on Fifth Avenue</li>
  <li>They reconstructed the 10 BCE <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_of_Dendur">Temple of Dendur</a> Roman Egyptian religious structure, which was originally located in Tuzis (later Dendur). Must I say more?</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_004105499_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_004347504_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_005320953_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_004205784_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>This massive museum spans through classical antiquity and ancient Egypt; paintings and sculptures from nearly all the European masters; and an extensive collection of American and modern art. All of these are intertwined with large thematic rooms where the installations are beautiful to behold. If you are going to see a single museum in New York, this should be the one.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_235305115_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_011538372_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_012833682_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_235757224_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>One of the last books I’ve listen on audiobook was <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Benjamin-Franklin-American-Walter-Isaacson/dp/074325807X">Walter Isaacson’s Benjamin Franklin biography</a>, where one of passages goes through the story of how a Duplessis’ painting of Franklyn’s portrait came to be. This <a href="https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436236?pkgids=367&amp;pos=1&amp;nextInternalLocale=en&amp;ft=*&amp;oid=436236&amp;rpp=4&amp;exhibitionId=%7Bfc6dc1eb-bea2-4986-afc2-1cd8b02db3ee%7D&amp;pg=1">1778 painting can be seen in the museum</a>, and curiously enough, Franklyn’s depiction on <a href="https://www.uscurrency.gov/denominations/100"><span>$</span>100 bills from 1914 to 1990</a> had him wearing a fur coat, just like this painting.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_012300076_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/p100_dollar_bill.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="met-cloisters">MET: Cloisters</h4>

<p>With the same ticket, one can visit the Cloisters and the 5th Avenue museum on the same day. The Cloisters museum is America’s only museum dedicated exclusively to the art and architecture of the Middle Ages, and is smaller than the 5th Avenue one. Still there much to explore not only inside the museum, but also on its surroundings</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_173852485_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_175636974_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_174330257_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_175347280_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>Surrounding the Cloisters is the beautiful Fort Tryon Park and it’s Heather Garden, sitting right next to the Hudson Riven. A bliss to behold.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_181839989_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_182328700_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_181531602_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="national-history-museum">National History Museum</h3>

<ul>
  <li>I lost count of the amount of dinosaur skeletons I’ve seen in the natural history museum. And nothing quite prepares you to see a gigantic skeleton of a Titanosaur. It’s so big that its head extends outside of its new home in the Museum’s fourth-floor gallery.</li>
  <li>I’ve learned while browsing the museum about mass dinosaur graves and their relationship to draughts, and went through thought provoking sections, such as the presentation of a massive turtle specimen, that if it were to be extinct it would probably be right part of our imaginary and event movies.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_213818102_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_211401308_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_214323316_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_215936304_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>Another thought that stuck to me is how deeply connected we are to other animals, Earth and outer space. Seeing life sized representations of several of these makes them immediately more relatable.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_222007189_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_222322881_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_220537911_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_222432148_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="guggenheim">Guggenheim</h3>

<p>On Saturdays, from 5 to 8 pm, admission to the museum is “Pay What You Wish”, for a minimum of <span>$</span>1. I would recommend doing so, since the museum can be easily visited in less than one hour, and in my opinion, it’s more about the building than the pieces themselves</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_232417666_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_231841394_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_224944325_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_230420060_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h2 id="entertainment">Entertainment</h2>

<h3 id="broadway">Broadway</h3>

<p>Broadway shows are a hallmark of NYC, although if you are from London or Europe, I would recommend not seeing shows that are already available in London. For example, I’ve heard that Hamilton is better seen in London, due to the larger contextual part that King George has in the UK.</p>

<p>The Chicago musical is a good bet, and is the one I’ve attended to, it is the second longest-running show ever to run on Broadway, behind only The Phantom of the Opera</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_234928765_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_010308753_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="comedy">Comedy</h3>

<p>Comedy Cellar is a comedy club in Manhattan where many top New York comedians perform, and where several comedians started, like Louis C.K. or Dave Chappelle. I found it be have down to earth, edgy comedy, and you are asked to leave your phone in a pouch, which I believe to increase presence of the entire crowd, but also provides extra freedom to comedians, given to how powerful cancel culture can be</p>

<h2 id="points-of-interest">Points of Interest</h2>

<h3 id="statue-of-liberty">Statue of Liberty</h3>

<p>You can get the Staten Island Ferry from the Whitehall terminal, for <em>free</em>. On your way to the terminal, several people will try to sell and cajole you into payed trips to the Statue of Liberty trips. The ferry is more than enough.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The ferry runs <a href="https://www.nyc.gov/html/dot/html/ferrybus/siferryschedule.shtml">every 30 minutes</a>, 24 hours per day, for most of the days, and travel time is approximately 25 minutes.</li>
  <li>Once you get to Staten Island, you can either take some time to explore it, or just return immediately to Manhattan, by exiting the ferry, by entering St. George’s Ferry Terminal, and entering the boarding gates for the next ferry.</li>
  <li>When entering the Whitehall terminal, enter through the right side of the ferry in order to be on the same side that the Statue of Liberty will appear. If entering on St. George’s Ferry Terminal, enter through the left side of the ferry. Regardless, you can easily change sides when inside the ferry</li>
  <li>Most of the people will likely go to the top floor with larger windows, which will eventually get crowded. I recommend instead to take the bottom floor, and find a window that is already opened. The view is much clearer (since you don’t have a worn down piece of glass obfuscating the view), you can sit comfortably near the window, and you won’t need to fight a crowd (in principle)</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_161039350_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_165241316_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_155152840_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="central-park">Central Park</h3>

<p>Central Park is an urban park between the Upper West Side and Upper East Side neighborhoods of Manhattan in New York City that was the first landscaped park in the United States. It is the sixth-largest park in the city, and it’s a great way to step out of the busyness of the city and discover the treasures that lie in the park.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_125413649_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_130759730_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_142626653_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_125123548_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_141915327_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_124924771_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_220853279_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="high-line-and-little-island">High Line and Little Island</h3>

<p>The High Line is a 1.45-mile-long elevated linear park, greenway and rail trail created on a former New York Central Railroad spur on the west side of Manhattan in New York City. If starting it from the north side, you can enter it near Hudson Yards, and walk your way south from there.</p>

<p>Upon the southern end of the High Line park, you can view Little Island, and quickly walk to it. Little Island is an artificial island park, with some beautiful views and interesting layout</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_185708336_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_192311812_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_193026592_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="financial-district">Financial District</h3>

<h4 id="memorial">9/11 Memorial</h4>

<p>The memorial is located at the World Trade Center site, the former location of the Twin Towers that were destroyed during the September 11 attacks. Each of the towers’ footprints are now the home of two large, recessed pools. The sheer dimension of these is awestrucking. The entire site is filled with symbolism.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_141537611_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_141644458_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_141258747_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_141110593_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="wall-street">Wall Street</h4>

<ul>
  <li>On the street itself, we can find the  New York Stock Exchange, the largest stock exchange in the world, which for decades filled the popular imagination with its hustle, bustle and hectic traders. Those same brokers and traders are now surrounded by computers that manage the majority of the buying and selling of stocks for their various accounts. Floor trading still exists, but it is responsible for a rapidly diminishing share of market activity.</li>
  <li>The Charging Bull of Wall Street is not really located on Wall Street itself, but it is quite near. The bull in finance represents optimism and growth. The statue on Wall Street represents the same ideas.</li>
  <li>The Federal Hall is a historic building, whose original building served as New York’s first City Hall and hosted the 1765 Stamp Act Congress before the American Revolution. With the establishment of the United States federal government in 1789, it was renamed Federal Hall, as it hosted the 1st Congress and was where George Washington was sworn in as the nation’s first president. The current structure was built as the U.S. Custom House for the Port of New York before serving as a Subtreasury building from 1862 to 1925, and the current national memorial commemorates the historic events that occurred at the previous structure.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_144104420_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_145646928_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_145010822_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="columbia-university--morningside-park">Columbia University + Morningside Park</h3>

<p>Walking west from Central Harlem, where you can find the Apollo Theatre for example, we reach Morningside Park, from which we can climb up towards Columbia university, a private Ivy League research university in New York City.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_145826976_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_145930594_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_145741521_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_145154312_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="grants-tomb">Grant’s Tomb</h3>

<ul>
  <li>In a mere 7 minute walk from Columbia University, you can reach the General Grant National Memorial (Grant’s Tomb), classical domed mausoleum, the resting place of an American military officer and politician who served as the 18th president of the United States from 1869 to 1877. The underlying background music and the attention to detail are something to behold</li>
  <li>Right beside it sits the soaring Riverside Church, all of this surrounded by the peaceful Riverside Park</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_151740330_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_152700864_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_152217648_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231216_151352840_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="citigroup-center">Citigroup Center</h3>

<p>Due to material changes during construction, the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/z4F9FgXe4QfVZvux5">building</a> as initially completed was structurally unsound. To save money, Bethlehem Steel changed the plans in 1974 to use bolted joints, and wind loads were calculated from perpendicular winds, as required under the building code; in typical buildings, loads from quartering winds at the corners would be less.</p>

<p>In June 1978, after an inquiry from an engineering student, the structural engineer recalculated the wind loads on the building with quartering winds, and found these to significantly increase the load at the bolted joints, and that a wind capable of toppling Citicorp Center would occur every 55 years on average.</p>

<p>Starting in August 1978, construction crews covertly fixed the issue, and six weeks into the work, a major storm was off Cape Hatteras and heading for New York. The reinforcement was only half-finished, with New York City hours away from emergency evacuation. The storm eventually turned eastward and veered out to sea. The repairs were finished successfully, and no major issues happened ever since.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231218_014618298_2.jpg')"></div>
<div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231218_014709737_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="the-woolworth-building">The Woolworth Building</h3>

<p>Completed in 1912, the Woolworth Building was the tallest building in the world from 1913 to 1930, with a height of 241 meters. It blows my mind that such a tall building was built more than 100 years ago.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
<div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_225035805_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="billionaires-row">Billionaires’ Row</h3>

<p>Home of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aN9DH_GxqEo">one of the most expensive apartments in the world</a>, the Billionaires’ Row hosts a group of ultra-luxury residential skyscrapers. Several of them are so thin that it’s hard to believe how they can stand upright without toppling over.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
<div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_133641940_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="lincoln-center">Lincoln Center</h3>
<ul>
  <li>The Lincoln Center is a complex of buildings in the Lincoln Square neighborhood on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, where the beautiful Metropolitan Opera House can found.</li>
  <li>It houses internationally renowned performing arts organizations including the New York Philharmonic, the Metropolitan Opera, the New York City Ballet, the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, and the Juilliard School.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
<div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_030521003_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_030609383_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="grand-central-terminal">Grand Central Terminal</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Grand Central Terminal (aka Grand Central Station or Grand Central), is a commuter rail terminal located right in the center of the city. So even if you don’t stumble upon it during your commute, it can still be easily reachable via public transportation.</li>
  <li>It has been the subject, inspiration, or setting for literature, television and radio episodes, and films, and every year the MTA hosts about 25 large-scale and hundreds of smaller or amateur film and television productions.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
<div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_021419177_2.png')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="the-bronx">The Bronx</h3>

<h4 id="the-joker-stairs">The Joker Stairs</h4>
<p>The first picture on this note was taken at the “Joker Stairs”, which is the colloquial name for a step street connecting Shakespeare and Anderson avenues at West 167th Street in the Highbridge neighborhood. The stairs are quite different from when Joaquin Phoenix danced as the Joker. They are more colorful, and have a construction site ongoing at the top.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pjoker_stairs.png')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="the-birthplace-of-hip-hop">The Birthplace of Hip Hop</h4>
<p>DJ Kool Herc is credited with helping to start hip hop and rap music at a house concert at 1520 Sedgwick Avenue, which is currently covered by scaffolds <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/@40.8471093,-73.9248007,3a,90y,114.56h,101.92t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1s93g4AGnSKx6nUj06gfNaTA!2e0!7i16384!8i8192?entry=ttu">as seen here</a>. I would recommend to go during daylight hours and to be attentive to your route, as it gets rougher on the way there.</p>

<h4 id="yankee-stadium">Yankee Stadium</h4>
<p>The stadium is the home field for the New York Yankees and New York City FC, and also has some small surrounding parks.</p>

<h3 id="brooklyn">Brooklyn</h3>

<h4 id="williamsburg-bridge">Williamsburg (Bridge)</h4>

<p>While the Brooklyn Bridge stands as the most famous bridge to cross the East River, you can easily dodge its flocking crowds by crossing the Williamsburg Bridge, which leads you into Williamsbridge, characterized by a contemporary art scene, hipster culture, and vibrant nightlife that has projected its image internationally as a “Little Berlin”</p>

<p>You can find several interesting places in Williamsburg such as the Domino Park, Spoonbill &amp; Sugartown Books and the City Reliquary Museum.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231209_213626376_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231209_213956803_2.png')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="brooklyn-bridge">Brooklyn Bridge</h4>

<p>The Brooklyn Bridge is an iconic landmark of NYC, which you can cross from Manhattan towards Brooklyn. Be advised that this crossing is often quite crowded, and there are several vendors in the bridge itself</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_181034675_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_174922975_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="dumbo--brooklyn-heights">Dumbo &amp; Brooklyn Heights</h4>

<p>Once you cross the Brooklyn Bridge, you can head directly to Dumbo, where you have a beautiful view to the Manhattan Bridge</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_182005979_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<p>You can also have several scenic views towards of the Brooklyn Bridge and Manhattan, in both Dumbo and Brooklyn Heights</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_182536653_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_185752446_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="brooklyn-museum--brooklyn-library">Brooklyn Museum &amp; Brooklyn Library</h4>

<ul>
  <li>The Brooklyn Museum is New York City’s second largest and contains an art collection with around 500,000 objects, and  is fairly easy to access from the subway. The breadth and depth of objects at the Brooklyn Museum is best compared to the Met, boasting strong departments of both Western and non-Western holdings. I didn’t fit enough time to visit the actual museum, but it is definitely on the todo list in case I visit the city again.</li>
  <li>Brooklyn’s Library four stories high main entrance is a marvel to behold just by itself</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_200935743_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_203904586_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_202836059_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="prospect-park">Prospect Park</h4>

<p>Prospect Park is an expansive and peaceful urban park with beautiful landmarks and structures, such as the Boathouse on the Lullwater, several watercourses, bridges, monuments and statues</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_211820390_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_211035936_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_211953074_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="th-avenue">5th Avenue</h3>

<h4 id="rockefeller-center-christmas-tree">Rockefeller Center Christmas Tree</h4>
<p>The Rockefeller Center Christmas Tree has been a yearly tradition ever since 1931, which now hosts a 20m+ Norway spruce, near to an also historical skating rink, which was opened below the tree in the plaza in 1936. This year, you’ll be able to see the tree up until January 13th 2024.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_023321308_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_023848830_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="saks">Saks</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Directly facing the Rockefeller Center, you can find Saks Fifth Avenue, an American luxury department store founded in 1867.</li>
  <li>In partnership with Dior, as part of Saks’ annual holiday, it is hosting a massive, bronze circle is broken up into eight sections with a deep blue center decorated with all the zodiac signs and a spray of stars, with one big star in the middle, where there is a periodic visual and sound show which is truly impressive.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_030008176_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231215_023442485_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h4 id="trump-tower">Trump Tower</h4>
<p>Just a few blocks north from the above places lies the Trump Tower, where Donald Trump descended on an escalator to announce his candidacy for president, the first step on a journey few believed would take him all the way to the White House.</p>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-wide image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_024049452_2.jpg')"></div>
<div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_024344960_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/ptrump_simpsons.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h2 id="eat-sleep-move-and-pay">Eat, Sleep, Move and Pay</h2>

<h3 id="where-to-eat">Where to Eat</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Unless you would be aiming to hit a specific high demand restaurant at a specific time span, there is limited need to pre-book a restaurant, since you can just walk for a few minutes and find other quality restaurants.</li>
  <li>There are several food stalls around NYC, many of which you will be able to recognize by their LED letterings and smell of burnt meat, I would personally avoid these. There are food stalls which are incredible though. One of these is <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/M9xwJBkt5n1bpkY87">Shawarma Bay</a>, just a block away from Radio City Music Hall. Incredible food, although it can gain quite a queue, which can take about 30 minutes, as it was my case. Worth the wait though– cops were eating there</li>
  <li>You can get incredibly good Deli Sandwiches in NYC, in places such as <a href="https://g.co/kgs/eXxHUA">Sunny &amp; Annie’s Deli</a>. I’ve personally tried one at <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/qKFMoUoXPdT9qSgg7">Gold Deli</a>, and it was seriously good.</li>
  <li>Are you in Times Square and want to grab a bite? Walk 2 blocks west and you will find yourself in Hell’s Kitchen, packed with good restaurants, without much less hassle</li>
  <li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/DDbPvmqBeturoA219">Wan Wan</a> Thai restaurant was the best dining experience I had in NYC, for an acceptable price.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Joe's+Pizza/@40.7307059,-74.0133713,14.6z/data=!4m10!1m2!2m1!1sjoes+pizza!3m6!1s0x89c259924a960df1:0x43b20488619b3f43!8m2!3d40.7306597!4d-74.0021707!15sCgpqb2VzIHBpenphWgwiCmpvZXMgcGl6emGSARBwaXp6YV9yZXN0YXVyYW50mgEjQ2haRFNVaE5NRzluUzBWSlEwRm5TVU5vYlRWaWRraG5FQUXgAQA!16s%2Fg%2F1tyyy0n3?entry=ttu">Joe’s Pizza</a> offers traditional New York slice-style pizza at a fair price, that has made a dent in popular culture. Definitely worth the it.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_173101528_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_173126990_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Want to grab quick, healthy, tasty bite? <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/search/dig+inn+restaurant+new+york/@40.7389988,-73.9951262,13.11z?entry=ttu">Dig Inn</a> has you covered.</li>
  <li>Williamsburg’s L’Industrie Pizzeria apparently has some of the best pizzas in NYC, but I can’t attest to that, given there was a massive queue when I arrived there. So I moved to <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Rosa's+Pizza/@40.7139722,-73.9582738,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m6!3m5!1s0x89c259438227569b:0x1ad684baf4902574!8m2!3d40.7139722!4d-73.9556935!16s%2Fg%2F11grts6bbq?entry=ttu">Rosa’s Pizza</a>, where I had delicious slice.</li>
  <li>On markets such as the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/5idADNssKsJFAe1aA">Chelsea Market</a> you can find several good food places.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231218_002619530_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231218_003453051_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Fraunces Tavern is a museum and restaurant that played a prominent role in history before, during, and after the American Revolution. At various points in its history, Fraunces Tavern served as a headquarters for George Washington, a venue for peace negotiations with the British, and housing federal offices in the Early Republic.</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_171014704_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="where-to-stay">Where to Stay</h3>
<ul>
  <li>This all depends on your budget, activities you would like to do, who is going with you, etc. But in general, I would advise on staying in Manhattan island, or at least near to a transport connection that can get you quickly to the city center, since it is where most of the points of interest are located, and transport links are quite good from there. Most likely you will also be in your lodging to sleep, and not much else.</li>
  <li>If looking for a hostel, <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/2EjoFJnZMMGqhC8N7">HI New York City Hostel</a> is a good one. It even sports free weekly comedy sessions every Sunday night. It’s located near Central Park, and you can’t go wrong with this one. In general, you can search through https://www.hostelworld.com/ and book through there, it was quite reliable for the two bookings I did.</li>
  <li>If looking for something more comfortable, citizenM Hotels are of incredible good value and location. Apart from the comfortable rooms that have nice view already, on Bowery it even has rooftop terrace with an amazing view of the city</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card image-mosaic-card-tall image-mosaic-card-wide" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231212_040015020_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231212_040052869_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231212_040221554_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h3 id="money--how-to-pay">Money / How to Pay</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Stores, food establishments (even chains), bodegas / delis, 7-11s, etc present their prices as pre-tax. New York City sales tax ranges from 4% to 8.875%, and <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pubs_and_bulls/tg_bulletins/st/listings_of_taxable_and_exempt_food.htm">some products are exempt from it</a>.</li>
  <li>Be prepared to tip everywhere. On restaurants it is customary to tip 20%. There is some debate about whether you should calculate the tip on the amount before or after tax.</li>
  <li>You don’t really need cash. You do need it if you want to buy from street vendors, or if you want to dodge the additional cost that certain sellers impose on card transactions (like the shawarma above)  </li>
  <li>On restaurants and entertainment venues, it is common practice for the attendant to leave with the credit card, to later return with an attached invoice that is meant to be signed and filled with the tipping amount.
    <ul>
      <li>It also happened to me that when trying to pay by contactless card to a market vendor, the card kept being rejected, and since the card insertion feature was not available, the vendor wrote down the card number and details into the system to proceed with the payment. That failed as well, because the card got blocked by my bank due to a false-positive suspected fraud, as I later discovered. Eventually I just payed with cash to resolve the issue.</li>
      <li>As an European, the practice of being physically separated from the card, verification via signature, and freely writing down credit card numbers strike me as quite unsecure.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="getting-around--transportation">Getting Around / Transportation</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Walking is one of the best ways to discover the city. Sidewalks are broad, the city is grid shaped (so expect to be given coordinates in the form of street / avenue to pinpoint a place), and pedestrian lights and timings ran standard everywhere I visited. The large majority of my city exploration was made over the span of 180km, throughout 4 days. Extra tip: if you are used to barefoot shoes, wearing <a href="https://www.vivobarefoot.com/rw/">firm ground outsole Vivos</a> to do so is amazing. My feet were sore, but happy.</li>
  <li>Walking through the perpendicular numbered streets and avenues is an absolute bliss, and makes it quite easy to navigate through them. Several times I just looked at the map and quickly memorized something like “3 right, 2 left”, which translated to “cross 3 roads and turn right, and then cross 2 roads and turn left”. This would keep me walking going for a long time and have time to appreciate the surroundings, without the need to constantly check the map.</li>
  <li>Ferry boats are a great way to sight the city, for a low price (<span>$</span>4 for a one way-ticket), and you can buy these tickets through the NYC Ferry app or a ticket vending machine.</li>
  <li>Subway and Bus now have OMNI, which just means that you can tap in with your credit / debit card. Each ride costs <span>$</span>2.90, and there are no different prices for different zones. This has a [rolling 7 day price cap] (https://omny.info/fares), so you never pay more than <span>$</span>34 over that period.
    <ul>
      <li>Metro Card is the pre-paid version of this. If you need one, buy it directly from the machines to avoid being scammed. For example, a 7-Day Unlimited MetroCard costs <span>$</span>34 upfront, and can be used any number of times during those 7 days.
        <ul>
          <li>Be aware that if you swipe in, then get out from the station, and then attempt to shortly swipe in again, it will reject your swipe, due to being too recent. If that happens, ask a MTA attendant to let you in (if available), or do like many others and wait for someone to crack open the emergency exit from the inside. If you hear an alarm going off in the station, most likely it is because someone opened the emergency exit to let others in.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Just like routine events such as figuring out post-tax prices purchases or how much and when to tip require some kind of mental effort, figuring out the different edge cases of the subway system will keep your mind busy. It is like there is a perpetual rat race game being played in the city.
    <ul>
      <li>Sometimes trains stop at all stations, sometimes they don’t, sometimes trains have indicators of which station you are in, sometimes they don’t, sometimes the station has (non-standard) indications of how much time it takes for the next train to arrive, sometimes they don’t. Sometimes it rains heavily inside the stations, sometimes it doesn’t.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231210_235550442_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231218_105228134_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h2 id="other-notes">Other Notes</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Something unexpected to me, which cannot be transmitted through visual media, is the collection of smells around New York, in almost all parts of the city, except a set of parks and neighborhoods mostly outside Manhattan. The smell of garbage (since it is comment that it accumulates in heaps of bags on city sidewalks), burnt street meat, horse manure in some parts of Central Park, a smell I can only describe as pervasive detergent / laundry smell that could even be detected inside several buildings like the MET and Delis; the strong smell of road paint (since it appears that several of the streets were recently repainted), and signature smells from the subway</li>
  <li>Several subway lines are relatively shallow, so they are easily heard at street level. They also generally run below the roads themselves, which I would assume to make it easier when building incredibly high skyscrapers whose foundations run quite deep.</li>
  <li>Be attentive of your surroundings and where you walk, such dodging through garbage debris and sidewalk cellar doors, be them open or <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/2015/01/26/man-dies-falling-through-cellar-doors-in-brooklyn/">closed</a></li>
  <li>Be prepared to encounter people who are not as well off, and might be living in the streets. Use your judgment, keep out of confusions, be respectable and don’t engage with people who have serious mental issues. If you are in a rougher area, memorize your path when possible, and stop at a local shop if you need to get your bearings. Use your common sense</li>
  <li>You might have noticed that I didn’t mention the common Edge / Top of the Rock / Summit One / Empire State Building / etc observation decks. It’s not that I don’t enjoy incredible views, but it didn’t fall high enough on the list of priorities, specially because I’ve had the opportunity to see skyline views through other buildings I’ve passed by, such as the Hotel.</li>
  <li>I tend to like long trans-atlantic flights, since they provide a moment of low stimuli, where there is less incentive to use the internet. My personal piece of advice would be to avoid the usual in-flight entertainment. I love to use them to resume a book or to write down my reflections from a trip for example (several of article lines were written during the return flight)</li>
  <li>This only shows my ignorance, but I had no idea that so many well-known artists were originally from New York, like Jay-Z (Brooklyn), Cardi B (South Bronx), Spike Lee (Brooklyn), and of course, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RciKM866Rhk">Jenny from the block</a>. That explains why I’ve consecutively heard “Empire State of Mind”, from Jay-Z and Alicia Keys (Hell’s Kitchen), and “All I want for Christmas is You”, from Mariah Carey (raised in Huntington).</li>
</ul>

<div class="image-mosaic">
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231217_201354728_2.jpg')"></div>
  <div class="image-mosaic-card" style="background-image: url('/files/nyc/pPXL_20231209_194823102_2.jpg')"></div>
</div>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>Ever since I was a kid I had a considerable fascination with the USA. The culture that arrived through the small and big screens, the big companies and entrepreneurs that I admired, the language, the people I’ve met along the way, the stories. Having had the opportunity to visit and experience it first hand was a true privilege. I’ve lived it like it was my last time, and it imprinted in me several thoughts and perspectives that I’m sure to last a lifetime.</p>

<p>New York ain’t no DisneyLand, and Elmo’s pictures in Times Square don’t come for free either, so set expectations accordingly. It can be one of the most fulfilling experiences you’ll ever have. I advise you to come prepared and plan accordingly.</p>

<p>Frank Sinatra sang that he wants “to wake up in the city that doesn’t sleep”. That phrase has a deep meaning that only struck me during my trip. The city does not indeed sleep. The Times Square lights, 24 hour subway, the constant movement. Living in NYC wakes you up, not only literally, but also figuratively. It wakes you up to a different reality that keeps you on your toes in several ways. In a way, it’s a celebration of life.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
