<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-10-21T13:52:32+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://lopespm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Relative Cost / Benefit of an Investment]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/10/14/investment_relative_cost_gain.html"/>
    <updated>2023-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/10/14/investment_relative_cost_gain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you spend <span>$</span>1,000 to acquire film equipment (camera, microphones, and lights) to shoot YouTube videos. If you use this equipment to film and publish 2 videos, it means that each of those videos costs <span>$</span>500 to produce. If 100 videos are published, each of them cost <span>$</span>10. If all of these videos are able to generate <span>$</span>10 of revenue, then the entire cost of the initial investment was amortized.</p>

<p>The above is a severely gross simplification<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the key point is that an investment left unused has a high associated cost. In the case above, if only two videos were to be produced, then it would have been a better idea to rent the equipment instead.</p>

<p>This simple heuristic of mapping the investment cost to its usage and upside, can be a potential rule of thumb in different scenarios.</p>

<h2 id="other-examples">Other Examples</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Apartment Rent</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You are renting an apartment for <span>$</span>1,000 per month. During the week you work in an office, on weekends you are sometimes out, and during the year you take sporadic vacations outside. Let’s say that, on average, you spend 14 hours per day on your apartment, including sleep → 14 hours * 30 days = 420 hours.</li>
      <li>This means that it costs costs about <span>$</span>33 per day to live in the apartment, or <span>$</span>2.3 per hour.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Study → Work → Net Worth Gain</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You studied 30 hours per week for 3 years (30 hours per week * 52 weeks * 3 years = 4680 hours) to land a job that increases your net worth <span>$</span>10.000 every year (on average), for 30 years. A total of <span>$</span>300,000 of networth gains.</li>
      <li>This means that you will gain about <span>$</span>64 for each hour invested in studying, or $274 per day.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Clothing</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You buy pair of trousers for <span>$</span>50, and wear them twice per month throughout for 2 years (24 months * 2 times per month = 48 times these were used).</li>
      <li>This means that it costs about <span>$</span>1 to wear them each time.
        <ul>
          <li>By contrast, if these trousers were only used <a href="https://www.vox.com/2019/9/12/20860620/fast-fashion-zara-hm-forever-21-boohoo-environment-cost">7 times</a>, it would cost about <span>$</span>7.14 to wear them each time.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Gaming</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You buy a Playstation 5 for <a href="https://direct.playstation.com/en-us/buy-consoles/playstation5-console"><span>$</span>499.99</a> and <a href="https://www.pushsquare.com/news/2019/01/ps4_has_a_very_high_software_attach_rate_average_player_owns_around_ten_games">10 games</a> (<span>$</span>60 each) totalling <span>$</span>1.100. You play <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/playstation/comments/ld7zuo/what_was_your_total_amount_of_hours_played_in_2020/">60 hours per year</a> during 5 years (60 hours * 5 years = 300 hours).</li>
      <li>This means that each playing hour costs about <span>$</span>3.6.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Phone</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You buy an iPhone 15 Pro for <span>$</span>999, and use it <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-59952557">4.8 hours per day</a> during <a href="https://www.iphonelife.com/content/how-long-do-iphone-last-how-to-know-when-to-upgrade-your-iphone">2 years</a> (4.8 hours * 365 days * 2 years = 3504 hours).</li>
      <li>This means that it costs <span>$</span>0.29 per hour of active usage.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Computer</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You buy a MacBook Pro 13” for <span>$</span>$1299, and <a href="https://mediapeanut.com/how-long-should-a-macbook-pro-last/">use it</a> 3 times per week for 2.5 hours per session, throughout 7 years (3 times per week * 2.5 hours * 52 weeks per year * 7 years = 2730 hours)</li>
      <li>This means that it costs <span>$</span>0.48 per hour of usage.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Musical Instrument</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You buy a guitar for <span>$</span>100. You play the guitar once per week, for one hour, during 2 years. 52 weeks * 1 hour * 2 years = 104 hours.</li>
      <li>This means that each hour playing the guitar has a cost of <span>$</span>1.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Video Streaming</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You have a standard Netflix subscription that costs <a href="https://help.netflix.com/en/node/24926/us"><span>$</span>15.99 per month</a>, and watch <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/advisor/vpn/netflix-statistics">3.2 hours</a> (3.2 hours * 30 days = 96 hours per month) of videos throughout that month.</li>
      <li>This mean that each hour costs about $0.17.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Audio Streaming</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>You have a premium Spotify subscription that costs <a href="https://www.spotify.com/us/premium/"><span>$</span>10.99 per month</a>, and listen to about <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/813876/spotify-monthly-active-users-time-spent-listening/">25 hours</a> of music and podcasts throughout that month.</li>
      <li>This means that each hour costs about <span>$</span>0.44.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>We could go on with further examples, as this simple heuristic could be applied to several scenarios, and the cost cost benefit analysis could have any perspective one so desires, but I would invite you to visit your storage and search for something you acquired long ago that got used less times than expected, and do a rough calculation of what was it’s relative cost / benefit.
The same for any other investment you did in the past.</p>

<p>Was it a surprising result?</p>

<p>How did it stack up against your initial expectations?</p>

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This gross simplification is meant to keep the example simple, and does not take into account other direct and indirect costs, such as the computer needed to edit the videos, electricity costs, office space costs, labor costs. It also does not take into account the gained equity, this is, you could sell the equipment and get some of that investment back. This was not considered because if the equipment breaks its value is rendered to zero, and when / if it is sold, it would be for a fraction at the initial value, not only because its inherent value would likely decrease through the years, but also because of inflation.</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importance of Goal Clarity for Delegation]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/09/30/goal_clarity_in_delegation.html"/>
    <updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/09/30/goal_clarity_in_delegation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Previously, in <a href="/2022/03/22/learnings-software-engineer-techlead.html">“Learnings as a Software Engineer Techlead”</a>, I’ve alluded to the 75/25 rule, where if you are ~75% certain that someone will correctly execute a given project/task, then delegate. The other ~25% is the unknown space that the person needs in order to learn, explore, make errors, innovate and grow.</p>

<p>If the project/task was decided to be delegated, what comes next?</p>

<h2 id="clarity-of-goals">Clarity of Goals</h2>

<p>One common challenge I’ve confronted when delegating was how unpredictable and uncontrollable the results felt upon handing over the work. This unstructured approach often left me thinking how I could decrease the non-completion risk by diminishing the delegated scope, and created confusion on the delegatee side on how they could proceed.</p>

<p>One tidbit of information from the “Who not How” book provided the guidance and structure to unlock this issue:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>(…) research has found that teams who have high levels of autonomy but low clarity goals, as well as little performance feedback, perform worse than teams with low autonomy.</p>

  <p><em>― <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Who-Not-How-Accelerating-Teamwork-ebook/dp/B0867ZJ151">Who not How, by Dan Sullivan with Dr. Benjamin Hardy</a></em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is claimed in the above research that teams which have high autonomy, high goal clarity and regular feedback on their results, were observed to have their performance shooting through the roof.</p>

<p>Apart from regular feedback, goal clarity is incredibly important, and even though it might sound obvious, it can be overlooked and drowned out on the process of delegation.</p>

<h2 id="clarity-in-practice">Clarity, in Practice</h2>

<p>After the above realization, I’ve made it a priority for each piece of delegated work to clearly define what was expected as an outcome, its definition of done, important milestones and deadlines, when should an issue be scaled to me, and which are the ownerships for each of the participants.</p>

<p>All of the above communicated in a clear and concise way, and preferably publicly documented to increase accountability and decrease ambiguity (depending on the situation, merely communicating these verbally might be enough, especially if the task is simple).</p>

<h2 id="the-delegation-formula">The Delegation Formula</h2>

<p>Given the above, the proposed formula for delegation is:</p>

<p><em>Delegation = [ 75/25 rule -&gt; Goal Clarity + Autonomy + Regular Feedback ]</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life has several exits]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/19/life_exits.html"/>
    <updated>2023-08-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/19/life_exits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Life has several exits:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The exit from your workplace. The last day of work for your employer or your company.</li>
  <li>The exit from that youth group that accompanied you through teenage years and early adulthood.</li>
  <li>The exit from your high-school.</li>
  <li>The exit from your hometown.</li>
  <li>The exit from a long term relationship.</li>
  <li>The exit from life. Your funeral.</li>
</ul>

<p>Upon your exit, your contributions, actions, decisions, opinions and presence most likely will have affected the trajectories of the people and the world around you, in obvious and less obvious ways. Perhaps your own trajectory was deeply changed as well.</p>

<p>These exits may be celebrated, be a special day with fulfilling words and thoughts. They may be the last time you see a set of people. The last time you will see them in your entire life.</p>

<p>Perhaps upon your final exit, you have made such consequential dents on the world that your name will be engraved into the annals of history for centuries to come. On the other hand, contemporary personalities such Steve Jobs, Bill Gates, Elon Musk and Warren Buffet might be mostly forgotten a few centuries from now. People will move on, so most likely you should be grateful if your loved ones keep you in their thoughts for those ensuing decades.</p>

<p>Life has several exits. Life is also short and limited. There’ll be a finite number of exits you will experience. Make the most out of each period they enclose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The real question behind 'what do you want?']]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html"/>
    <updated>2023-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s easy to want something. If you are fortunate enough to be on <a href="https://www.gapminder.org/fw/income-levels/income-level-4/">income level 4</a> living in a peaceful nation, the world has so much to offer, within easy reach. Yet, the currencies required to enjoy them are limited: time, energy, health, money. Even though it is easy to make lists of everything one wants (typically occurring on yearly passages, such as new year’s and anniversaries), only a handful of them are achievable.</p>

<h2 id="smaller-lists-require-sacrifices">Smaller lists require sacrifices</h2>
<p>Given that lengthy lists are unachievable, they need to be slimmed down to a manageable and realistic size. They need to be prioritized. <em>Prioritization</em> is an euphemism for <em>sacrificing</em>.</p>

<p>It’s easy to want something, it’s hard to choose it against another desirable one.</p>

<h2 id="an-example">An example</h2>

<p>At the start of each year, I produce a small list of 3 to 4 high priority goals and 1 optional low priority goal of what I want to achieve by end of it, along with a small description on why I want them, and their impact. This takes several hours, sometimes days to put together, because of all the other ones that need to be left out.</p>

<p>Once the list is made though, it’s incredibly powerful due to it’s easy recall. This means that whenever I am faced with conflicting preferences, I can easily remember it and know in a snap what is the right thing to do. That is the real power behind that list. It’s guiding all the tiny small steps and decisions happening throughout the year, bringing me progressivily closer to those goals.</p>

<h2 id="the-question">The question</h2>
<p>The real question behind defining <em>knowing what we want</em> is actually <em>what we are willing to sacrifice</em>. Once the latter is defined and we are 100% convinced about it, then <em>knowing what we want</em> is bullet proof and easy to follow through. </p>

<p>What are you willing to sacrifice?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing as a form of thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking.html"/>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Large language models (LLM) like ChatGPT triggered a remarkable societal and computational shift that feels comparable to the impact from the initial internet era with its first impressive search engines like Google. LLMs are the toast of the town.</p>

<p>Writing emails, reports, school homework, analysis, code, summaries. The list goes on.</p>

<p>Save from when you would delegate this task to another fellow human, long hours would be passed in the past trying to conjure a piece of text that could communicate something to another entity. Now this can be made at scale, at low cost, with low effort.</p>

<p>Since we are still liable for the results of this tool, i.e. it’s still our name on the email sender, instead of just sending that email, we might first read that LLM output, interpret it, understand it, and then send it.</p>

<h2 id="more-than-just-text">More than just text</h2>

<p>Text is a form of communication. If something, or someone wrote it for us, certain decisions were made along the way to convey the goal that we gave. Out of the many paths possible to crystallize that piece of knowledge into a piece text, one of them was chosen.</p>

<p>I would claim that something gets lost on that delegation.</p>

<p>The writing process is more than just the production of text. Many times it requires the exploration of different perspectives, thinking deeply and coming to terms that we don’t know enough about a subject and need to learn more about it.</p>

<p>For example, it’s essential for me to have a notebook at hand to take notes during meetings and formal discussions. I write phrases, loose words, make small diagrams, jot down some reminders. Some of them are never to be re-read again, others I revisit to structure them down into a concise structure. Most of all, they help me think about a problem.</p>

<p>Same holds for notes and articles. I start with a cloud of loosely related ideas, which I attempt to refine into a structured form. Similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_Diamond_(design_process_model)">double diamond</a> process.</p>

<p>Same for books. Several times I’ve come to terms that I learned close to nothing about a book read one month before. Or conversations. Or movies. Or experiences.</p>

<p>This is, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=otazg3TuPWM">except</a> if I reflected or acted about them. Except if I wrote down my conclusions about them.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For me, taking notes helps make sure that I’m really thinking hard about what’s in there. If I disagree with the book, sometimes it takes a long time to read the books because I’m writing so much in the margin</p>

  <p><em>― <a href="https://youtu.be/eTFy8RnUkoU?t=11">Bill Gates</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
