<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-11T01:02:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://lopespm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story of the Human Body Book: Lessons]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/10/story-human-body-lessons.html"/>
    <updated>2025-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2025/02/10/story-human-body-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently finished reading <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Story-Human-Body-Evolution-Disease/dp/030774180X">The Story of the Human Body: Evolution, Health, and Disease</a>, a book from Daniel Lieberman of how the human body evolved over millions of years, that I would recommend all Humans to read. These are are my main takeaways:</p>

<!--more-->

<h1 id="why-we-are-the-way-we-are">Why we are, the way we are</h1>

<h2 id="it-is-all-about-how-energy-is-used">It is all about how energy is used</h2>

<p>Us humans and other living beings are essentially organisms that use energy to reproduce and maintain ourselves.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Natural selection prunes off organisms that don’t use energy in a way that is suited to their conditions and environment.</li>
  <li><strong>Every energy transformation feature / trait has a cost</strong>. For example: walking upright allows one to walk using less energy, but lacks the speed of a quadruped.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="long-distance-walking--running-machines">Long Distance Walking / Running Machines</h2>

<h3 id="what-drove-selection-for-bipedalism">What drove selection for bipedalism</h3>

<p>Hominid bipedalism was likely to have been initially selected to help the first hominids forage and obtain food more effectively in the face of major climate change</p>

<p>Between 10 and 5 million years ago, the earth climate cooled considerably, and overall effect in Africa that caused rainforests to shrink and woodlands to expand. If you were to be in the heart of the rainforest, you likely wouldn’t have noticed much of a difference, but if you were in the margins, this change must have been stressful. As the forest shrinks and becomes woodland, ripe fruits become less abundant, more dispersed and more seasonal. These changes would require you to travel farther to get the same amount of food.</p>

<p>Walking on two legs is more energy efficient for longer routes. Main trade off is less speed, because we could not gallop. We are 3x more efficient moving a distance of 6km than a chimp.</p>

<h3 id="the-consequences-of-bipedalism">The consequences of bipedalism</h3>

<p>Not only was endurance walking useful, but also long distance running was likely selected for scavenging. Running to fresh carcasses, running with food and, persistence hunting, where a big animal is followed  by running and walking on sun. They need to find shades and pant, and eventually collapse due to heat stroke.</p>

<ul>
  <li>We are unique in that we have sweat glands all over the body. Other apes mostly have on the palms of their hands. And we. Don’t have fur, allowing the air to come in contact with sweat and cool your body down. This is essential for long distance running and walking.
    <ul>
      <li>Other animals have fur that reflects solar radiation, but does  it allow body to cool down through sweat</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Other features that help us to run effectively. Some of them not specially helpful for walking, like shorter toes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Big gluteus maximus muscles, mostly active when running.</li>
  <li>Nuchal ligament is a back neck ligament that connects head to arm that helps stabilize the head while running. It was developed independently in humans and other animals well adapted for running.    </li>
  <li>Big semi circular inner ear canals to have more signals to allow for stabilization of our inner systems, such eye actions to compensate for the jiggle.</li>
  <li>Predominance of slow twitch fibers in legs. More endurance, thus compromising speed.</li>
  <li>Narrow waists, wide shoulders, shorter toes.</li>
  <li>Long noses are selected for walking long distances without drying up. Nose humidifies air coming into the lungs, which is necessary, and retains moisture going out. Trade-off is that lungs have to work a bit harder.</li>
</ul>

<p>All of these walking and running adaptations made us clumsy climbing trees, like shorter toes, but also freed up our hands to interact with the world, create the first tools and throw objects (we are especially good at throwing, having shoulders and upper body that makes it ideal for it), which not only provided some protection, but also allowed us to obtain and process fallback / lower quality foods (which were essential due to scarcity from global cooling climate).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Only mad dogs and Englishmen go out in the midday sun
<em>― Noël Coward</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="better-dexterity-tools-cognition-less-digestive-cost-more-energy-availability">Better dexterity, tools, cognition, less digestive cost, more energy availability</h3>

<p>In the average adult human, the brain represents about 2% of the body weight, but accounts to about 20% of total energy consumption.</p>

<p>As the ability to create and use tools allowed the gathering and processing of fallback foods, more usable energy was able to be extracted. Processing foods to smaller chunks, or cooking it, largely increases how much energy can be obtained during digestion, but also requires less intense chewing (we didn’t need as bigger teeth as australopithecus, which resulted in use losing the snout due to less space being needed in the head) and shorter intestines, which reduce energy required for digestion, increases surplus energy to be used by the brain. These factors selected hominids with better manual dexterity and better cognition.</p>

<p>Our manual dexterity, and what it unlocks, plays a big role in our evolution.</p>

<h3 id="energy-hungry-brain-and-relation-with-fat">Energy hungry brain, and relation with fat</h3>

<p>If our brain<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> is deprived of glucose for even 1 minute or two, it causes irreparable damage. This likely selected humans to become unusually fat. 400 to 500 calories daily, are for the brain alone. Extra intense thought only increases hourly usage by 5 calories per hour.</p>

<p>Hunter gatherer mothers have to expend about 2.3k calories for themselves alone to raise kids. Babies are unusually fat. 60 percent of their energy consumption is for the brain. It takes 12M calories to grow a child into a full grown adult. Twice as much as those needed for a chimpanzee.</p>

<p>Our way of living affected the size of our gut so profoundly, that now we are pretty much dependent on cooking to get the caloric intake we need for our body and brain.</p>

<p>Exercise is not great to lose fat (unless you don’t succumb to overeating after exercise) but it’s good to prevent fat gain. It increases muscle (and not fat) sensitivity to insulin and makes the muscles more readily available to store energy, and also increases the number of mitochondria that burn fat and sugar.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A lean man that doesn’t exercise has twice the risk of dying, compared to obese men that engaged in regular physical activity</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="high-offspring-investment">High offspring investment</h3>

<p>Life is fundamentally a way of using energy to make more life.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If the environment is risky: quick returns are favored, where little investment is made during life, but a lot during reproduction. Such as spiders, salmon that lay a lot of eggs, hoping that a lucky few will survive</li>
  <li>But when resources are predictable and infant mortality is low, it is feasible to mature slowly and invest a lot in raising the few offspring. This is the strategy of humans, elephants and apes.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cost-of-clear-speech-choking">Cost of clear speech: choking</h3>

<p>What good is it to have a good idea, if you can’t communicate it? One of the main features we developed as humans was our ability to use speech to clearly communicate thoughts, ideas, plans, and other information.</p>

<p>The price is that we are the only mammal that can risk asphyxiation when swallowing something too large or imprecisely<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, because of the big common space behind the tongue through which food and air both travel to get either into the esophagus or trachea, a consequence of our short and retracted faces and selection of anatomy that favors clear speech. As a result, food sometimes gets lodged on the back of the throat, blocking the airway.</p>

<p>When you are having lunch with friends, consider that you are doing two things: speaking clearly, and swallowing a little dangerously.</p>

<h1 id="diseases">Diseases</h1>

<p>We’ve created a system that makes people sick through a surplus of energy, and keeps them alive without needing to turn down the energy flow</p>

<p>Lieberman presents the concepts of Mismatch diseases and Dysevolution:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Mismatch diseases</strong>: Diseases that occur because our bodies are poorly or inadequately adapted to environments in which we now live. An example would be eating large amounts of sugar or being very physically inactive leads to problems like diabetes or heart disease that then make us sick    </li>
  <li><strong>Dysevolution</strong>: Form of cultural evolution where the symptoms of a mismatch disease are treated, but not the cause.  One example of this is cavities, which are treated with dentists, and not by removing the sugar from our diet, which is the underlying cause. Lieberman emphasizes that mismatched diseases and their causes must be understood fully to treat the true cause.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-much-energy-surplus">Too much energy surplus</h2>

<p>Our ancestors ate fruits as sweet as carrots, but as energy dense foods had their availability increased<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, more humans moved from subsistence farming and physically strenuous jobs to lower physical effort jobs (in the USA, only 11 per cent are actually factory workers. The rest are in management, services, wealth management and banking services), the same mechanisms that made us effective is storing energy and craving certain foods, are also the ones that have become maladapted to our current environment.</p>

<p>It has been only about 300 generations since we’ve been subsistence farmers, which didn’t give enough time for natural selection and body adaptations to develop.</p>

<h3 id="sugar-and-fat-absorption-mechanisms-and-effects">Sugar and fat absorption mechanisms and effects</h3>

<p>Your body can use <strong>glucose</strong> as energy readily, but <strong>fructose</strong> can only be worked as fat or in the liver.</p>

<ul>
  <li>When the liver is flooded with too much fructose, too quickly, it is overwhelmed and converts most of the fructose into fat, triglycerides. Some of this fat fills up the liver and causes inflammation, which blocks the action of insulin in the liver.    </li>
  <li>Chain reaction occurs, in that the liver releases stores of glucose into the bloodstream, driving the pancreas to release more insulin, shuttling extra glucose and fat into cells. The rest of fat created by the liver is dumped into the bloodstream, where it ends up in fat cells, your arteries, and other potentially bad places.
    <ul>
      <li>Visceral fat is more hormone sensitive than other fat cells, resulting that its stores are dumped fat more readily than other fat cells, and since it sits close to the liver, it tends to clog up the liver and constrain its glucagon function when it dumps fat.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Sugar is 50 percent fructose; fruits also have it. An apple for example has 13g of sugar. 30 percent is glucose, the rest is fructose.</li>
</ul>

<p>Comparing an apple to a highly processed fruit roll, apart from nutritional differences:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Fiber</strong> covering the apple (the skin) prevents the full absorption of sugar. Fiber makes food stay longer in the stomach, generating signals that release appetite suppressing hormones.
    <ul>
      <li>Speed of eating and amount of fiber is important. That’s why salads and low glycemic foods should come first in your meal</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>An apple gives your pancreas time to realize how much insulin to release. On the other hand, high glycemic, calorie dense foods are easily and quickly absorbed in the digestive process, prompting the pancreas to produce a lot of insulin, which it often overshoots, plunging blood sugar levels, which in turn makes us hungry.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="height-as-a-measure-of-extra-caloric-availability-and-health">Height as a measure of extra caloric availability and health</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Maximum height is constrained by genes, but available energy will limit actual height. Because if you spend most of your energy fighting diseases and toiling in the fields, then you won’t have extra calories to gain height. 
    <ul>
      <li>It was seen for populations that turned to subsistence  farming, like in Asia and America, to have had their height shortened. For example, subsistence farming children spent about 4 or 6 hours working, as compared to children of hunter gatherers that would spend about 1 to 2 hours working in tasks like gathering firewood and helping in domestic tasks.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Tall people are naturally selected in hot climates, because of higher surface area to release heat. Colder climates select for shorter ones, because they can retain more heat.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-much-stress">Too much Stress</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Stress is an ancient adaptation to save you from dangerous situations, and activates energy reserves when you need them.
    <ul>
      <li>If a Lion roars nearby, a car nearly runs you over, or if you go for a run, your brain triggers your adrenal glands (which sit on top of your kidneys), to secrete a small dosage of the hormone cortisol.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cortisol does not cause stress. It is released when you are stressed.</li>
  <li>One of cortisol’s functions is to cause liver and fat cells (specially visceral fat cells) to release glucose into the bloodstream. It increases heart rate and blood pressure, makes you more alert and prevents sleep, and makes you crave for calorie rich foods.
    <ul>
      <li>Chain reaction for long bouts of stress: as you crave more energy rich foods and consume them, this increases insulin levels, which inhibits the brain’s response to leptin (fat cells release it to increase satiety), as such, the stressed brain thinks you are starving, so activates reflexes to make you hungry and other reflexes ot make you less active.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-little-sleep">Too little Sleep</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Insufficient sleep promotes stress and stress promotes insufficient sleep. Higher income populations get on average more sleep, likely because of having of less challenges of making ends meet and less stress
    <ul>
      <li>Sleep deprivation is sometimes caused by elevated levels of stress, thus more cortisol.</li>
      <li>Sleep deprivation elevates the ghrelin hormone, a hunger hormone that stimulates appetite.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Only until recently did we do start sleeping alone or with a single partner the child detached from parents during sleep, and in stimulus deprived environments
    <ul>
      <li>On the other hand, hunter gatherers used to sleep in relatively noisy environments, woke up at about 7h, took a one hour nap in the middle of the day, and then went to sleep at 9pm, where they would get two sleeps. Likely an adaptation, that prevented predator under vigilance</li>
      <li>But now we have entertainment and lights that are able to keep us awake far beyond 9pm, in sensory deprived environments, with less exercise, excess calories, and stress</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="too-crowded">Too Crowded</h2>

<p>Villages, cities, are our human fortresses from the wild. Because we have that fortress, we don’t need to carry arms and be attentive to outer animal threats, like lions. Mostly. There were costs to these though:</p>

<ul>
  <li>High concentration of humans in low<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> sanitation<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> environments facilitated the spread of these diseases, and close contact with animals gave rise to diseases such as influenza, coming from pigs.</li>
  <li>Before the 1900s, the death rates in cities such as London were higher than in rural areas, so they needed a large influx of rural immigrants to keep them going. Which they did, because of a larger scope of opportunities and wealth.</li>
  <li>Cows’ digestive systems were adapted to eat grass, but in the crowded industrial complexes they are fed grains, and as a consequence they have to be constantly medicated with antibiotics, to counter their chronic diarrhea and diseases coming from these crowded, filthy environments.
    <ul>
      <li>Antibiotics given to industrially raised animals because microbes also consume energy. So this makes them fatter</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cancer">Cancer</h2>

<p>There is a <strong>positive correlation between cancer development in reproductive organs and high energy balance</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Women’s bodies adapted towards delivering as many children as possible, and are maladapted towards having a high energy balance:
    <ul>
      <li>High exposure to estrogen incentives cell division in breast, ovaries, and uterus, in preparation of a fertilized embryo. Chances to develop cancer in these organs increases substantially from the number of menstrual cycles, and decreases as the number of children the woman bears.
        <ul>
          <li>During the menstrual cycle the levels of estrogen and progesterone rise significantly</li>
          <li>While nursing, chances of having cancer go down, as there is less exposure to reproductive hormones, and likely breast feeding aids flushing memory ducts.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>For women, the incidence of breast cancer was observed to be higher in nuns (hence, the nuns disease)</li>
      <li>Women in contemporary USA have about 350-400 menstrual cycles, start menstruating at 12, 13, and then stop at early fifties
        <ul>
          <li>Hunter gatherers have about 150 cycles, and start menstruating at 16. They spent most of their life being pregnant or nursing, while barely having energy to do so.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Obese women can have 40 per cent more estrogen, because of the role of fat in the endocrine system. So after menopause being obese is correlated with cancer in women</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>For men, higher exposure to testosterone throughout their life is correlated with prostate cancer. But correlation is not as strong as in women.</li>
</ul>

<p>More exercise results in lower chances of cancer. Likely because the energy spent there is not otherwise spent on reproductive hormones that have these side effects.</p>

<ul>
  <li>There is <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC1402378/">compelling evidence</a> that routine physical activity is associated with reductions in the incidence of specific cancers, in particular breast and colon cancer. Physically active men and women exhibited a 30%–40% reduction in the relative risk of colon cancer, and physically active women a 20%–30% reduction in the relative risk of breast cancer compared with their inactive counterparts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="use-it-or-lose-it-no-strain-no-gain">Use it, or lose it; No strain, no gain</h2>

<p>Imagine you are tasked with building a robot that is aimed to accomplish a task in the future that is unknown. You can either create a series of specialized robots (e.g. only able to swim, to dig, jump, etc), or a single one that adapts to multiple situations. When you don’t know what the robot will do, the latter works best. That is how animals and plants work. But if you don’t use it, you lose it.</p>

<h3 id="bone-loss">Bone loss</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Bones are a reserve of calcium, an essential component to the body. If there is not enough calcium, osteoclasts start dissolving them at a higher rate.</li>
  <li>Most people will reach their peak bone mass between the ages of 25 and 30, then it keeps going away. Specially struts in spongy bones like vertebrae and joints. They don’t come back.    </li>
  <li>Just having a supply of calcium and vitamin D is not enough. You also need to load your bones, otherwise the osteoblasts will not kick in to start building bone.
    <ul>
      <li>High intensity weight bearing can stop or even moderately reverse some loss.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="teeth-problems">Teeth problems</h3>

<p>If you don’t chew enough when you are young, teeth will become misaligned, and overcrowding happens, leading to issues on wisdom tooth growth for example. The body needs that stress.</p>

<h2 id="allergies-and-hygiene-hypothesis">Allergies and hygiene hypothesis</h2>

<p>Hygiene hypothesis states that early childhood exposure to particular microorganisms (such as the gut flora and helminth parasites) protects against allergies by properly tuning the immune system. In particular, a lack of such exposure is thought to lead to poor immune tolerance. There are two main hypothesis for it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>First hypothesis is that T helper 1 cells are not busy enough<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, which increases the number of T helper 2 cells. With more sterilized environments, children’s immune systems are less busy, having more of these T helper 2 cells swimming unemployed, leading to a higher probability that they react to a non-threatening component. First reaction is mild, but the immune system keeps a memory, so the following time that component is detected, it’s devastating.</li>
  <li>Second hypothesis is microbiome destabilization, the “old friends” hypothesis. Microbes have evolved to cohabit with others and us in a cold war kind of environment. Once you start killing several of them with antibiotics and cleaning products, you destabilize their equilibrium
    <ul>
      <li>There is a case to be made that possible treatments would be to have fezes or filth</li>
      <li>And it also follows that after antibiotic treatments, that probiotics are taken</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="we-frequently-mistake-comfort-for-wellbeing">We frequently mistake comfort for wellbeing</h2>

<p>Hannah Arendt introduced the expression and concept of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eichmann_in_Jerusalem#Banality_of_evil">banality of evil</a>, where a common person does nefarious actions, since they became accepted and normalized in their society.</p>

<p>Actions that we perceive as normal, such as usage of cancer inducing sodium nitrate in foods (which stems for a trade-off between structural economic gain and health), wearing comfortable shoes, reading and sitting, are in fact not normal when seen through the lenses of long term evolution.</p>

<h3 id="comfortable-shoes">Comfortable shoes</h3>

<p>Our feet have adapted for us to efficiently run and walk, but highly cushioned, constraining shoes deform and inhibit our feet from fulfilling their purpose</p>

<ul>
  <li>Habitual barefoot people have much lower incidence of flat foot, which very likely is due to the high usage of the foot arch, which is restrained on comfortable shoes with arch support, which instead overload the plantar fascia, leading to plantar fasciitis</li>
  <li>A constrained toe box restrains how much stability the foot can provide, and an unbalanced foot leads to an unbalanced knee, hip, body.</li>
  <li>I’ve personally transitioned to using barefoot shoes daily and when hiking, and can only recommend them after using them for more than one year.
    <ul>
      <li>One common question is if these are appropriate on hard terrain. Turns out that your foot already has a built in mechanism, which is to forefoot / midfoot strike, instead of heel strike. Try to jump to see how your foot automatically lands using the ball of your foot, and how softly you land, when compared to a (dangerous) similar jump landing on your heel.</li>
      <li>Going barefoot or using minimal shoes, provides you full perception of the terrain and impact, so you’ll adapt towards hitting the ground more softly, and not using heel strikes as much.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>

<p>Myopia is a formerly rare evolutionary mismatch that is exacerbated by modern environments. In the USA and Europe, about one third of all children (aged 7 to 17) become nearsighted.</p>

<p>Evidence suggests that being nearsighted used to be very rare: that less than three per cent prevalence amongst hunter gatherers and populations that practices subsistence agriculture. In 1813, it was noted that amongst the Queen’s guards, many were myopic. On the hand, from the 10k foot guard, less than half dozen were myopic.</p>

<p>The mechanisms of how myopia are still not fully understood, but two main causes are suggested:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Close work, forcing long bouts of close focus. Singapore <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4041336/">study</a> found that students who read more than 2 books per week had strong myopia.</li>
  <li>Children spending <a href="https://bjo.bmj.com/content/104/5/593">more time outdoors</a> have lower incidence of myopia. Brightness of light and visual stimuli appear to have a beneficial effect.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="sitting">Sitting</h3>

<p>While sitting in different positions to rest after strenuous activity has been around for much of our species, only until recently have we been multiple hours sitting in a chair, day after day, which is a risk factor towards:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Muscle atrophy and shortening: calf muscle shortening also happens for high heels usage</li>
  <li>Lower back pain. To prevent this issue, make sure to maintain a strong back via moderate intensity load, but not too much load, like furniture movers.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="how-to-solve-these-issues">How to solve these issues</h1>

<p>One solution would be to wait for natural selection to sort out these problems, which is very unlikely due to the high rate of change in our societies and environments, in short time windows. As the commander of the Albigensian Crusade said, on a mission to eliminate heretics: <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caedite_eos._Novit_enim_Dominus_qui_sunt_eius.">“Kill them all; let God sort them out.”</a></em></p>

<p>We are all subject to influence by advertising, availability and peer pressure, but we can be nudged to acquire behaviours that benefit us. Daniel Lieberman suggests:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We should invest in prevention over treatment    </li>
  <li>Although adults have the right to get sick, children need guidance. How different is it to restrict fast foods to them, to restricting which movies they are able to attend? Or availability of alcohol to them?</li>
  <li>Just like nature obliged us to do the right thing and evolved our behaviours, government has the right and duty to have information to do rational decisions and nudge or even push us to do so:
    <ul>
      <li>Question is how much and where and when</li>
      <li>Government shouldn’t prevent you from smoking, but “you are free to do as wish, as long as I don’t have to pay for it”</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="culture-does-not-allow-us-to-transcend-biology">Culture does not allow us to transcend biology</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Culture is roughly everything we do and monkeys don’t.
<em>― FitzRoy Richard Somerset</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Clever as we are, we cannot modify our human bodies any more than superficial ways. And it’s arrogant to think we can engineer body parts any better than nature did. There will be no Pasteur for mismatched diseases.</p>

<p>We should come to terms that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We are fat, furless, bipedal primates that crave sugar, salt, fat and starch.</li>
  <li>We crave comfort, but our bodies are endurance athlete machines.</li>
  <li>As Voltaire wrote: “Let us cultivate our garden”. <strong>We must cultivate our body.</strong></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Compared to other animals with the same body weight, they have a fifth of the brain size, and double the intestine system. Size of the brain correlates with the size of the group. Humans are able to interact with 100 to 200 individuals.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Choking on food is the fourth leading cause of accidental death in the USA.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Between 1985 and 2000, the purchasing power of the US dollar decreased by 59 per cent, the price of fruit and vegetables doubled, fish increased by 30 per cent, diary about the same. In contrast, sugars and sweets became 25 per cent less expensive, fats and oils 40 per cent, soda 66 percent less expensive. Portion sizes ballooned: in a fast food restaurant in 1955 order of hamburger and fries would yield 412 cals. Today for the same inflation adjusted size, the same order would have double the calories, 920 cals.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>If you are curious of how the sewers of earlier cities smelled, the <a href="https://musee-egouts.paris.fr/en/">Paris Musée des Égouts</a> provides an <em>illustrative</em> tour through these sights and smells  <a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Thomas Crapper did not invent the toilet. But was a pioneer in its mass manufacturing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Crapper#Origin_of_the_word_%22crap%22">Origin of the word “crapper”</a><a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>For example, Hepatitis A virus stimulates T helper 1 cells, which suppress the number of T helper 2 cells<a href="#fnref:6" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2024 Lookback]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/31/2024-lookback.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/31/2024-lookback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s time to wrap up and celebrate 2024, an eventful year that fueled my yearning for internal growth and curiosity, with challenges and lessons I am grateful for.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>I’ve recently built a set of <a href="https://grafana.com/">Grafana</a> dashboards to track my personal goals, which I’ve been finding incredibly interesting to explore and visualise (something that might be interesting to share in a later post).</p>

<h2 id="final-tally">Final Tally</h2>

<p>There are other metrics I track, but specifically to 2024 content creation, these are the final statistics<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="2024 Stats">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/2024_lookback/stats.webp" aria-label="2024 Stats">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/2024_lookback/stats.png" aria-label="2024 Stats">
             <img src="/files/2024_lookback/stats.png" aria-label="2024 Stats">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<ul>
  <li>17 posts on this blog, 16 of them being <a href="https://lopespm.com/notes/">notes</a> (not counting this one), and one of them being a full blog article sharing how to build a <a href="/machine_learning/2024/06/24/personal-llm.html">personal local (Llama3 8B) LLM, extended with WhatsApp and Obsidian data</a></li>
  <li>10 YouTube videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@lopespm">main channel</a>. 8 of them being long form, the other 2 being shorts.</li>
  <li>5 YouTube videos on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@out-and-about-channel">Out and About</a>, a recently created channel where I share random experiences on activities such as walking / hiking around or driving.</li>
</ul>

<p>Notice that the tracked metrics are on the volume of content produced, not their number of views, subscribers, likes. Although keeping track of topline metrics makes sense for a full fledged business, I chose instead to track what I <em>can</em> control, which is my output. At the end of the day, this is a hobby, a labor of love.</p>

<p>If I can influence someone’s life for the better, that will already fill my heart to the brim. This, added to how important posting these contents has become to consolidate and structure my thoughts, and serendipitous opportunities they randomly opened, make this an incredibly satisfying endeavor.</p>

<p>I’ve experienced time and time again that consistency eventually bears wonderful fruits. Who knows which doors might open one day later? I don’t, but I’m curious to find out.</p>

<h2 id="one-day-away">2025, one day away</h2>

<p>With 2024 wrapped up, let’s welcome 2025. <a href="/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html#an-example">I’ve pinned down next year’s goals</a> and will be looking forward to sharing what I learn along the way. Happy new year, and see you on the other side! 🫡</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This dashboard was produced using a custom Grafana dashboard, where the RSS feeds for this blog and YouTube channels were tracked, transformed and presented in simple gauge widgets</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Note Taking]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/30/note-taking.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/30/note-taking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Stack of notebooks">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/note_taking/note_stack.webp" aria-label="Stack of notebooks">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/note_taking/note_stack.png" aria-label="Stack of notebooks">
             <img src="/files/note_taking/note_stack.png" aria-label="Stack of notebooks">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Over the past 4 years, I’ve written about 1820 pages on the 13 A5 notebooks shown in the picture above. This tool has become essential for my job, and in this article I’ll describe the simple process behind it, which I’ve found to deliver consistent results, reliably.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="write-consolidate-repeat">Write, Consolidate, Repeat</h2>

<p>The process I’ve been using for several years is based on <a href="/notes/2023/05/18/solving-task-switching-through-documentation.html">Option 3. of Solving Task Switching Through Documentation</a>, and is broken down in three steps:</p>

<p><strong>1. Write</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Material</strong>: A5 spiral notebook (it makes it easier to be written anywhere, because the pages can always be flipped around in a way that only the writing page is facing up, and the rest of the pages serving as a solid writing surface; plus the notebook’s rings are great for carrying your pen or pencil reliably), with clear pages (this allows for diagrams, phrases, texts, tidbits, collaborations to happen without any formal restriction). Have another backup notebook within reach, to replace the main one when it runs out.</li>
  <li><strong>When</strong>: Make sure to always have your notebook and pen / pencil at your desk, meetings, conferences, 1:1s, and any environment where a collaboration is made, within reason.</li>
  <li><strong>What</strong>: Write down your thoughts, key points that coworkers communicate, ideas, anything else you find relevant. These are your notes, so allow yourself to expand and experiment.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Consolidate</strong></p>

<p>With several notes written, their consolidation can happen in three different time spans:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Immediately</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>The mere act of writing often helps the thought process, since it forces ethereal concepts to be materialized into paper. Expect that a good portion of the written notes to not be read ever again.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Shortly after they are written</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Keeping track of conversations: has it ever happened to you that suddenly you completely lost track of the discussion, especially a complex / ambiguous one? Refer back to the jotted down key points to quickly recall and connect points. Soon after you will be back on track, and maybe with new insights.</li>
      <li>Summarization of conversation segments, usually at the end of a meeting: leverage the written notes to summarize key takeaways and action points. There is nothing worse than spending 30 minutes in a discussion without material end results or follow ups.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Some time after notes are written</strong>: I avoid this period to be longer than one day.
    <ul>
      <li>Transcribe key points into a structured medium, such as a document, article, or personal log (I use a simple text file where I log important events during the day; this text file has been consistently updated for 4 years, and is a personal historical treasure trove spanning several thousands of lines).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>3. Repeat</strong></p>

<p>Just like other processes, their value only becomes apparent after they have been used several times. Build a habit. It will then become immediately apparent whenever a notebook is not at hand, or when structured notes are not written down.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diary of a CEO Book: Lessons]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/28/diary-of-ceo-book-lessons.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/28/diary-of-ceo-book-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently finished reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Diary-CEO-Laws-Business-Life/dp/0593715837">Diary of a CEO: 33 Laws of Business and Life</a>, which draws from both Steven Bartlett’s entrepreneurial journey and interviews from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@TheDiaryOfACEO">homonymous podcast</a>. These are are my main takeaways:</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="building-high-performance-groups">Building high performance groups</h2>

<h3 id="incentives-and-culture">Incentives and culture</h3>
<ul>
  <li>If you want to predict what a group of people will do over the long term, you need to look at their incentives, not their instructions.</li>
  <li>Companies don’t have one company culture: every manager in an organization creates a subculture underneath them.</li>
  <li>In a small group / startup, when the culture is strong, new joiners become like the culture. When the culture is weak, the culture becomes like the new joiners.</li>
  <li>In a small group / startup (and likely this can be applied to teams), create a cult-like dynamic upon its inception, but then transition it to a more sustainable structure. Key elements of a cult:
    <ul>
      <li>Provides meaning, purpose and belonging. Asserts superiority of the group.</li>
      <li>Clear shared identity and commitment to ideology.</li>
      <li>Leaders present themselves as infallible, confident and grandiose.</li>
      <li>“Us vs Them” mentality: there is a clear adversary.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="traits-of-a-good-leader">Traits of a good leader</h3>
<ul>
  <li>The factor that kills meaning the fastest is a leadership team that dismisses employee’s work or ideas, removes their sense of ownership and autonomy, and asks them to spend time on work that is cancelled, changed or disregarded before it’s been completed.</li>
  <li>Allow people the space to fail and succeed. The main job of a leader is to be a supportive enabler, not a critical micromanager.</li>
  <li>Leaders should proactively remove any obstacles, bureaucracy and sign-off processes that prevent the team to achieve daily progress, this includes identifying and providing the required resources for them to do their job. To discover these gaps, ask the teams informally or formally about these problems (via retros for example).</li>
  <li>Leaders need to point out, publicize and praise progress as loud, far and wide as they possibly can. Recognition reinforces behaviour, but it also acts as evidence to adjacent teams that progress is possible for them too.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Ferguson">Alex Ferguson</a>, the widely successful manager from Manchester United, didn’t care about tactics, strategies and formations. He cared about getting the best out of each individual, the team’s culture and attitude. He didn’t want them to be become complacent:
    <ul>
      <li>He had different ways of dealing with different players. He knew how to get the best out of everyone. He knew his players well, and what made them tick, like Gary Neville’s important connection with his grandparents.</li>
      <li>Some players strived under Ferguson’s “hairdryer” treatment, others under a more compassionate approach, and others by being more hands off. There was not a size fits all approach. The main objective was always to have the team and club at a higher ground.</li>
      <li>It is impossible to seamlessly blend into a team as a jigsaw piece, unless you comprehend the unique shape of each of your team members.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="ask-who-not-how">Ask who, not how</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Every CEO and founder will be judged on their ability to hire the best, and bind them into a culture that gets the best out of them. An environment where they become more than the sum of the parts.</li>
  <li>Your ego will insist that you do. Your potential will insist that you delegate.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="excise-bad-apples-promote-bar-raisers">Excise bad apples, promote bar raisers</h3>
<ul>
  <li><em>“The cost of one bad apple can be the loss of many good ones”</em> - CEO of General Electric
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2018/03/research-how-one-bad-employee-can-corrupt-a-whole-team">Study</a> found that employees were 37% more likely to commit misconduct at work when they encountered a new co-worker who had a history of misconduct themselves. Toxic employees really are contagious.</li>
      <li>When a bad apple isn’t fired, it can lead to employee disengagement, other employees copying the behaviour, social withdrawal, anxiety and fear. Culminating in the deterioration of trust in the team and further disengagement from its team members.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.rismedia.com/2024/02/01/thoughts-leadership-building-winning-team-with-3-bars-framework/">3 bars framework</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Ask yourself, or managers: “if everyone in the organization had the same cultural values, attitude, and level of talent as this employee, would the average bar be lowered, maintained, or raised?</li>
      <li>Fire the ones that lower the bar, promote the bar raisers.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wTgQ2PBiz-g">“(…) not settling for B and C players, but really going for the A players”</a>. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/8586131-it-doesn-t-make-sense-to-hire-smart-people-and-then">“It doesn’t make sense to hire smart people and tell them what to do; we hire smart people so they can tell us what to do”</a> - Steve Jobs</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="dealing-with-discomfort">Dealing with discomfort</h2>
<ul>
  <li>“Hard” is the price we pay today for an “easy” tomorrow.</li>
  <li>When you refuse to accept an uncomfortable truth, you’re choosing to accept an uncomfortable future.</li>
  <li>When something is unresolved because we’ve chosen to bury our heads in the sand, it doesn’t sit dormant, waiting to be addressed; it becomes toxic, contagious and poisonous to those around us, inflicting more collateral damage with every day that it remains unaddressed.</li>
  <li>When seeking the truth that is causing the discomfort, listen to understand, not to look for a victory, but rather in the perspective of a partner that wants to overcome that difficulty.</li>
  <li>In a relationship, if you’re having the same conversation over and over again, you are having the wrong conversations. You’re avoiding the uncomfortable conversation you should be having.</li>
  <li>It is in talking about our disconnections that people create more connectedness with one another.</li>
  <li>You can predict someone’s success in any area of their life by observing how willing and capable they are at dealing with uncomfortable conversations. Your personal progression is trapped behind an uncomfortable conversation.</li>
  <li>As mentioned by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism#Vaillant's_categorization">George Vaillant</a>, denial can be healthy, enabling individuals to cope with rather than become immobilized by anxiety, or it can be unhelpful, creating a self deception that alters reality in ways that can be dangerous.</li>
  <li><a href="(https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10225430-even-when-we-think-we-re-seeking-pleasure-we-re-actually-driven)"><em>“People think they’re motivated by seeking pleasure; they’re wrong, they’re motivated by avoiding discomfort”</em></a> - Nir Eyal</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="pressure-only-comes-to-those-who-earn-it">Pressure only comes to those who earn it</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.usopen.org/en_US/news/articles/2024-07-19/billie_jean_king_reveals_origin_of_iconic_quote_pressure_is_a_privilege.html"><em>“Pressure is a privilege, and champions adjust”</em></a> - Billy Jean King (BJK)</li>
  <li>Pressure is external, stress is internal.</li>
  <li>How you handle pressure and its resulting stress is essential, and makes a difference between positive and negative outcomes.</li>
  <li>Great pressure moments often precede great privileges.</li>
  <li>Life without pressure is a life without purpose.</li>
  <li>Pressure is neither good nor bad. It’s what we do with it that matters.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/kelly-mcgonigals-ted-talk-on-stress-2014-3#in-the-first-study-mcgonigal-looked-at-university-of-wisconsin-researchers-tracked-30000-american-adults-for-eight-years-they-found-that-subjects-with-a-lot-of-stress-had-a-43-increased-risk-of-dying--but-only-if-they-believed-stress-was-harmful-1">Kelly McGonigal</a> looked at a study made for 30k American adults, and noticed that people who experienced a lot of stress during their lives had 43% increased risk of dying, but this was only true for the ones who perceived stress as harmful. The ones that did not perceive it as harmful had the lowest risk of dying, even when compared to the ones who experienced relatively little stress.</li>
  <li>Objective is not to get rid of pressure, it’s to change your relationship with it altogether.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/7-it-is-not-the-critic-who-counts-not-the-man"><em>“It is not the critic who counts; not the man who points out how the strong man stumbles, or where the doer of deeds could have done them better. The credit belongs to the man who is actually in the arena, whose face is marred by dust and sweat and blood; who strives valiantly; who errs, who comes short again and again, because there is no effort without error and shortcoming; but who does actually strive to do the deeds; who knows great enthusiasms, the great devotions; who spends himself in a worthy cause; who at the best knows in the end the triumph of high achievement, and who at the worst, if he fails, at least fails while daring greatly, so that his place shall never be with those cold and timid souls who neither know victory nor defeat”</em></a> - Theodore Roosevelt</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="building-good-habits">Building good habits</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Instead of fighting against a bad habit, acknowledge the cue, routine, reward habit loop. When removing any of these elements, its void will need to be replaced. Replace rather than delete.</li>
  <li>Cues are powerful, since they are the starting points to routines. As such, be mindful of how you set up your environment. For example, Steven Bartlett placed his DJ set in the kitchen table, in plain sight, and made sure to take only one click to start practicing, in order to reduce perceived cost of practicing it. I’ve personally done the same thing with my camera setup to shoot <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@lopespm">YouTube videos</a>, by using a simple and predictable set up for video and microphone, which I have with highly visible in my living room, incentivizing me to do more videos.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="persistence">Persistence</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10644791-we-don-t-have-to-be-smarter-than-the-rest-we"><em>“We don’t have to be smarter than the rest. We have to be more disciplined than the rest.”</em></a> - Warren Buffett</li>
  <li>Katherine Milkman shared <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/plan-a-works-better-when-theres-no-plan-b-1471356000">research</a> that having a plan B, in any ambition, has a net negative on our chances of succeeding with a plan A.
    <ul>
      <li>The more you perceive negative emotions in the event of failure, the more driven you will be to succeed-</li>
      <li>But don’t be reckless. Take risks that don’t put you in irreversible and dangerous circumstances.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-jeffersoncc-introliterature/chapter/680/"><em>“If there be no alternative but death, the soldiers exert themselves to the utmost.”</em></a> - Sun Tzu, The Art of War</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="incremental-wins-keeping-momentum">Incremental wins, keeping momentum</h3>
<ul>
  <li>How much you are achieving is pretty much irrelevant to your motivation: but if you feel like you are getting somewhere, you’ll be driven to keep going.
    <ul>
      <li>When problems seem insurmountable or too hard or unknown, that’s when procrastination creeps in.</li>
      <li>The key here is to break down the problem into smaller, more manageable ones. The small resulting improvements and the sense of momentum will keep you going, and these will eventually compound.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="applying-time-and-energy-effectively">Applying time and energy effectively</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The exact same skill applied in a different industry or context can have a widely different value, as seen by a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/magazine/pearls-before-breakfast-can-one-of-the-nations-great-musicians-cut-through-the-fog-of-a-dc-rush-hour-lets-find-out/2014/09/23/8a6d46da-4331-11e4-b47c-f5889e061e5f_story.html">Washington Post experiment</a> where one of the world’s greatest violinists Joshua Bell, who was able to professionaly command $1,000 a minute, barely got any attention or spare change from playing in the subway.</li>
  <li>Position yourself correctly, and get the skills that your industry finds to be rare and valuable, and that your competitors don’t have.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="time">Time</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Time betting exercise
    <ul>
      <li>Imagine you, and everyone is sitting around the game of life. Each player is assigned a number of chips, each representing an hour. They don’t know how many they have. Maybe it’s one, maybe it’s 500k. You can try to predict, but you don’t really know.</li>
      <li>The rule is that every hour you need to put one chip on the table, or it will just be placed automatically. You can place it on Netflix, learning a new skill, sleeping, etc. Certain actions that increase your health will increase your stock of chips.</li>
      <li>Your fitness will block you from betting on certain positions. For example, if you have a serious locomotion injury, you cannot choose to run.</li>
      <li>The game ends when all chips are gone. You don’t get to keep anything you earned during the game.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Being selective about how you spend your time, and who you spend your time with, is the greatest sign of self respect.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="failure-as-an-advantage">Failure as an advantage</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Ask the questions: Why will this fail? Why is this a bad idea?</li>
  <li>Apply the pre-mortem process to visualize and attempt to preempt failures in your plan. This will mitigate risk and likely increase your prediction accuracy.
    <ul>
      <li>A <a href="https://hbr.org/2007/09/performing-a-project-premortem">1989 study</a> found that prospective hindsight—imagining that an event has already occurred—increases the ability to correctly identify reasons for future outcomes by 30%.</li>
      <li>Steven Bartlett’s pre-mortem method:
        <ul>
          <li>Set the stage: the objective of the exercises. It is to uncover risks, not to look for escape goats.</li>
          <li>Fast forward to failure. Ask team to visualize failure as clearly as possible.</li>
          <li>Brainstorm reasons for failure.</li>
          <li>Ideate independently, and then share and discuss.</li>
          <li>Develop contingency plans.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Share experiment failures, so that their knowledge can be leveraged when building new experiments.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/acref/9780191826719.001.0001/q-oro-ed4-00003960"><em>“I have not failed, I have just found 10k ways that won’t work”</em></a> - Thomas Edison</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling seen]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/21/feeling-seen.html"/>
    <updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/12/21/feeling-seen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Being seen ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p1.webp" aria-label="Being seen ad">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p1.png" aria-label="Being seen ad">
             <img src="/files/feeling_seen/p1.png" aria-label="Being seen ad">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>This ad struck me as the culmination of a long-standing trend. I struggled to articulate it at the time, but I’ll attempt to do just that in this article.</p>

<p>Let’s start by the ad itself. It carries implicit symbols and memes, whose interpretations will vary wildly from person to person, but in general I believe it attempts to convey these subtle messages:</p>

<ol>
  <li>In order to be seen and acknowledged as an individual, one must spark admiration and rise above the crowd with a stylish look, makeup and fashionable garments. Appearance <em>is</em> the solution.</li>
  <li>Feeling seen is about exterior validation (which requires the advertised beauty products), rather than real understanding and connection with another being.</li>
  <li>You need to command the attention of acquaintances and strangers, their judgement is important for your self worth.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
</ol>

<!--more-->

<p>Relying only on external validation, specially from foreign entities, as a means to sustain one’s self-esteem is a time honored strategy to produce nefarious results. Yet, it’s celebrated by certain influencers, mainstream media, TV shows, ads and movies that attempt to distort a small sample into a normality.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p5.webp" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p5.png" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad">
             <img src="/files/feeling_seen/p5.png" aria-label="Lasting more than your last relationship ad">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="demanding-standards">Demanding Standards</h1>

<p>When external validation is postulated as a basic human need, and one’s default natural, vanilla body is not sufficient to garner the validation one needs (as the above ad suggests), it soon follows that external interventions are required to achieve it.</p>

<p>I was fortunate enough to grow in an environment where artificial external displays of vanity were seen as a quirk, and sometimes even frowned upon (depending on the situation), thus not a requirement for a happy and fulfilled life. But once one is born or dislodged into the eye of a hurricane, it is hard to see the surrounding damage, especially when peers abide by those standards, generating an underlying group integration peer pressure.</p>

<h2 id="hazardous-trends">Hazardous trends</h2>

<p>Several off-the-shelf beauty products are known for their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rObAX1r8r0s">toxicity</a>, contributing to increased prevalence of cancer and infertility, yet they stand as one of the cornerstones of modern standards of beauty.</p>

<p>How we show up is important, and is a meaningful way of self expression, but when the baseline for allowing one’s self expression requires one to consume / apply several products (sometimes on the go), or even subject to invasive body modifications, then I would argue that something is wrong in the underlying societal system.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p3.webp" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p3.png" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad">
             <img src="/files/feeling_seen/p3.png" aria-label="Makeup in the tube ad">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="mind-the-ouch">Mind the ouch</h3>

<p>One such body modification, turned mainstream, is the injection of botox.</p>

<p>Botulism is an often-fatal nervous system disease, first recorded in Europe in 1793, claiming the death of over half of those patients who had become ill through eating uncooked blood sausages. <em>botulus</em> being the Latin word for sausage. One one-millionth of a gram this neurotoxic protein can kill a man, and one pint would be enough to kill everyone on earth.</p>

<p>In 1989, purified botulinum toxin was approved as a drug under the brand name Oculinum, and later renamed to <em>Botox</em>. In small doses, the same nerve damage that causes fatal paralysis in poisoning cases, helps to remove forehead creases and crow’s feet, with the only side effects being an inability to express emotion using your face, and an occasional case of drooping eyelids.</p>

<p>Today, injecting the deadliest substance on earth into one’s face is normalized, as seen in this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uSjIfBNwvYw">TV commercial</a> (where its mid-commercial disclaimers makes one question if it’s a real ad, or a parody<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>), or as seen in this suggestive London tube ad:</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Mind the ouch ad">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p2.webp" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/feeling_seen/p2.png" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad">
             <img src="/files/feeling_seen/p2.png" aria-label="Mind the ouch ad">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p><br /></p>

<h1 id="look-within">Look Within</h1>

<p>I hold nothing against those who choose to subscribe to a certain mode of expression or style. I too, have my own. I do welcome you to introspect <em>why</em> you chose it. If your sincere <em>why</em> comes from a deep rooted desire to feel accepted and valued by others (good to receive these in healthy dosages, but dangerous when overbearing), then it might be something to look out for.</p>

<p>Relying <em>solely</em> on external validation likely results in feelings of emptiness and insatisfaction. I’ve been there several times, and its not pleasant. Instead, attempt to obtain self validation by looking in, rather than out. <a href="](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LzHmifZo5Jk)">Some simple, yet powerful strategies</a>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Consider your ancestors, a stable past. For example, what would your ancestors eat, do, that worked out for their health? Our bodies have adapted throughout milenia to certain patterns, and if we are on their descendancy line, surely they did <em>something</em> right. Time is the great filter of nonsense and fallacies.</li>
  <li>Recognize the cycle: ask yourself why you are seeking external validation, and understand the patterns and needs that lead to it.</li>
  <li>Practice self-appreciation: build your self-acceptance structure, practice gratefulness and appreciation for what you are and did (a journal might help).</li>
  <li>Rejection therapy: put yourself in situations you seek rejection. Start small, such as asking for a discount or applying for a job you think you are not qualified for. It helps you realise that rejection is not as bad as it appears, which decreases the need for other’s validations.</li>
  <li><a href="/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html#an-example">Set personal goals</a>: instead of relying on others to measure against, take control, and set goals that serve your needs and desires. Keep yourself accountable to hit them.</li>
  <li>Listen to your intuition: you know yourself best, so why rely on others for answers? Reach within and take distraction free time to listen to yourself.</li>
  <li>Self care to self validate: do activities that make you feel good, use self affirming thoughts, take care of yourself.</li>
</ol>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>Why: friends, family and close connections likely already acknowledge you by who you really are, or at least should. Why would they need you to wear a beauty product in order for you to feel seen? Therefore the remaining target audience are acquaintances and strangers</em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Transcript from the TV commercial: <em>(…) FDA approved to temporarily make frown lines crow’s feet and forehead lines look better. The effects of Botox Cosmetic may spread hours to weeks after injection causing serious symptoms alert your doctor right away as difficulty swallowing, speaking, breathing, eye problems, or muscle weakness may be a sign of a life-threatening condition. Do not receive Botox Cosmetic if you have a skin infection. Side effects may include allergic reactions, injection site pain, headache, eyebrow, eyelid drooping and eyelid swelling. Tell your doctor about your medical history muscle or nerve conditions and medications including botulinum toxins, as these may increase the risk of serious side effects. So get that “just saw a puppy look”! (…)</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
