<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-09-30T19:56:26+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://lopespm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importance of Goal Clarity for Delegation]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/09/30/goal_clarity_in_delegation.html"/>
    <updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/09/30/goal_clarity_in_delegation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Previously, in <a href="/2022/03/22/learnings-software-engineer-techlead.html">“Learnings as a Software Engineer Techlead”</a>, I’ve alluded to the 75/25 rule, where if you are ~75% certain that someone will correctly execute a given project/task, then delegate. The other ~25% is the unknown space that the person needs in order to learn, explore, make errors, innovate and grow.</p>

<p>If the project/task was decided to be delegated, What comes next?</p>

<h2 id="clarity-of-goals">Clarity of Goals</h2>

<p>One common challenge I’ve confronted when delegating was how unpredictable and uncontrollable the results felt upon handing over the work. This unstructured approach often left me thinking how I could decrease the non-completion risk by diminishing the delegated scope, and created confusion on the delegatee side on how they could proceed.</p>

<p>One tidbit of information from the “Who not How” book provided the guidance and structure to unlock this issue:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>(…) research has found that teams who have high levels of autonomy but low clarity goals, as well as little performance feedback, perform worse than teams with low autonomy.</p>

  <p><em>― <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Who-Not-How-Accelerating-Teamwork-ebook/dp/B0867ZJ151">Who not How, by Dan Sullivan with Dr. Benjamin Hardy</a></em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is claimed in the above research that teams which have high autonomy, high goal clarity and regular feedback on their results, were observed to have their performance shooting through the roof.</p>

<p>Apart from regular feedback, goal clarity is incredibly important, and even though it might sound obvious, it can be overlooked and drowned out on the process of delegation.</p>

<h2 id="clarity-in-practice">Clarity, in Practice</h2>

<p>After the above realization, I’ve made it a priority for each piece of delegated work to clearly define what was expected as an outcome, its definition of done, important milestones and deadlines, when should an issue be scaled to me, and which are the ownerships for each of the participants.</p>

<p>All of the above communicated in a clear and concise way, and preferably publicly documented to increase accountability and decrease ambiguity (depending on the situation, merely communicating these verbally might be enough, especially if the task is simple).</p>

<h2 id="the-delegation-formula">The Delegation Formula</h2>

<p>Given the above, the proposed formula for delegation is:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">Delegation = [ 75/25 \text{ } rule \rightarrow Goal \text{ } Clarity + Autonomy +Regular \text{ } Feedback ]</script>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life has several exits]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/19/life_exits.html"/>
    <updated>2023-08-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/19/life_exits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Life has several exits:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The exit from your workplace. The last day of work for your employer or your company.</li>
  <li>The exit from that youth group that accompanied you through teenage years and early adulthood.</li>
  <li>The exit from your high-school.</li>
  <li>The exit from your hometown.</li>
  <li>The exit from a long term relationship.</li>
  <li>The exit from life. Your funeral.</li>
</ul>

<p>Upon your exit, your contributions, actions, decisions, opinions and presence most likely will have affected the trajectories of the people and the world around you, in obvious and less obvious ways. Perhaps your own trajectory was deeply changed as well.</p>

<p>These exits may be celebrated, be a special day with fulfilling words and thoughts. They may be the last time you see a set of people. The last time you will see them in your entire life.</p>

<p>Perhaps upon your final exit, you have made such consequential dents on the world that your name will be engraved into the annals of history for centuries to come. On the other hand, contemporary personalities such Steve Jobs, Bill Gates, Elon Musk and Warren Buffet might be mostly forgotten a few centuries from now. People will move on, so most likely you should be grateful if your loved ones keep you in their thoughts for those ensuing decades.</p>

<p>Life has several exits. Life is also short and limited. There’ll be a finite number of exits you will experience. Make the most out of each period they enclose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The real question behind 'what do you want?']]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want.html"/>
    <updated>2023-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/08/05/real_question_behind_what_you_want</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s easy to want something. If you are fortunate enough to be on <a href="https://www.gapminder.org/fw/income-levels/income-level-4/">income level 4</a> living in a peaceful nation, the world has so much to offer, within easy reach. Yet, the currencies required to enjoy them are limited: time, energy, health, money. Even though it is easy to make lists of everything one wants (typically occurring on yearly passages, such as new year’s and anniversaries), only a handful of them are achievable.</p>

<h2 id="smaller-lists-require-sacrifices">Smaller lists require sacrifices</h2>
<p>Given that lengthy lists are unachievable, they need to be slimmed down to a manageable and realistic size. They need to be prioritized. <em>Prioritization</em> is an euphemism for <em>sacrificing</em>.</p>

<p>It’s easy to want something, it’s hard to choose it against another desirable one.</p>

<h2 id="an-example">An example</h2>

<p>At the start of each year, I produce a small list of 3 to 4 high priority goals and 1 optional low priority goal of what I want to achieve by end of it, along with a small description on why I want them, and their impact. This takes several hours, sometimes days to put together, because of all the other ones that need to be left out.</p>

<p>Once the list is made though, it’s incredibly powerful due to it’s easy recall. This means that whenever I am faced with conflicting preferences, I can easily remember it and know in a snap what is the right thing to do. That is the real power behind that list. It’s guiding all the tiny small steps and decisions happening throughout the year, bringing me progressivily closer to those goals.</p>

<h2 id="the-question">The question</h2>
<p>The real question behind defining <em>knowing what we want</em> is actually <em>what we are willing to sacrifice</em>. Once the latter is defined and we are 100% convinced about it, then <em>knowing what we want</em> is bullet proof and easy to follow through. </p>

<p>What are you willing to sacrifice?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing as a form of thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking.html"/>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Large language models (LLM) like ChatGPT triggered a remarkable societal and computational shift that feels comparable to the impact from the initial internet era with its first impressive search engines like Google. LLMs are the toast of the town.</p>

<p>Writing emails, reports, school homework, analysis, code, summaries. The list goes on.</p>

<p>Save from when you would delegate this task to another fellow human, long hours would be passed in the past trying to conjure a piece of text that could communicate something to another entity. Now this can be made at scale, at low cost, with low effort.</p>

<p>Since we are still liable for the results of this tool, i.e. it’s still our name on the email sender, instead of just sending that email, we might first read that LLM output, interpret it, understand it, and then send it.</p>

<h2 id="more-than-just-text">More than just text</h2>

<p>Text is a form of communication. If something, or someone wrote it for us, certain decisions were made along the way to convey the goal that we gave. Out of the many paths possible to crystallize that piece of knowledge into a piece text, one of them was chosen.</p>

<p>I would claim that something gets lost on that delegation.</p>

<p>The writing process is more than just the production of text. Many times it requires the exploration of different perspectives, thinking deeply and coming to terms that we don’t know enough about a subject and need to learn more about it.</p>

<p>For example, it’s essential for me to have a notebook at hand to take notes during meetings and formal discussions. I write phrases, loose words, make small diagrams, jot down some reminders. Some of them are never to be re-read again, others I revisit to structure them down into a concise structure. Most of all, they help me think about a problem.</p>

<p>Same holds for notes and articles. I start with a cloud of loosely related ideas, which I attempt to refine into a structured form. Similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_Diamond_(design_process_model)">double diamond</a> process.</p>

<p>Same for books. Several times I’ve come to terms that I learned close to nothing about a book read one month before. Or conversations. Or movies. Or experiences.</p>

<p>This is, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=otazg3TuPWM">except</a> if I reflected or acted about them. Except if I wrote down my conclusions about them.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For me, taking notes helps make sure that I’m really thinking hard about what’s in there. If I disagree with the book, sometimes it takes a long time to read the books because I’m writing so much in the margin</p>

  <p><em>― <a href="https://youtu.be/eTFy8RnUkoU?t=11">Bill Gates</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Custom Pomodoro Technique]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/custom-pomodoro-technique.html"/>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/custom-pomodoro-technique</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Time is the most valuable thing a man can spend.</p>

  <p><em>― Theophrastus</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are countless articles, books, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aXvDEmo6uS4">videos</a> and lectures about time management. Since all of us have different needs, goals and environments, it is best to face them as guidances, where we take the ones we need, and leave the others in our toolbelt for another time.</p>

<p>One of these methodologies is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">Pomodoro Technique</a>, in which a kitchen timer is used to break work into intervals, typically 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks. </p>

<p>This doesn’t work for me, so here is my <em>Custom Pomodoro Technique</em>.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-works">How it works</h2>

<p>I usually need long bouts of deep focus during my work or any complex tasks. This can be reading / writing code, aligning with partners, structuring plans, going through my finances, etc. 25 minutes is typically not enough, since it coincides with where most of my flow peaks happen.</p>

<p>One hour is my target for continuous focused work. Below that, I know that I can still take advantage of the remaining time to productively go through a problem. Above that, I start to prepare to wind down and take a break.</p>

<p>Rule of thumb for breaks are to be enough to feel rested, which tends to happen in less than 15 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>

<p>I’ve tried several tools to track time. Physical and digital. Complex and simple. One has stuck for several years, and is the only one I use right now: <a href="https://www.klokki.com/">Klokki</a></p>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p>Klokki is a concise Mac application that tracks time and generates nice time reports. It also allows you to track your time automatically, but I don’t use that feature.</p>

<p>This is a wonderful tool that fulfills my main requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Being able to start and stop the timer with a single click.</li>
  <li>The timer should be always visible, but also non-obtrusive.</li>
  <li>Simple usage, with a low UI footprint. No distractions.</li>
  <li>Concise time reports, which allow me to know how much time (and energy) I’ve used throughout the week. This is important for pacing calibration.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-rules">The rules</h2>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Whenever I sit down at the computer and start working, I start the timer. <em>I converged into using a single category to track all my deep flow blocks, since having multiple categories created too much mental overhead</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Whenever the timer is on, I’m in productivity / work mode, and no distractions outside my goals are allowed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Refrain from stopping the flow session before the one hour mark. Start preparing to stop the flow session after the 1 hour mark.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take breaks in-between flow sessions, until I feel rested. Normally less than 15 minutes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When the timer is off, scattered tasks, exploration and wandering are allowed and encouraged.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<h2 id="the-benefits">The benefits</h2>

<p>This is an incredibly simple methodology that I’ve been using throughout the past years. The recurrent benefits I’ve captured from it were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Clear boundaries between focus time and exploration.</li>
  <li>Simple, easy to follow process, allowing for flexibility on how time blocks are managed. Easy to consistently abide by.</li>
  <li>Pacing: prevents over-working or under-utilization of my energy / time.</li>
</ul>

<p>Feel free to use this guidance / methodology and experiment with it, Or not 🙏</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
