<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-23T20:58:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://lopespm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing as a form of thinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking.html"/>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/writing-as-a-form-of-thinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Large language models (LLM) like ChatGPT triggered a remarkable societal and computational shift that feels comparable to the impact from the initial internet era with its first impressive search engines like Google. LLMs are the toast of the town.</p>

<p>Writing emails, reports, school homework, analysis, code, summaries. The list goes on.</p>

<p>Save from when you would delegate this task to another fellow human, long hours would be passed in the past trying to conjure a piece of text that could communicate something to another entity. Now this can be made at scale, at low cost, with low effort.</p>

<p>Since we are still liable for the results of this tool, i.e. it’s still our name on the email sender, instead of just sending that email, we might first read that LLM output, interpret it, understand it, and then send it.</p>

<h2 id="more-than-just-text">More than just text</h2>

<p>Text is a form of communication. If something, or someone wrote it for us, certain decisions were made along the way to convey the goal that we gave. Out of the many paths possible to crystallize that piece of knowledge into a piece text, one of them was chosen.</p>

<p>I would claim that something gets lost on that delegation.</p>

<p>The writing process is more than just the production of text. Many times it requires the exploration of different perspectives, thinking deeply and coming to terms that we don’t know enough about a subject and need to learn more about it.</p>

<p>For example, it’s essential for me to have a notebook at hand to take notes during meetings and formal discussions. I write phrases, loose words, make small diagrams, jot down some reminders. Some of them are never to be re-read again, others I revisit to structure them down into a concise structure. Most of all, they help me think about a problem.</p>

<p>Same holds for notes and articles. I start with a cloud of loosely related ideas, which I attempt to refine into a structured form. Similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_Diamond_(design_process_model)">double diamond</a> process.</p>

<p>Same for books. Several times I’ve come to terms that I learned close to nothing about a book read one month before. Or conversations. Or movies. Or experiences.</p>

<p>This is, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=otazg3TuPWM">except</a> if I reflected or acted about them. Except if I wrote down my conclusions about them.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For me, taking notes helps make sure that I’m really thinking hard about what’s in there. If I disagree with the book, sometimes it takes a long time to read the books because I’m writing so much in the margin</p>

  <p><em>― <a href="https://youtu.be/eTFy8RnUkoU?t=11">Bill Gates</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Custom Pomodoro Technique]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/custom-pomodoro-technique.html"/>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/07/02/custom-pomodoro-technique</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Time is the most valuable thing a man can spend.</p>

  <p><em>― Theophrastus</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are countless articles, books, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aXvDEmo6uS4">videos</a> and lectures about time management. Since all of us have different needs, goals and environments, it is best to face them as guidances, where we take the ones we need, and leave the others in our toolbelt for another time.</p>

<p>One of these methodologies is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">Pomodoro Technique</a>, in which a kitchen timer is used to break work into intervals, typically 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks. </p>

<p>This doesn’t work for me, so here is my <em>Custom Pomodoro Technique</em>.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-works">How it works</h2>

<p>I usually need long bouts of deep focus during my work or any complex tasks. This can be reading / writing code, aligning with partners, structuring plans, going through my finances, etc. 25 minutes is typically not enough, since it coincides with where most of my flow peaks happen.</p>

<p>One hour is my target for continuous focused work. Below that, I know that I can still take advantage of the remaining time to productively go through a problem. Above that, I start to prepare to wind down and take a break.</p>

<p>Rule of thumb for breaks are to be enough to feel rested, which tends to happen in less than 15 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>

<p>I’ve tried several tools to track time. Physical and digital. Complex and simple. One has stuck for several years, and is the only one I use right now: <a href="https://www.klokki.com/">Klokki</a></p>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_full_dialog.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<p>Klokki is a concise Mac application that tracks time and generates nice time reports. It also allows you to track your time automatically, but I don’t use that feature.</p>

<p>This is a wonderful tool that fulfills my main requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Being able to start and stop the timer with a single click.</li>
  <li>The timer should be always visible, but also non-obtrusive.</li>
  <li>Simple usage, with a low UI footprint. No distractions.</li>
  <li>Concise time reports, which allow me to know how much time (and energy) I’ve used throughout the week. This is important for pacing calibration.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-rules">The rules</h2>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_on_1_minute.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Whenever I sit down at the computer and start working, I start the timer. <em>I converged into using a single category to track all my deep flow blocks, since having multiple categories created too much mental overhead</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Whenever the timer is on, I’m in productivity / work mode, and no distractions outside my goals are allowed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Refrain from stopping the flow session before the one hour mark. Start preparing to stop the flow session after the 1 hour mark.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take breaks in-between flow sessions, until I feel rested. Normally less than 15 minutes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When the timer is off, scattered tasks, exploration and wandering are allowed and encouraged.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><center>
          <picture>
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.webp">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.png">
             <img src="/files/custom_pomodoro/timer_off.png">
           </picture>
         </center></p>

<h2 id="the-benefits">The benefits</h2>

<p>This is an incredibly simple methodology that I’ve been using throughout the past years. The recurrent benefits I’ve captured from it were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Clear boundaries between focus time and exploration.</li>
  <li>Simple, easy to follow process, allowing for flexibility on how time blocks are managed. Easy to consistently abide by.</li>
  <li>Pacing: prevents over-working or under-utilization of my energy / time.</li>
</ul>

<p>Feel free to use this guidance / methodology and experiment with it, Or not 🙏</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solving task switching through documentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/05/18/solving-task-switching-through-documentation.html"/>
    <updated>2023-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/05/18/solving-task-switching-through-documentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We don’t actually multitask. We switch-task, rapidly shifting from one thing to another, interrupting ourselves unproductively, and losing time in the process <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. It just so happens that many aspects of our life require managing multiple tasks at the same time, so how to approach it?</p>

<p>One strategy that consistently worked for me has been using documentation to checkpoint each step of a process. Just like in a videogame where the last saved checkpoint can be recalled.</p>

<h2 id="the-backtracking-inefficiency">The Backtracking Inefficiency</h2>

<p>Similar to a CPU, our short-term memory (STM) has access to a limited amount (around four or seven concepts have been suggested <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>) of very quick memory. Everytime we change to a different task, most of the resident concepts need to be flushed in order to load the ones from the incoming task. This is quite taxing by itself and narrowly optimizable, since our wetware is mostly fixed. The biggest efficiency opportunities lie in <em>where</em> these concepts are loaded from.</p>

<p>When working on a task, often we grab several simultaneous concepts, combine them together and generate new ones, which are then added to the concept pool and built upon further. During this process we are faced with these options:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Option 1.</strong> Don’t store our working memory - essentially lose work. Let’s rule out this option.</li>
  <li><strong>Option 2.</strong> Progressively store the existing concepts into our long term memory.</li>
  <li><strong>Option 3.</strong> Progressively store the existing concepts into an external memory bank, such as a document or piece of paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Option 2.</strong> works well, but requires significant cognitive effort and often only keeps the most relevant conclusions. If for some reason these need to be re-considered or understood why they were generated in the first place, we backtrack into the seminal thought processes, which in turn will probably require a repetition of previous work.</p>

<p>This is one of the biggest offenders when task switching, because even if we recall the end state of a task (which is hard by itself), a lot of time and energy are spent when revisiting the overall context via backtracking.</p>

<h2 id="documentation-as-checkpoint-mechanism">Documentation as Checkpoint Mechanism</h2>

<p>Enter <strong>Option 3.</strong>: <em>Progressively store these existing concepts into an external memory bank, such as a document or piece of paper.</em> Although writing in an external memory bank the contents of our working memory can take some effort, the yielded results greatly justify the initial investment:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Less cognitive load upon re-starting a task</li>
  <li>Backtracking effort is reduced, since it is a matter of reading a document</li>
  <li>Shareable with other stakeholders, which shaves off the time required to explain these concepts</li>
  <li>Task switching becomes smoother and less burdensome</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="parting-thoughts">Parting Thoughts</h2>

<ul>
  <li>The documentation’s structure significantly impacts how efficiently it can be parsed and shared. That is a whole new topic by itself.</li>
  <li>Documentation as a checkpointing mechanism is a great way to consolidate personal learnings and reflections. It’s a valuable tool for leveraging life’s experiences to mature and grow. <em><strong>Option 1.</strong> is such a waste.</em></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Bregman, <a href="https://hbr.org/2010/05/how-and-why-to-stop-multitaski">How (and Why) to Stop Multitasking</a><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3425965/">About the Distinction between Working Memory and Short-Term Memory</a><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The case for not having a TV]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/05/04/the-case-for-not-having-tv.html"/>
    <updated>2023-05-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/05/04/the-case-for-not-having-tv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Listen to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@DavidSinclairPodcast">David Sinclair</a> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@hubermanlab">Andrew Hubberman</a> on how to extend lifespan or improve health markers, and a common trait emerges: the body strives and improves when exposed to just enough stress and struggle. Not too much, though. Cold baths, saunas, fasting, exercise, red light (which disrupts the way that our mitochondria make energy), eating <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DO8FJ8i02Xo">stressed greens</a>, are examples of just that.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if you spend your whole day sitting, or typing, always satisfying your hunger, your AMPK and mTOR pathways (which are master regulators of cell metabolism) and sirtuins say: <em>“Hey, times are good. Let’s just grow tissue, go forth, multiply and not build a sustainable body in the long run.”</em></p>

<p>The idolized unhurdled, stable and comfortable life, the easy access to resources and high caloric food, can do more harm than good when left unattended.</p>

<h2 id="the-riveting-third-person">The riveting third person</h2>

<p>I’ve consumed gargantuous amounts of television throughout my youth, so I’ve grown familiar with it’s charming alure. In an almost frictionless experience, where it suffices to lean back and pick one of the channels or series/movies/documentaries readily suggested by a streaming provider, an experience is entered where carefully crafted packages and passionate stories are delivered to us, requiring only our attention. It can even serve as the <em>third-person</em> to liven up the room, when in a tedious moment with a loved one.</p>

<p>No real struggle, no real effort required. A passive experience. The body rejoices in it, like it does when ingesting a sugar packed sweet. Just like most, I enjoy that feeling. Just like most, I have a limited amount of willpower. Hence why I don’t have a TV at home. Neither do I have sweets.</p>

<p>I love it. I don’t love the fact that I’m blocking myself away from those satisfactions. No, I relish the long term results. The time it opens up to actively read, write (this post for example), create, think, be present with others, and even watch podcasts (of which I make an effort to pick an episode outside the normal recommendations). I’m not perfect, and the above serves as a rule for me. And rules do have exceptions, and that’s ok. </p>

<p>Still, this is the case for not having a TV.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The First Note]]></title>
    <link href="http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/04/07/first-note.html"/>
    <updated>2023-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lopespm.github.io/notes/2023/04/07/first-note</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <em>Notes</em>!</p>

<p>This is a new space where you will be able to find essays, notes and other quick thoughts, whereas the existing <em>Blog</em> section will remain allocated to denser article pieces.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<h3 id="the-recurrent-idea">The Recurrent Idea</h3>

<p>I have a rule when buying non-essential items for my house: if I’ve been recurrently thinking about buying something over a span of multiple days, then it’s a good purchasing signal. The thought process for writing articles for this blog is similar.</p>

<p>The downside of this approach is that the ideas and thoughts that don’t make it to a blog article are relegated into the realm of personal writings and/or conversations with others, but never exposed to the public. On the other hand, this very same thirst to share quick thoughts was recurrent by itself.</p>

<h3 id="framing">Framing</h3>

<p>The yearning towards developing this concept was there, but a satisfactory hosting plaform was missing still:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Twitter: although it allowed for volume and looser thoughts, the character restriction would limit the exploration of a topic, and all the content would not be owned by me.</li>
  <li>New self-hosted space: this allowed me to own the contents and have a clear separation between dense blog articles and quick thoughts, but the maintenance cost was prohibitive.</li>
</ul>

<p>The third option was to host them here, in <em>Byte Tank</em>, which was customized over several years and already had the workflow and components I strived for. But how to frame this new concept into the existing structure?</p>

<p>The answer came from <a href="https://notes.alinpanaitiu.com/How%20I%20write%20this%20blog%20on%20my%20iPhone%20in%20a%20train">Alin Panaitiu</a>. On his website, Alin has a separate section for <em>Notes</em>, which makes perfect sense to me. <em>Notes</em> sets the expectation that they are not fully fledged articles, and that they cater towards volume, rather than density.</p>

<h3 id="making-it-a-reality">Making it a reality</h3>

<p>An idea is only worth for its implementation, and these were the last nudges that incentivized me to bring it to life:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The inspiring examples presented in several of the comments in <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35164819">Ask HN: What has your personal website/blog done for you?</a>. One of them being a reference to <a href="https://www.benkuhn.net/writing/">Why and how to write things on the Internet</a>, the other one being Alin’s website (see above).</li>
  <li>The spirit of the earlier Internet. I remember the earlier times of the Internet where there was this widespread fascination with the fact that with a telephone connection, one could have access to its immense world, and had the possibility to create their own virtual home, that anyone could visit. That is one of the many beauties of this massive network. Low cost, virtually no gatekeepers, nearly boundless. I find this idea incredibly exciting and empowering.</li>
  <li>Even in an era where text content is now produced for a low cost and in massive amounts (GPT and other LLMs), I believe there is still space for <em>artisanal</em> human baked opinions. The human relatableness, its connection with the environment, biology and even its limitations are still charming on their own.</li>
  <li>The incentive to create notes in volume could be a great way to generate more source material that can be coalesced into new blog articles</li>
  <li>Exposing looser thoughts publicly forces me to structure then, and I believe this process can make me better equipped to navigate the complex universe of human interactions, in which having a more structured mindset can make a world of a difference. Personally and professionally.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="going-forward">Going Forward</h2>

<p>This is an exciting new phase for this modest establishment, and I’m looking forward to populating this section with new content. Until then!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
