<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes | Byte Tank]]></title>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://lopespm.com/"/>
  <updated>2024-06-24T21:10:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://lopespm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro Lopes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aloof]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/06/09/aloof.html"/>
    <updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/06/09/aloof</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="einsteins-rambles">Einstein’s rambles</h2>

<p>I’ve been listening to the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Einstein-Life-Universe-Walter-Isaacson/dp/1847390544">“Einstein: His Life and Universe”</a> audiobook, from Walter Isaacson, which recounts a series of curious stories of how he carried himself through his life.</p>

<p>Einstein was often known to be aloof and lost in this thoughts, so much so that when sailing his clunky 15-foot sailboat named Tinef (Yiddish for “worthless” or “junk”), he often found himself to being rescued more than once by locals near to his rented a summer cottage overlooking Cutchogue Harbor.</p>

<p>Another delightful story was when he lived in Princeton, where occasionally, he would take rambling walks on his own. One day, called into the Institute for Advanced Study, where he worked, and asked to speak to a particular dean. When the secretary said that the dean wasn’t available, he hesitantly asked for Einstein’s home address. That was not possible to give out, he was informed. His voice then dropped to a whisper. “Please don’t tell anybody,” he said, “but I am Dr. Einstein, I’m on my way home, and I’ve forgotten where my house is.”</p>

<h2 id="thinking-in-safety">Thinking, in safety</h2>

<p>Over the past years, I’ve made a habit of having at least one long walk / hike every weekend. I take immense joy - if I happen to go by myself and I’m not actively listening to an audio book or am concentrating on some task - to just wander around and immerse myself in random thoughts, think about hard problems, strategise, and attempt to arrive at sound conclusions. This mental wandering, almost like a meditation, I am sure that happens for most of us, in several instances. Maybe when waking up, during the shower, during a walk, during a boring talk, when contemplating art or nature, etc.</p>

<p>Since we are not omniscient and omnipresent, we have several limitations in knowing how a given action will translate into a set of consequences, so we use probabilistic models and heuristics in our thought processes to discern which are the most likely actions that will help us arrive at a desirable outcome. And the more relevant information and time we have to process our thoughts, the better our results will be.</p>

<p>In all of these, I believe there is one common denominator that is fundamental for that process to happen: safety.</p>

<h2 id="the-influence-of-ones-environment">The influence of one’s environment</h2>

<p>Let’s assume you live with access to information and resources (food, money, shelter, etc), but are living in a situation where your surrounding environment requires you to keep alert and attentive to hazard to your physical / mental wellbeing, or you are in a situation where your social stability is dependent on incapacitating amounts of your energy and time. This could be due to living in a dangerous neighborhood, having overly demanding peers, an abusive household, etc.</p>

<p>Even though there might be a series of limited actions one could take to improve their situation, the constant fight-or-flight severely restricts the opportunities where these action plans can be considered, which eventually leads to reactive actions that could have a number of possible outcomes (good or bad), rather than surgical long term actions that would pave the path towards positive outcomes.</p>

<h2 id="the-takeaway">The takeaway</h2>

<p>While many many situations are not under our control, such as our initial conditions, birth place, etc, which place a default upper bound on any possible outcomes, we do have agency over some parts of our life, and that is what we can focus on. The path to unwanted consequences is a slippery slope made of several small decisions, some under our control, others not. But for the ones we have the opportunity to control, we should.</p>

<p>For example, the peers one <em>choses</em> to have around, the <em>choice</em> to avoid short term pleasures that have a high long term cost, the <em>choice</em> of which country or neighborhood to live in, the <em>choice</em> of which job offer to strive for, etc.</p>

<p>Do notice that the italics are intentional. The <em>choices</em> above assume that those are options you have under your control to pick, which I am conscious that is not always the case.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let me tell you a story]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/05/05/let-me-tell-you-a-story.html"/>
    <updated>2024-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/05/05/let-me-tell-you-a-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>You could never convince a monkey to give you a banana by promising him limitless bananas after death in monkey heaven. How do you cause people to believe in an imagined order such as Christianity, democracy or capitalism? First, you never admit that the order is imagined.</p>

  <p><em>― Yuval Noah Harari</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Take a minute to think of what a nation is. Let’s say the United States of America. What makes someone American? Is it their physique, genetic traits, family lineage, pheromones? No, it’s a concept in their head, which stems from a mix of identity, ideology, personal gains from abiding to that concept (say, gaining currency via a job or a company, that allows you to acquire things you desire), perceived protection and support from peers because they believe you are commonly aligned on core beliefs / concepts.</p>

<p>The same can be said of a company. A company is not a physical being, it’s a shared idea in our imagination. As Yuval mentions in <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Sapiens-Humankind-Yuval-Noah-Harari/dp/0099590085">Sapiens</a>, Peugeot does not really exist, except in our minds. It doesn’t have a body, mind, anything. We have the common belief that Peugeot exists, because we also have the common belief of what a company means, we are aligned on how it should be represented and who can represent it, we recognize it as an entity with rights and duties, and which laws it should abide by.</p>

<p>Laws, as well, are worth nothing if only one person believes in them. They are powerful because a large group of people believe in them, and they expect others to do so as well. That’s why we have courts, prisons, and educational systems for that matter. They are ways to punish, format, and incentivise for the entire group to have the required level of consistency, and keep rowing in the same direction.</p>

<p>That’s why complete anarchy loses its edge on a large scale. It extinguishes the biggest thing Humans have going for them: the ability for large numbers of people to rally in common goals, even though they don’t personally know most of their fellow believers.</p>

<p>As N. K. Humphrey suggests, these ideas, behaviors, or styles that spread by means of imitation from person to person within a culture, also known as memes, could even be considered as living structures, not just metaphorically. The generational propagation of a meme outweighs the lifespan of the Human who created it, so in a way, <em>“we are living inside the dreams of dead people”</em>, as Yuval puts it.</p>

<p>That being said, how do we align on a common concept or belief?</p>

<h2 id="stories">Stories</h2>

<p>We’ve seen above how powerful and valuable having a broad range of concepts aligned within a group of people. They bring value to the whole, but also to the individual.</p>

<p>You can force someone to abide to a given concept via force (coercion, blackmailing, etc), but since they see little value going on for them, they don’t have the incentive to grow that concept inside them, or to propagate that concept to others</p>

<p>Stories however, allow you to describe a world to others that they can interpret in their head, and they can see by themselves how it would benefit them, and the ones around them. It’s an information passage mechanism that allows Humans to communicate and agree on a given concept, and they are everywhere:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Children’s bedtime stories - notice how several of these transmit moral values, this is, expectations of how one should behave in a given situation, in order to be in alignment with the overall group / society</li>
  <li>Novels, biographies, movies</li>
  <li>When interviewees tell you a story of their childhood, how they created their company, how they achieved X, what happened during their struggles, etc</li>
  <li>When a leader, such as a CEO, convinces others of their vision / story, and that future prospects that would derive from working in a certain direction</li>
  <li>When meeting someone, when you talk about your background and your goals</li>
  <li>When you sell you employee skills to an employers, giving a summary of your professional trajectory</li>
  <li>When politicians portray their vision on how they want to improve their nation</li>
  <li>The lore of a nation, tribe, family, and their laws / duties / rights</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="being-a-good-storyteller-is-a-powerful-skill">Being a good storyteller is a powerful skill</h3>

<p>As a species, one of our biggest distinguishing factors is that we are able to goal on highly abstract concepts that only exist in our minds, such as the concept of a company, a nation, a mission, an ideology, an intellectual relationship, the concept of money. As Yuval puts it, <em>“We are the only species with the ability to use language—not just to describe things we can see, taste, and touch, but also to invent stories about things that don’t exist.”</em></p>

<p>A magical thing happens when a group of people interpret and value that concept in the same way, and are highly aligned on it. Narrative is the first and most crucial step for leaders who want to solve big problems and shape the world for the better. After all, a person can have the greatest idea in the world, but if they fail to rally others to make that idea come alive, nothing gets done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Banishing mobile phones from bedroom]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom.html"/>
    <updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-problem--why">The Problem / Why</h2>

<p>When <a href="https://youtu.be/K2tGt2XWd9Q?si=h-xh-X90JWxwF1KU&amp;t=2229">asked</a> about which practices supported Chris Williamson into his current position, Chris mentioned that sleeping with his phone outside of the bedroom and getting a plain alarm clock was his number one change.</p>

<p>I found that statement interesting, especially because I had grown a habit of seeing the occasional video before sleep and being engaged with random distractions shortly after waking up.</p>

<p>Overriding these behaviors required a good amount of self discipline and willpower to be overridden, and fundamentally deviated my focus from what I would want to accomplish on a given day, from the book I had been putting off, or to simply wind down.</p>

<h2 id="alternative-alarm-and-note-taking">Alternative Alarm and Note Taking</h2>

<p>Even though my phone sponsored my distractions, it was also my trusty alarm and favorite way to write down notes and reflections that crossed my mind outside my work desk. So to make the leap of keeping my mobile phone at the bedroom door, I would need to replace the alarm clock, and find a new way to write down my notes.</p>

<h3 id="alarm">Alarm</h3>

<p>This seems like an easy step, but it turns out the selection of alarms is immense, and many of them either do too much, or don’t tick all the boxes.</p>

<p>Essentially, I needed a trustworthy, low maintenance, alarm with essential functionalities that would not flood my dark bedroom with blue light when I wanted to check the time during night.</p>

<p>I essentially browsed through:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.lumie.com/">Lumie alarms</a>: had the enticing proposition of science-backed approach of waking up via warm light or soothing sounds, but didn’t have the basic functionality of having recurrent alarms on the models I was interested in, and required a mains connection, meaning that upon a power outage it could only support itself for a limited amount of time.</li>
  <li>White brand alarm clocks: the selection is immense on <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/s?k=alarm+clock">Amazon</a>, and even though they come in at relatively cheap prices, some require a mains connection, or have short battery life, or need to be recharged every so often, or do too much (like having a bluetooth connection) or use noisy clock dials.</li>
</ul>

<p>After several searches, I’ve stumbled upon Braun alarm clocks. These have been around for decades, and I recalled that Steve Jobs was inspired more than once by products made by Braun when creating his Apple products, due to Braun’s thoughtful approach on how everyday products were designed.</p>

<p>I’ve settled with the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Braun-Digital-Compact-Negative-Crescendo/dp/B083KMCHRH">Braun BC08B</a>. No moving parts, a single AAA battery apparently lasts more than half a year, small, simple, easy to operate, and the beeping sound is not brain drilling. The one aspect I am not fully satisfied is its screen light, which when activated is too strong on a dark bedroom (my mobile phone far excels in this aspect, due to its less intrusive always on black and white display).</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="Braun BC08B">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.webp" aria-label="Braun BC08B">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.png" aria-label="Braun BC08B">
             <img src="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/alarm_braun.png" aria-label="Braun BC08B">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h3 id="note-taking">Note Taking</h3>

<p>These were the alternatives I found for writing down notes, and jotting down diagrams (as a plus):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Physical Notebook:
    <ul>
      <li>Pros: Easy to use, low cost, no distractions, low maintenance (no battery to recharge, software updates, etc)</li>
      <li>Cons: My handwriting is appalling and my character output is much lower when compared to typing; extra step needed to transfer it a digital means; harder to organize</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>E-Ink Devices:
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://remarkable.com/">Remarkable 2</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: well thought out, clean and focus driven, great writing experience; allows for handwriting to text conversion</li>
          <li>Cons: Able to connect to a Google Drive for free, but works storage rather than syncing, so it is cumbersome to iterate on notes and diagrams between it and other devices</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://supernote.com/">Supernote</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: clean and focus driven, great writing experience; allows for handwriting to text conversion; open <a href="https://trello.com/b/l0COP24j/supernote-a5-x-a6-x-nomad-software-roadmap-2024">roadmap</a> and ideology; easy repair and upgrade</li>
          <li>Cons: As with Remarkable, it does not provide real file syncing, but file copy to Google Drive</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Kindle-Scribe-the-first-Kindle-for-reading-writing-journaling-and-sketching/dp/B09BS26B8B">Kindle Scribe</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: Writing experience seems to be good and on-device handwriting recognition to convert notes into actual text</li>
          <li>Cons: No Google Play apps, meaning that Google Keep and Google Docs would not be available, and no Google Drive sync; the device caters more to readers, rather than writers in my opinion</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/BOOX-Tablet-Note-Air3-ePaper/dp/B0CP3CGG8P">Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W</a>:
        <ul>
          <li>Pros: it can use Google Keep and Google Docs apps, since can do almost everything a normal Android table can, but since it uses a e-ink screen and has limited processing capabilities, it does not make a good fit for browsing the web or seeing videos (which is actually a good thing); the default experience and drawing app are bloated offer too many distractions (<a href="/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html">see here how to debloat it</a>); allows for handwriting to text conversion within Onyx drawing app</li>
          <li>Cons: noticeable lag when writing; if not using Onyx’s cloud, it requires extra steps to export and share a diagram / drawing</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.apple.com/uk/ipad-pro/">iPad Pro</a>: even though this device is amazing, it made it too easy to access the same distractions I was trying to avoid, and it also sports an invasive backlit screen that provides too much stimulus while in bed. A hard no.</li>
</ul>

<p>Given the options above, I picked the Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W. Note that the <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/BOOX-Tablet-Note-Air-ePaper-Dark-grey-green/dp/B0CHF423CP">color screen version of this tablet</a> is available, but I did not pick it because of Air C’s reduced battery life from the always-on BSR (Boox Super Refresh Technology). BSR allows for a smoother and more responsive experience when writing for example, but that is not actually a problem since I mainly use the Boox to write long streams of text / braindumps, rather than text editing; and BSR also takes it a step closer to a general purpose tablet non-eink display, which starts to defeat the initial purpose. Apart from that, I have a personal preference towards the black and white screen feel.</p>

<p>Learn more on how I customized my Boox Air3 <a href="/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html">here</a>.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <img src="/files/banish_mobiles_bedroom/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2>

<p>I have now transitioned to not having any mobile phones in my bedroom, and only having the Boox Air 3, the Braun alarm clock, physical books and my Kindle. I am pretty satisfied with this change, which I’ve noticed to provide more focus time after waking up, more time to think, plan my day, reflect, write my thoughts, read, and wind down.</p>

<p>The most fundamental aspect was having more time to focus on my plan for the day, which translated into a substantial improvement on how productive and consequential my days have become. I welcome anyone to give it a try!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W Setup]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox.html"/>
    <updated>2024-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/03/25/minimalist_boox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the <a href="/notes/2024/04/01/banishing_mobile_phones_from_bedroom.html">plan to banish mobile phones with access to instant rewards from my bedroom</a>, I’ve acquired a Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, which is a Android tablet with a black and white e-ink screen that is focused on writing and reading <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="house-rules">House Rules</h2>

<p>First of all, <em>why</em> I did get the device in the first place? This was in order to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reduce distractions before going to sleep and after waking up, increase focus on the things that really mattered, block out all other noise, and make it really hard to have access to instant gratification and rewards (such as video consumption)</li>
  <li>Register any ideas and thoughts that occur to me before and after going to sleep, which is one of my most proficuous times for such, and then have them available on other devices</li>
</ul>

<p><em>How</em> to achieve this using the BOOX:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Only two functionalities should be easy and quick to use:
    <ul>
      <li>Write text and notes (via Google Keep and Google Docs)</li>
      <li>Write diagrams and mental maps (via the device’s main app, which has the snappiest performance)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Getting to above functionalities should be as fast as possible, and they should be fast</li>
  <li>The cost to get to other apps and functionalities should be high</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="focusing--debloating">Focusing &amp; Debloating</h2>

<p>The Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W is not an incredibly fast device, and comes with several functionalities, apps, and a launcher that increase the distraction degree, and also slow down the device.</p>

<h3 id="google-play-google-keep--docs">Google Play, Google Keep &amp; Docs</h3>

<p>The first step towards the objective above was to install Google Play (see <a href="https://help.boox.com/hc/en-us/articles/8569260963732-Google-Play-Store">guide here</a>, and afterwards installed these apps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Google Keep</li>
  <li>Google Docs</li>
  <li>Android Hidden Settings - this app provides access to several hidden settings, that allow the access of settings such as enabling the Developer Options in Android (useful in the debloating process described below)</li>
  <li>Lawnchair (see below)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="new-launcher-lawnchair">New Launcher: Lawnchair</h3>

<center>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"><div class="video-wrapper-two">
   <center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_before.png" aria-label="How the home screen looks like now">
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>Before:</b> Default BOOX Launcher <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> </p>
</div>
<div class="video-media-caption-wrapper-two"> <div class="video-wrapper-two">
	<center>
          <picture aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.webp" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/home_screen_after.png" aria-label="How the home screen looked like before">
           </picture>
         </center></div>
 <p class="media-caption media-caption-two"><b>After:</b> Using Lawnchair Launcher<br class="video-br-end" /></p>
</div>
</center>

<p>The default device’s launcher was replaced by <a href="https://lawnchair.app/">Lawnchair</a>, which is a lightweight, open-source, highly customizable launcher for Android.</p>

<p>What was added to the Lawnchair’s home screen:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Keep</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Docs</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Onyx Launcher - for any custom changes that are only accessible on the device’s default launcher, which are are in practice, so this was eventually something I removed from the home screen as I wrote this note</li>
  <li>Shortcut to Google Calendar - to add any events or reminders</li>
  <li>A widget to Onyx Sketch app, which is one the only way I found to have that app directly accessible from the Lawnchair home screen, without having to use Onyx’s launcher to do so. The widget can be added by long pressing on the home screen, then select “Widgets”, and then on the “ContentBrowser” section select one of the “Notes” widgets</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="disabling-bloatware">Disabling bloatware</h3>

<p>With all of the above in place, we could start disabling non-essential apps and services, to prevent them from running in the background.</p>

<p>Here are the steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The first step is to enable “Developer Options”, by accessing the system settings via the “Android Hidden Settings” app above, and then finding the <a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/debug/dev-options">Build Number</a> in order to click it enough times to eventually enable “Developer Options”.</li>
  <li>Connect the BOOX to the computer</li>
  <li>On the computer’s terminal run the below commands</li>
</ol>

<p>In general, these are the commands one can run via the terminal to manage bloat apps:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>// See all packages
$ adb shell pm list packages

// See all disabled packages
$ adb shell pm list packages -d

// Disable a package
$ adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 &lt;package_to_disable&gt;

// Re-enable a package
$ adb shell pm enable &lt;package_to_disable&gt;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br />
And these are the specific ones I used in my BOOX to disable bloatware, without any relevant side effects for my usages:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.appmarket
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.floatingbutton
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.dict
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.mail
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.igetshop
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.easytransfer
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.kime
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.android.ksync
adb shell pm disable-user --user 0 com.onyx.calculator
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The commands above should be enough to remove all bloatware, and if you wish to learn more, <a href="https://www.kaspersky.co.uk/blog/how-to-disable-and-remove-android-bloatware/26993/">this article</a> and <a href="https://digitaluncoded.com/cpu-usage-android">this article</a> provide a good overview.</p>

<h2 id="using-an-external-keyboard">Using an external keyboard</h2>

<p>Given that this device is meant to be used in bed, and since it is quite unwieldy to write on the on-screen display, I was looking for an external keyboard that could be somehow attached to the BOOX, that would bestable, low-maintenance and allowed for flexibility on the writing position.</p>

<p>From the keyboards and keyboard stands I’ve researched, the most elegant solution I found was to use <a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-gb/products/keyboards/k480-multi-device-wireless.html">Logitech K480</a>, a bluetooth keyboard with an in-built cradle, detachable batteries (i.e. zero issues related internal battery becoming faulty), incredible battery span (some users reported this to be <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EoH2bXoNEE0">in the order of years</a>), and wonderful typing experience.</p>

<p>One caveat is that the BOOX slides backward and falls when using the cradle without any other aid. A very simple fix is to get a piece of cardboard, and place it behind the BOOX (see picture below) to create a better fit. It works remarkably well.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/keyboard_k480_with_boox.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h2 id="writing-and-drawing">Writing and Drawing</h2>

<h3 id="writing">Writing</h3>

<p>Writing is my main use case for the device, and even though it has some lag when doing it, it works great for me, because I tend to write long streams of ranting text, rather than editing it.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="bYENTrabzXw" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The best mode I’ve found for writing was the “A2” Mode. It has ghosting, but is responsive enough for this use case.</p>

<p><center>
          <picture aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/webp" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.webp" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <source type="image/png" srcset="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
             <img src="/files/minimalist_boox/configuration_for_writing.png" aria-label="BOOX attached to Logitech K480 cradle, with and added piece of cardboard">
           </picture>
         </center>
<br /></p>

<h3 id="drawing">Drawing</h3>

<p>To draw, I use the default Onyx’s Sketch app due to its responsiveness, even though I would have preferred to have a more customizable UI interface and faster ways to share the drawing.</p>

<p>Sharing is one of the downsides of the Onyx Sketch app. You need to either use their cloud service, or export the image in order to get the sketch easily accessible on other devices. I’ve opted to use the export functionality, which allows to directly share the image to a Google Keep note, which fits well into my workflow. I would prefer to not have this extra step, but still, it works well enough.</p>

<div>
	<div class="youtube-player" data-id="iW3IZ9MnFL8" data-thumbsize="1"></div>
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>This has been one of the most satisfying devices I’ve added to my routines, and it’s incredibly satisfying to write on this device, almost distraction free. It allows enough customizability for it to be tailored to my use case, but is also limited enough to deter me from falling prey to distractions.</p>

<p>I hope this was useful towards your journey - do let me know your tips for distraction free environments!</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">

  <ol>
	<li id="fn:1">
  	<p>The BOOX Note Air3 B/W is a very capable device, able to do most of the things one would expect from an Android Tablet, but its screen refresh rate, speed and screen drag make it less suited for fast browsing and video usage for example. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
	<li id="fn:2">
  	<p>The screenshot is from BOOX Tablet Note Air 3 C, the color counterpart of Onyx BOOX Note Air3 B/W, but the layout is the same, save from the color display <a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">↩</a></p>
	</li>
    
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Musk's biography: why it's interesting]]></title>
    <link href="https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography.html"/>
    <updated>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://lopespm.com/notes/2024/02/18/elon_musk_biography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been hearing the <a href="https://amzn.to/3I97bBi">latest Elon Musk biography</a> <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> on audiobook, and just like Ashlee Vance’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3I5hUNu">book</a><sup>1</sup>, I’m finding it incredibly interesting. Here’s why:</p>

<h2 id="possibilities-monty-python-costs-whys-and-whos">Possibilities, Monty Python, costs, whys and whos</h2>

<h3 id="the-action-on-potential">The action on potential</h3>

<p>I find his path inspiring. It makes me want to create and do things, and shows that many things that are thought to be impossible, are actually achievable. There is a whole realm of opportunities waiting to be grabbed, and his life demonstrates just that.</p>

<p>There is a cost though. If it were that easy, everyone would do it.</p>

<h3 id="the-defining-characteristics">The defining characteristics</h3>

<p>The book goes deeper into the unique aspects that allow Musk to be an extreme overachiever, but also the personal and professional costs those same aspects inflict.</p>

<p>Musk’s capacity to take pain, risk, stress and adversity is staggering. I’ve been reading several biographies over the past years and met quite a few people throughout my life. I can only find a handful of them that are even comparable.</p>

<p>The relentless pursuit, sometimes maniacal, of product quality, functional and non-wasteful design, and effective manufacturing. All in the name of a greater objective, larger than any single human being or corporation.</p>

<h3 id="the-relationships">The relationships</h3>

<p>The book dives into the relationships that shaped Musk (for the better, for the worse, or both), the types of relationships he consistently attracted (which resonated with his personality and upbringing), and essential relationships that allowed him and his projects to thrive.</p>

<p>They come to further prove that no man or woman is an island. You can’t succeed by your own.</p>

<h3 id="the-humor">The humor</h3>

<p>Consistently throughout Musk’s life, there is a balance between dark and light, between lighthearted comedy and downright hell.</p>

<p>I’ve had a good laugh with some of the humorous sides though, such as when <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=grA5XmBRC6g">eels and hovercrafts</a> were catered to one of his marriages, or when Blue Origin filed a formal protest against SpaceX to prevent the company from having exclusive use of a NASA launchpad, to which Musk <a href="https://spacenews.com/37389musk-calls-out-blue-origin-ula-for-phony-blocking-tactic-on-shuttle-pad/">replied</a> that <em>“if they do somehow show up in the next  5 years with a vehicle qualified to NASA’s human rating standards that can dock with the Space Station, which is what Pad 39A is meant to do, we will gladly accommodate their needs. Frankly, I think we are more likely to discover unicorns dancing in the flame duct.”</em></p>

<p>Shortly after, a SpaceX employee bought dozens of inflatable unicorns and took a picture of them standing in a flame duct 🦄</p>

<h2 id="musks-algorithm">Musk’s algorithm</h2>

<p><em>“The Algorithm”</em>, is a distillation of lessons learned while relentlessly increasing production capacity, which Musk repeatedly preached on his enterprises:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Question every requirement</li>
  <li>Delete any part of the process you can</li>
  <li>Simplify and optimize</li>
  <li>Accelerate cycle time</li>
  <li>Automate</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="questioning-requirements">1. Questioning requirements</h3>

<p>It can be summarized into this: <em>“The only rules are the ones dictated by the laws of physics. Everything else is a recommendation.”</em>. It’s a recurrent theme.</p>

<p>Doesn’t come without a cost though: it is often associated with conflict and chaos.</p>

<h3 id="about-2-delete-any-part-of-the-process-you-can">About 2. Delete any part of the process you can</h3>

<p><em>“Delete, delete, delete”</em></p>

<p>Optimization many times goes hand in hand with deletion. Deleting is hard. It requires letting go of past achievements, comfort, and acceptance that something is not coming back. Almost like a breakup.</p>

<h3 id="simplify-and-optimize">3. Simplify and optimize</h3>

<p>Goes hand in hand with deletion.</p>

<h3 id="accelerate-cycle-time">4. Accelerate cycle time</h3>

<p>This is where intensity and being “hard core” are most leveraged, in my view. Again, with their pros and cons.</p>

<h3 id="automate">5. Automate</h3>

<p>A more obvious one. Put a machine to do it. Easier said than done though.</p>

<h2 id="data-points---cause--effect-probabilities">Data points -&gt; cause &amp; effect probabilities</h2>

<p>I’m fond of biographies because they provide several data points that I can later use in my life. This is, which set of actions preceded a given consequence. Of course the context matters, and surely no same action will lead to the same consequence, specially if made by different people.</p>

<p>But patterns start to emerge, and their respective probabilities. These help me solidify my own personal theories and strategies. Learning from others is important. It allows for “shortcuts” similar to the ones provided by good mentors.</p>

<p>To build these, I need data points, a lot of them.</p>

<p>That is why I like Isaacson’s biographies so much <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This is this third book I read (or hear) from Walter Isaacson, and one of the things I enjoy most about his writing is how deep he goes into the details of someone’s story. I believe that details are important when portraying someone’s life. Sometimes, the smallest of events make an immense difference over someone’s path.</p>

<h2 id="just-read--hear-it">Just read / hear it</h2>

<p>Love him, or hate him, I recommend Musk’s biography to just about anyone.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>This link is an affiliate link, and as an Amazon Associate I earn from qualifying purchases whose commissions help this small establishment, <u>at no additional cost to you</u></em><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>Except <a href="https://amzn.to/48m3D9u">Steve Jobs Biography</a> <sup>1</sup>, which I could not bear to finish. Jobs personality was a bit too much for me to handle</em><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
